≫ MIRIAM: All right.
Yeah. We're going to be talking
about the origins of the
web, but especially design on
the web using
CHSS, cascading HTML style
sheets proposed
by Hokum Lee in 1994. This is
still archived online. You can
read it. I recommend it.
It's fascinating, the original
design of the language.
But this wasn't the only
proposal for design on the web.
And it wasn't the first
It was actually based on
several existing proposals like
the one built into the Viola
browser, or this easily
parsable format where I have
no idea what's going
on, equals 14, I don't know.
But CSS solved a major problem
for this new platform. Not a
technical problem exactly, but
a
philosophical problem,
political, like all of the
decisions
we make when we're designing a
new platform or interface.
The first web browser,
developed by CERN,
called the hyperbrowser www.
editor was developed for the
fancy machine for this graphic
interface , but you can't make
a worldwide web by saying
it works on my machine and
everyone else is a edge case.
They hired Nicola Pello to
design, it's text only, you
don't have to install it. Any
device with an internet
connection can log into the
CERN servers and browse the
web. This becomes the mission
statement.
Web for all, web on everything.
And everything is a lot of
things.
There's so many different
things that the web is on. And
that includes devices without
any screen or
visual display at all as well
as screen readers, which do
read the screen.
So are sort of a combination of
interfaces .
If we really want this to work,
web for all web on everything,
then we get some interesting
constraints.
And these are documented on the
first website, the HTML
documentation that was launched
around 1991.
And is also still online. You
can go read that, as well.
And it says browsers should
ignore tags, which they do not
understand and ignore
attributes which they do not
understand of tags which they
do.
So browsers should ignore tags
they don't understand, so you
can see here, hopefully, in
this
code I've inserted a lot of
tags that aren't real
. They're fake tags, I made
them up and the browser's
ignoring them and displays the
tags it understands and
displays the content inside of
those tags . Also ignoring
attributes I made up.
That's become very useful as we
start doing web components and
custom attributes. This was
planned from the beginning.
The goal is to protect content
over code. The code is
optional, the content is
essential.
Whatever else happens, browsers
should protect the content.
And that's why we can still see
this first website on modern
browsers.
And we can also load modern
browsers, modern websites on
the first browser. This is an
emulator you can go play with
of the www. Browser. You don't
see -- sorry, that's a lot of
noise. You don't see CSS in
images, but all the text is
there. You can see via
international symposium
website, and my cascading style
systems workshop website, they
load fine. And the content is
preserved.
This limitation becomes even
more dramatic for graphic
design. In order for HTML to be
a common language between all
platforms
, we can't have any
device-specific markup
or anything which requires
control over fonts and colors.
That's in the original
documentation web design
will never happen, at least in
the graphic sense.
And the problem isn't styling
documents online, that's easy
enough and all of the early
browsers provided internal
style sheets, even the text
-only browser, you can see it
has all caps headings and space
between paragraphs .
So there's styles happening
here, but the styles are
provided by the browser, so
there's this same across all
websites, they depend what
browser you're using.
And this is fundamentally
different from print design.
Right? Where we get to describe
everything about our page.
In fact, we describe the page
itself. How big is it?
And then, it stays that size
forever. It's static. So we can
export to a PDF or a JPEG or
send it to the printer and what
we get back is exactly what we
designed.
And you can click on it all you
want, nothing's going to
happen. It just sits there.
The same was true for other
digital formats at the time .
Postscript had been around for
almost a decade . That's the
basis of PDFs, which came
slight , I think around the
same time. It's a page
description language. So like
print, we describe a static
page, how big is it? Where does
each thing go? And we set the
fonts and colors, et cetera.
We get all of the control in
those systems, but that control
comes at a cost. The page,
print or PDF is a static medium
. It can't adapt a context or
preferences.
And that's a limitation of the
medium. Go read John Elsop
's style of web design from
2000, it's still relevant . I
won't wait.
Web styles have to be
different. They have to be
contextual. Even static sites
aren't static.
What we ship is not always what
our audience sees
. So styles must adapt to all
of the different situations
where they might show up
because the web is responsive
to context. And that's a
political vision from the
beginning.
Not just the width of the
viewport, but user needs
and preferences, device
interfaces, and changing
capabilities over time. In
other words, we're not alone.
We're part of an ecosystem here
and our decisions impact other
people. We don't get final say.
We're collaborating with the
browsers who are
instructed to ignore us when we
go off the rails.
And we're also collaborating
with the people who interact
with our sites
on their chosen devices with
varying capabilities , with a
browser that they choose, and
wearing
these handy little tool belts
that I think are very cute. And
we're probably also
collaborating with aliens,
maybe, who knows, if they're
around, we should collaborate
with them. They're just trying
to get home.
The CHSS proposal is
explicitly designed around this
collaboration. That's how the
document starts
. This proposal tries to soften
the tension between the author
and the reader.
It's specifically for that.
And, if conflicts arise, the
user should have the last word.
And that is built into the
cascade itself.
It's the first step of the
cascade is that the user styles
can override the author styles
when it's important from step
one, origins important, when
the user
marks sometime important, they
take priority over everything.
That's the purpose of
importance.
It's not for us to get into
petty
squabbles, but to maintain
balance in the universe and
give power back to the...  I
don't know...
rebel users, I don't know.
Analogies are hard.
A Jedi uses importance for
knowledge for defense, never
for attack. This also becomes a
core W3C principle.
If a tradeoff needs to be made
in the design of the platform
itself, always put user needs
above all.
So under these sort of absurd
constraints,
design seemed almost impossible
on the web
. If we want this political
vision, how are we going to
control fonts and colors, for
example, we can't
.
But nobody was happy with that
outcome.
When every site looks the same,
that's not just boring for
people who are trying to brand
their product, it's kind of
boring for everybody. People
like design.
The turning point came in 1993
when
Mosaic added the image tag to
HTML. This was before web
standards, web styles were
suddenly possible
through the image tag.
You could just throw everything
into an image.
And then, when it breaks,
there's no content to protect.
This fundamentally breaks
everything that was special
about the political
vision of HTML. If it doesn't
load, it's just lost. This was
a real risk to the platform.
The web could've become a giant
fax machine where pictures
of text would be passed along.
So there's a real race
between 1993 and 1994, a rush
of different proposals trying
to figure out how are we going
to get styles on the web is
that that don't
break what makes the web
special?
I recommend checking out a
bunch of these. They're really
fascinating. But all of them
talk about this problem.
Allow the authors, that's us,
building the web.
To attach style hints. Styles,
not rules, but hints and
suggestions.
This phrase shows up over and
over in many of the proposals.
Provide hints that the browser
may or may not use. Again,
we're drawing from HTML's rules
there.
A set of hints or suggestions
to the renderer, which might be
used .
In Hokum's proposal, authors
and publishers have stylistic
influence without resorting to
page description languages.
That's called out specifically.
We're not giving us full
control. Only the ability to
provide some
influence.
And this uses the same
resilient logic as HTML
. And we can see that, again,
did I leave that tab open?
I did not. Let's go back to it.
In CSS, I've done the same
thing. Calling colors that
don't exist.
Oh, my I must have -- that
became content.
I'm using colors that don't
exist.
I'm useing entire declarations
that don't exist.
Selectors that don't exist.
Everything can just
be ignored and it's fine.
That's how CSS is designed. We
can be ignored.
And this is the reason that the
default overflow is visible.
If we get cocky and make a box
too small for our text,
browsers will try to bail us
out. Not because it's the
best-looking solution, but
because the web will
try to protect content whenever
it can, browsers are helping us
out here.
This is another design
principle of the W3C.
Content should be viewable and
accessible by default. And the
browser ensures that's the case
unless
we go in and mess it up.
Indesign doesn't have to worry
about
this. Accidental overflow can
be found and fixed before we
hit publish or after
we get a proof and fix it.
And then, once it's fixed, it
stays the way we designed it.
It's not going to change.
It's not going to move. But
we're doing graphic design of
unknown
content with unknown
collaborators on an infinite
and unknowable canvas across
operating systems, interfaces,
languages, writing modes.
It's absurd what we're trying
to do here. What this language
is trying to accomplish.
I don't know any other tool
that is trying to do this in
design.
There are too many variables to
consider. The point of CSS is
to make it so we don't
have to worry about all of
them.
We have We hand some of that
over to the browser, that's why
CSS is a declarative language.
We literally write our hints as
declarations of property and
value.
And some of those can seem like
simple concepts, the width of a
box, 500
pixels, some are more abstract.
Wrapping text so it looks
pretty, whatever that means.
Even the concepts that
seem simple, hide a deeper
complexity. Should the box be
smaller on a higher resolution?
What do we mean by a pixel?
And how does the unit respond
to zooming in or out?
And are we talking about the
width of the content where the
padding and border are
additional to that width?
Or the width of the whole box
with the borders and padding?
There's not one universal
answer.
It depends on what we're doing.
And maybe we really don't want
the width at all, we're
thinking about the in line
size. The size available to a
line of text.
Or maybe we should be sizing
the box based
on its contents, the min size
or max size.
Or the size of a character in
the font we're using, or
based on context, parent
element, viewport, container,
some combination of those, the
minimum of two values.
Everything in CSS is based on
this constant back and forth,
context pushing in, defining
the
space variable, and content
pushing out, taking up space,
and
we're trying to make those two
always work together.
How do we ensure that our
content will fit
any container that we put it
in? We can't. We don't have all
of that information.
We don't know but the browser
does have that information.
So if we want this power, we
have to give up some control .
The most useful parts
of CSS express this kind of
abstract behavior, letting the
browser work out the details.
If we can avoid touching it, we
should.
The browser knows more than we
do. So, we're using an
expressive language, not
describing the page in step by
step de
tail, but expressing high-level
concepts. Our job is poetic,
providing subtext
for the browser, no the just
the resulting style, but the
purpose of a style choice. And
units are great for this.
And it's why CSS has so many
units because they help convey
this meaning and intent.
So, 1em and 16 pixels may in
some cases by default look the
same.
But they have very different
meanings.
They adapt differently in
different context.
So our job is not to make it
look good on my device.
But to make sure it adapts to
different contexts as needed.
Adapting to unexpected changes
in the
context. Similar with layout
methods.
Flex and grid can give us the
same result in a static
setting. But they move
differently. They behave
differently.
It's useful to learn both
because they're going to
act differently in different
contexts.
Even when we can get the same
result, they have different
meanings, and that's worth
paying attention to.
We're trying to express more
meaning with fewer constraints.
Expressing our intent clearly
using hints and suggestions for
the browser.
So, to me, this meme, the CSS
is awesome box breaking meme.
It actually perfectly captures
what is awesome about
CSS and how much can go wrong
when we try to control things
that
we shouldn't necessarily
control. When we add too many
constraints at once.
So how can we loosen our grip
on this?
There are several things we can
do.
We could change
the -- we could remove the
width and height constraints .
And oh, we could keep that font
size.
Let's see. Yeah, we could --
the height's not going to do
much in this case,
but the width there, that's
going to help.
We could even say the min width
is min content and otherwise,
we leave the max height and
width.
We could change this to
overflow, wrap break word. We
could play with hyphens, or we
could, yeah, if we're going to
break word there, we want to
get rid of the max height. We
could decide if we want the
height to move or the width to
move.
We can change overflow to clip
or scroll.
Get all sorts of different ways
that we can mess with this box.
I mean, I think the most fun is
just, there we go . CSS is rad.
That fits perfectly in our box.
Yeah, so I love that meme for
the wrong reasons.
To avoid harm, we don't want to
describe a static
page but express a design
vision through hints and
suggestions, help the browser
understand the constraints that
are important for our de sign.
So that when things change,
browsers can adapt
to -- can adapt our design to
those changes.
We're designing systems, in
facts I would say cascade
ing style sheet is a designing
system, it's a set of guides
for maintaining cohesive design
across a variety of contexts.
It's the kind of design system
that a browser can read and do
something with.
To avoid harm, we use a light
touch. We define the outer
boundaries, the constraints of
our design, rather than every
little detail.
We provide hints that help the
browser understand our goals
that let the browser take care
of the details.
This is our job as designers,
design engineers, whatever we
want to call ourselves.
Everything else in CSS is built
around this political vision to
protect the content, protect
the
user, and our first
responsibility is not to break
that .
Thanks.