I'm Ivan. This will probably
lean on the more like
history/theory
of the talks today, but super
excited to chat about this.
So my kind of fascination and
love for Chinese type recently
came about when I was traveling
in Taiwan.
And if you're a fan of this
creature, there's
a 7-eleven in Taiwan that sells
it.
I was enamored by this juxta
position of the Chinese type
VER
because it reflects the
personality. And I've been
fascinated in thinking how do
we balance these kind of
systems together today?
And so, yeah, a little bit
about me, I'm Ivan, I make
websites, animations, comics,
but I'm
fascinated in this whole world
of how do we make weird things
on the internet ? And how do we
communicate and create tools
and infrastructure to do so?
If you've ever taken a history
of graphic design or anyone
's talked to you about type
design, there's a very a famous
book in the mid 15th Century
called the
Gutenberg bible that everyone
likes to look and pontificate
upon. Look at the scripture,
think about the black
lettering. I'm here to tell you
that, you should completely get
rid of
the Gutenberg bible, and in the
famous book Patricia Lockwood's
nobody's talking about Chinese
writing system. The history of
printing ascends back into 11th
century China with this worker,
commoner
named Bichon Hu who created one
of the first examples of print
making .
So in Chinese history, there
are four notable kind of
inventions and print making is
one of them made in the 11th
century. This is an old bank
statement.
Made at the time using one
immovable type . And one of the
things interesting about this,
if you look at kind of the
entirety of the Chinese history
and sort
of Chinese writing system, it
compared d, is pictograph
ictal,.
But here you can see the top
that all of these sort of
representations started as the
original image.
You can kind of see on the
left-hand side, there's this
progression of what a horse
looks like starts very much the
image of the horse and we get
down to the simplified script,
that's what's being used today.
What's super fascinating about
this, as well, is that
the -- when you look at it, the
current standard for Chinese
language in China 2300
is used in 5% of websites.
But during the time when this
was happening, the
simplification, one of the
things about the Chinese
languages, there's an old
traditional script, which
you see is like the standard
script versus the simplified
and that happened during the
1950s where the CCP and
Communist Party wanted to
improve the literacy rates of
the Chinese people.
The literacy rates were super
abysmal.
I think more than 90% of people
at the time were unable to read
. It's really complicated.
If you've ever tried to learn
east Asian
language/character-based
language, there's so many
things to learn. How do we make
this easier? How do we
incorporate this into a
modernized world? How do we
think about this?
And so, coming here, this is an
example of what an immovable
type kind of emphasizing if
you've ever worked with print
making or letter
press, you would know that you
have in Latin script, you have
GLIFs
you have gl
yphs, you have to have all of
the individual characters.
This is an example of how much
stuff you would need which is
really terrifying. Even in the
modernization of it, it's
like, what would this even look
like? So this was just like a
speculative sketch of a
typewriter.
And so, it's like, you have all
of these characters mapped out
on to it.
The average Chinese dictionary
has 60,000 to 80,000 words.
A body font for a Chinese font
would require
you to have about 8,000 words,
but that doesn't take into
case differences in simplified
and traditional. There's a lot
you have to deal with and a lot
of history associated with
this.
There's also a lot of political
structures,
one thing, specifically, is
that in this example, the
Chinese language is comprised
of individual radicals.
So radicals and also characters
composed of traditional and
simplified.
And so, here, this radical
means speech.
So one of the things in the
basis for the Chinese language,
it's composed of
the various radicals that add
up to sort of give meaning to
the character. And you can kind
of see all of the characters
above have this speech rad KAG
and they all have words that
are -- meanings that are
related
to speech creation, word
creation, or sort of like
communication.
This is not like ubiquitously
true across the language, but
it is one thing really
interesting to consider when
you think about comprising and
creating the Chinese language
as a whole especially from a
type design perspective where
you want to sort of
componentize all of these
characters. But one thing
you'll also notice in this kind
of creation is that you can't
-- you have to make different
components for each specific
one.
For example, even in the
character on the right for
talking fast,
ha, there's two of these sort
of smaller radicals on the
bottom and one on the top.
And within the components have
to make different
subcomponents. And so, I think
this is a really interesting
and theoretical approach when
you consider to like how you
make UI abstractions or the
ways components exist in the
UI.
Is there a way this can exist
for font software and making it
easier for Chinese ?
This is aS Ais an example of
the traditional versus
simplified dichotomy looks to.
One of the main things to
consider in traditional versus
simplified,
there's political ramifications
around two where traditional is
more present in places like
Taiwan and Hong Kong and other
locations while simplified is
in the mainland. That's for
another conversation, but
something to keep in mind if
you ever have to do
localization .
Just to dig into what
specifically where you're
thinking about creating those
languages for.
And so, now a little bit into
classifications of Chinese
writing systems. So the way
that we have type systems kind
of as
like san
serif and italicized and all of
that stuff, Chinese also has
this in the font,
as well, this is called sunti,
which is based off historical
precedence in
the Song dynasty after the name
sonti.
It alludes to this more call
calligraphy nature. There are
large flat stones, flourish at
the end that is indicative of
old style.
This is what we would consider
kind of a serif in the Chinese
world. Next up, we have this
thing called hati which
translates to black lettering
or black body, and so,
this more represents kind of
the
san serif world and this rose
to prominence, mainly in the
late 2000s as a result of
increased digitalization where
it was like, how
do we make these characters
like easier to read online?
We also have this thing called
k iti, less engrained in
older historical periods, be
but some of the same
flourishes. And the fourth one,
a mix of this kind of old
songti. You can see here as the
one in the past, we have these
little flourishes
and like more sort of softer
notes.
And so, this kind of gives more
of a different writing style/ I
think in terms of the bamboo
pendant you would potentially
be using.
And one of these things, also,
is kind of
a classification, which is
translates to kind of artistic
display or artistic font. And
typically, it describes this
world of display fonts
, and like display lettering
that's super fun, very bouncy,
sort of like hard to define.
And I think I'm personally like
really interested in
this because it's like all of
those things can be done really
well, but where are the things
with a lot of personality and
depth to them?
And so, how do you use this?
Default set for English
language contains 230 gyphs.
In Chinese, you have to make a
lot of gyphs.
What happens with this, the
size of your font file becomes
really, really large and
becomes really kind of almost
terrible to use.
And the fact that in China,
there's different character
encoding
methods that are primarily
used, as well. But luckily,
thanks to the
unicode consortium, you can
ignore that and use
the unicode UTF-8, which will
always work for you given the
sort of
as long as your font file is
dwell defined within the font
file specifications. P
And you can always use that,
UTF primarily supports all of
the Chinese characters that
exist out in the world. But
luckily, when you use this, you
can actually just define the
font family inside your CSS
like this.
One thing to consider, you want
to put the Romanization and the
Chinese characters' names.
Just in case you don't know
which one it's going to map to.
You want to put it as a
fallback and also always define
your Latin language CSS font
family first.
There's some interesting stuff
being done in the
Taiwanese world. This is a site
which translates to, there
exists a font library. We have
a font library, which I think
is really funny.
And they have this kind of
experimental API that allows
you to fetch for a web P file
that provides
all of these gy
lyphs for you and checks which
are needed and will only
send you the corresponding
glyphs, thus decreasing the
size of it, as well.
This is sort of a reference for
if you ever want free fonts,
free Chinese fonts, because
they're really hard to get to
and really hard to find and
make, this is a great GitHub
for it call Words Hub free
font.
And one of the things I've also
noticed, when you look at these
fonts, all of them in the
beginning have the denotation
of what foundry made them. This
is Fongjun, kind of like
founder is the name of it.
These are foundries of the
various different types of
files. There's the san serifs
and the calligraphy
. You can use this writing mode
that allows
you to write right to left,
. You also have this great
thing called font variant East
Asian. Which is specifically
for East Asian languages and
scripts. You can move between
normal and traditional.
And then, one of the other
things to obviously mention as
a side note, is that no sans,
which is a project by Google
and Adobe exist to kind of
provide language scripts across
the world. And so how do we
feel about, we feel
that it BLOJ belongs in the
trash and look for other
things.
Really quickly, just some
examples of kind of like fonts
and use of what can you
actually do this? Or how do you
pair it with Latin scripts?
This is a comparison of what
hati and songti look together.
There was a project doing the
Chinese rebranding of the "New
York Times" and he uses this
beautiful black letter kind of
alluding to the same
"New York Times" motif and uses
the same stem/notion for this,
as well.
One of the funniest things if
you've been following along in
the three body problem
discourse, is the type
serif used in the banner for
the communist party. Everyone
in China was pissed because
it needed to be a heavier
weight. And you can see in the
bottom corner what it should
look like
. And you can also argue about
the issues in the three body
problem.
Here's a really great example
from the Taiwan design expo. I
love the sort of
constrained/put together
use of the Latin type that has
these weird
end traps/contrast together
with the more traditional
notions of the characters.
Here's a piece, who did the
Chinese brand identity
for Alice in Wonderland, and
you can see them piecing
together with the original
characters.
Here's another poster by a
graphic
designer who takes the original
character and uses the lines
and glyphs as individual
shapes.
Just a couple more examples.
One thing I wanted to mention
in the sort of vein of fun
Indie programming, you can make
your own Chinese esoteric
language.
This is written in the script
of sort of old Chinese
languages and programs and
compiles to both JavaScript,
Ruby . You can write programs
in Chinese if you wanted to.
And the great about it.
Since it's defined on the grid
structure, you can always --
they're all monospace by
default. So that whole problem
is solved for you.
Lastly, I wanted to sort of end
with this talk
. This is a characters that
means to add oil.
But encourage everyone sort of
to, you know, if there's
any interest, dig into these
things, look at Chinese
characters, think about
different scripts in the world
and how you can use them to
benefit your
own designs and your own sites.
So thank you.
≫ MIKE: That was really cool.
Just a whole world you brought
us into.
Yeah, it's fascinating thinking
about that
difference between the number
of characters and Latin versus
Chinese
and the
necessity to strip it out of
the font sizes. It really is
like a performance difference,
pretty major performance
difference that you need the
extra level of optimization on.
What sort of tooling do you use
to do that?
≫ IVAN: Yeah, so there's a lot
of kind of like one things I
mentioned, there's some
experimental stuff.
There's two font foundries, one
of them called just font, which
is based in Taiwan. And the
other one is also based in
Taiwan.
You'll find the interesting
type foundries are based not in
mainland China because of
various political reasons.
But they're providing like
experimental APIs that allow
you to do that . But honestly,
if you're doing it on kind of
like a one -off site or
project, you can just download
an OTF or raw file and use it
regularly as a font file.
≫ MIKE: Got it. Ivan, thanks
again for joining. That was
fantastic.
≫ IVAN: Thank you so much.