Light mode versus dark mode, I
have changed the title to
Why Not Both? Or why building
both dark and light schemes
together is easy, actually.
I hope I'm not overselling
that. Hi, I'm Sara. I have am
both an old hand,
like Mike said, I've been
building websites as a teenager
since 1999, only my own stuff.
It was only ever really a hobby
thing.
I had a long hiatus. And now
I'm a newbie, again, I
switched my career from doing
general electronic and other
stuff in small companies and a
couple of big companies.
And I jumped into web
development,
not last year, two years ago
now. I still feel like a
newbie. I guess I'm not, but I
feel like one.
Just a little warning that
there's already been some
movement, there'll be some more
movement, a tiny bit of
animation and abrupt changes
between dark and light modes in
this presentation. Because it's
difficult not to.
If you suffer from migraines,
epilepsy, strong
astigmiatism,
I'm really sorry, but I hope
with this information I'm about
to present to you, browsing the
web will get more comfortable
for you and everyone else.
So with that aside, I'll try
and warn whenever I'm about to
flash the screen from dark to
light. Let's get started. Dark
mode versus light mode.
And we all love a good
polarizing argument. And what
could be more polarizing in
dark versus light? But there
are physical reasons to prefer
one over the other.
And just allowed to prefer dark
or light mode. That's OK.
You don't have to have a
logical reason for it because
your eye is your choice.
So that said, why dark mode?
Your pupils constrict when they
come across a bright page or
bright anything. I think you
can quite often notice.
You feel the muscles pulling
your pupil, pulling your iris
inwards to make your pupils
smaller.
And if you're in a dark
surroundings, like I am right
now, yeah, it's quarter past
10:00 here. If you suddenly
jump into a bright website,
that's uncomfortable.
And then, other people have
floaters that appear or block
their vision.
A lot of you may, I mean, I'm
40 now, so sometimes, when I'm
looking up at a bright sky, I
see these things.
The second example on the right
is a bit more
what I see, sort of translucent
something or other drifting
across.
That some people with really
severe floaters might struggle
to read, text on a light
background
because the light background
just sort of is distorted
through the floaters.
Why light mode?
Pupils constrict when coming
across a bright page . But that
can be a good thing, actually,
because it's easier to
focus when your pupil is
smaller.
Like with a camera (inaudible)
you might close your aperture
in order to get a whole
landscape in focus.
Whereas if the aperture is
large, you have to very
carefully focus on separate
items. You have your foreground
and background and they're
different and you have to
focus and it's the same with
your eyes, they have to work to
focus more when your pupil is
large because everything's
darker.
And then, people have
astigmiatism
STIG
stigmatism. Light text on dark
backgrounds can become hard to
read.
They might be clear like they
are now, but with a little bit
of extra fuzz and your brain
and eyes work together to
try to sharpen out that fuzz to
try to focus better.
But when you can't, get away
from that.
When you can't get...  when you
start to get headaches.
Interestingly, I found a lot
more examples about this and
people struggling with dark
mode, because clearly there's a
lot of people annoyed about
websites only available in dark
mode.
So there's really loads of
examples people have made
of slightly fuzzed out or
distorted text, light text on a
dark background. And even, I'm
looking at these, and you know,
I'm trying to focus them.
I can feel my eyes and my brain
trying to focus these bits of
text and I can't, of course.
And if you're staring at this
all the time, it's going to
hurt.
And I love this one, I am the
douche
bag that makes people read
white text on a black
background.
So that would be why you might
prefer light mode.
Why not both?
Both. Both. Both is good.
I'm sure everyone gets that
reference.
[ Laughter ]
Anyway. So in this talk scope,
is just having
your site react to preferred
color scheme.
So I'm not going to talk about
manual toggling. It can be
done. I will show you it.
Shortly because with a bit hof
of JavaScript, it's easy and
you can find advice on the
internet including
me trying to give advice on it.
I've got a little toggle here.
Be warned, it's going to go
white.
And back, again.
I'm back to auto. So the
toggling is absolutely
possible.
But I'm not going to go into
how to do that in this talk.
And I must remember to click
right. So this is what I get
for rolling my own
presentation.
So starting from scratch. If
you have no styles, this is no
problem.
However, if you have already
really big
mature site or design system or
massive project , this may be
tricky to bring into your
projects.
If everything already has
specific colors , branding,
everything's set, it's going to
be hard to put this back in.
It's possible. I'm sure it's
possible.
But it's going to be difficult.
But I want you to keep this
light mode/ dark mode bothness
in mind next time you have --
you start a new project.
So we know this, we all have
seen default HTML themes, not
that we look at it anymore
because you probably set your
CSS reset before you even look
at the page.
I often set everything to just
san serif at least before I
start anything.
It's standard HTML here.
There's nothing unusual.
But you may not know that
there's also default dark
theme.
And everything's done for you,
the buttons, the inputs, the
link.
Link colors here have all been
adjusted already to look better
in dark mode. You don't have to
do it.
The browser's done it for you.
How do we get to that? You
don't even need CSS.
And Mayank did hint to this
earlier that you can put a
metatag in your HTML.
The meta  name is color-scheme.
And the content is light/dark.
You can put dark/light.
It might make a difference if a
user's OS isn't broadcasting
I'm in
light mode or I'm in dark mode.
I'm not sure many of them do
that now.
I think almost all of them are
in light mode or dark mode,
there might be some that don't
care.
If there's some that don't
care, if you put dark/light, it
may be that your website shows
in dark mode first.
As a preference. I haven't been
able to test it.
You can also put it in your
CSS.
So, under the root or HTML
selector, you have color
-scheme, color light/dark.
This website can show up in
light or dark, no problem.
And then, the browser will
follow the operating system's
preference and show you your
preferred version of this
website.
So just as an example, in
CodePen, tech
nically, it has a separate
place for the he, head.
You're not supposed to put the
head here within the HTML, but
you can do it and it seems to
work. This is what I'm using as
a display.
And because my laptop, my
Windows is
in dark mode because I prefer
the dark mode, it's going to
dark.
I could just -- drop dark, go
back to light.
In fact, I can put some sort of
gibberish
in there and it'll still be
light because light remains the
default default.
Or I can say all of this is
going to be dark.
And just to prove this is the
case, I'll pop open dev tools
here.
We've got color scheme
light/dark, prefers from dev
tools. Oh, everything is light.
I'll put it back to automatic,
which is what my laptop wants
to be. For some reason, this
gets home in a very
strange position, I suspect
it's this head getting annoyed
with real head, I'm not sure
entirely what's going on there.
We also have system colors and
the most reliable of these is
canvas text.
And canvas. And they're kind of
what you expect them to be.
Don't confuse them with canvas,
the element canvas.
Con vas text is the color of
the text. Canvas is the color
of your background.
Here, you can see I've just
done
a div with what you've expected
and I've reversed them. And
just reversed in here.
If I call this dark, it's dark.
I'll put it back to light.
Or I can do light/dark and
it'll turn dark, again,
because my laptop is in dark
mode. So you can apply color
scheme to elements, but you do
need to put the canvas text and
the canvas in there first.
If I just remove them
here, it doesn't quite work
because your element is sort of
transparent by default.
You need to have given them a
color before you can put a
color on an element otherwise
it's got nothing to work on.
I found that by trial and
error.
There are other system colors
and I have a role, because
they're patchy and I wanted to
tell you it's patchy and it's a
bit sad.
I can get rid of dev tools now,
too, apologies.
Here, you'd expect that link
text, which is being applied to
this one should look like the
text of the actual link.
And visited text should look
like the color of the text of
an actual visited thing. And
active text should look like,
let's have a dash go to this
link.
It should look like that.
Unfortunately, it does not.
This is Edge I'm using, so
Chrome yum
Chromium. Who does do it well
is Firefox
. Beautiful, link text looks
like link text.
(Audio cutting out) visited
text.
So,
Firefox for that one. I believe
they're going to trickle
through, but I have not seen
any improvement in a couple of
years. Maybe we can push on
that. Contrast too high.
So you're there, you've got
your con
canvas and your canvas text and
you're thinking like, great,
but I don't just want to use
those.
Maybe contrast is a bit too
high. And like is written
there, those implementing
WCAG for accessibility may find
it unlikely that contrast could
be too high. But for some, for
example, migrainers, they do
have trouble with this.
It can kick off micro
migraines, especially on
websites where things are
moving and scrolling if the
contrast is too high, it can
start to kick things off.
But there's also preferred
contrast.
This is a bit tricky because
I'm not sure where you can set
preferred contrast in your
operating systems. But it's
there.
And I'm fairly sure prefers
color scheme came before all
OSs allowed you to
toggle dark or light.
So, hoping that prefers
contrast starts allowing OSs to
allow you to toggle contrast.
The simplest way to bring
contrast down across the board
is filter contrast.
So, for example, that's just an
extra thing I've added there .
I've added a filter,
prefers less. And filtering the
whole thing by half, which is
possibly a bit extreme.
But let's bring dev tools back
in.
And under rendering, under here
so with the -- I'm trying to
remember how I opened this
somewhere, you can
find this rendering
options. And there's all sorts
of different options, including
prefers color scheme.
But here is prefers contrast.
Nothing for custom, nothing for
more, but you can, you can
totally do something different
for prefers contrast more.
Or prefers contrast less. And
then, my media query is kicking
in. I have done a lot of CSS
nesting because it's fun, not
just because it's best
practice, yet.
I think it's great.
Let's bring down the contrast
change a tic.
And even for me, with normalish
eyesight apart from age-related
trouble,
it's already
for me, you might prefer lower
contrast. But might not want to
filter all the time.
We can start using other
colors, of course. I really
like color mix.
Because we can use canvas text
and canvas, we can use them as
mixes with other colors.
So they look good
both in dark mode and light
mode while only having to
declare them once. So, for
example, here, if you
knock out the percentage, which
you can, it just goes to 50/50.
40 looks good here, so I'll
stick 40 back in.
I'll switch it into light mode.
And the backgrounds also
lighten up because they're
mixed with canvas and the
text has darkened, which has
flipped along with my color
scheme .
Another way to do it is having
a bit of lower opacity.
So here, I've got magenta. It's
all red, zero green, all blue
plus O
opacity of 4, I'm going to flip
it, again .
Flip.
So that's one way.
We can, as we used to, use
prefers color scheme.
We're totally used to it, we
can do it.
However, if you're flipping
color scheme, just color scheme
light/dark with your JS like I
am here, it doesn't change.
Now, here I've set it so that
when it's prefers color scheme
light, top one should have a
background of a Teal color. And
this bottom one should have a
background of
a green with 25% opacity.
And they do not.
Because prefers color scheme is
only asking the OS, it's
not flipping with color scheme.
Again, we'll go to dev tools.
Just to prove that it does
work.
So color scheme light coming
on, again.
We're in a halfway house
because I've got dark mode
here. These all interact with
each other, and it's so
interesting.
So, light and back to dark.
And light, again, the purpley
colors are going to green
colors. And make it clear that
it's automatic. Light, dark.
So it's
prefers color scheme and the
color scheme property are a
little bit away from each other
once you start to introduce
toggling.
But -- what's coming is
light/dark and it's not quite
an all browsers.
It's coming in version 17. 5 of
Safari and there might be one
or
two straggler browsers after
that. But it's really nearly
with us.
And just to show the
difference, here we have a
whole media query. Here is
nested within the first
declaration.
So it's not too big, but still
is a whole media query
where it's just saying, when
it's
light, I want this color, when
it's dark, I want this color.
And the same here, when it's
light, I want this color, when
it's dark, I want this color.
And that will work with the OS
flipping to being
dark or light mode and also,
just with it's going to go
light now. With color scheme.
And back to light.
And back to dark. Soer, this is
really satisfying for me.
But this is happily working on
Microsoft
Edge and Chrome and I think
Fire
fox and just Safari left to go.
It's so close.
To summarize, once it lets me
go to the next slide.
In summary, have a go at using
color scheme light/dark or the
metatag. Either way, it really
doesn't matter.
If you use the metatag, it's
easier to flip with JavaScript.
Try using color mix when you're
adding colors
. Mixing it with canvas or
canvas text.
Have a go at supporting user
contrast preferences.
And look forward to light/dark
like I am. And then, just
encourage you to experiment.
Because it's just changing
these things
are quite easy things to
change. You need to experiment
to see what works with what and
how you can adjust things
and what looks good in dark and
light at the same time .
I find it immensely fun to play
with.
So I'm glad to share it with
you. And I hope you fine it fun
to play with.
The takeaway, is to offer
choice. Just with the dark
mode/light mode and the more
contrast/
less contrast you have four
different themes already
. And if you decide to do
something for, well, that would
be normal contrast, I suppose,
and less contrast,
if you decide to do something
extra for more contrast, then
you've got 6. Yeah.
I mean, and you've got 6 themes
all at once.
On my home page, I added a
border to everything
in canvas or canvas text
depending on whether it's dark
or light mode.
And it's brilliant. It shows
everything extremely contrasty.
That's it.
I hope you have some fun
playing with it.
There's -- I'll share these
slides. I obviously stand on
the shoulders of giants.
There's so many people whose
stuff I've read and digested.
And some people have digested
my previous stuff and come,
again, with better, written it
better than I did
. So please follow a few links
and thank you, I'm
really honored to have taken
part in the 11ty Conference
, huge thank to the crew, Mike,
David, and I can see here in
the studio,
captioner Diane, because that's
work, and thank you very much.
And hope to see you, any of
you, again. Thank you.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, Sara. Amazing.
Yeah. I learned a lot.
I've just been doing the --
I've been doing the basics of
light/dark mode.
It's just fascinating how far
you can take that.
I didn't know about light/dark,
a lot of those things .
≫ SARA: Oddly, I find this to
be more basic, just these
couple of properties have made
so much of it way easier, now
you've got a bigger play room
to jump into.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, and being able to
do it without any CSS at all,
I didn't realize that was
possible. Yeah.
≫ SARA: Right?
It was a surprise to me, too,
just like, oh, I didn't have to
style all that dark stuff
myself.
It already had it.
[ Laughter ]
≫ MIKE: Awesome. I've got to
play around with it.
Yeah, it's going to be a lot of
fun. Thanks, again, for
joining, Sara. It was awesome.
≫ SARA: Thank you so much.