Yeah sure, and I’ll go ahead
and proceed
I'm Paul
Everitt, developer advocate as
Mike mentioned.
We're going to talk about using
11ty on larger
projects, but first, I wanted
to give a big thank you to all
of you to you,
especially to Zach for this
conference. It's like you
crawled inside my brain and
found the
exact speakers and the exact
topics that I would be
interested in seeing.
And not only that, Zach created
this community
around 11ty, which is
fantastic.
I'm just such a supporter and
advocate for everything he's
doing.
And like was mentioned before,
trying to put the web back in
the web. So let's begin.
We have a website called the
JetBrains guide.
It has content, we've been
working on it for a while
while with a big friend of
11ty. And when I started this,
in 2018
, I used Gatsby. No, seriously,
please, stay.
We all make decisions, just
like getting beat up on the
playground as a kid, you can
learn from your mistakes, but
we also can learn some of the
things that can take us
forward.
I learned a lot about modern
web, good and the bad.
Learned a lot about I come from
a CMS background, I learned a
lot about modern CMSs.
And there was a point when
Collin came to me and said, you
know, really everyone hates you
about this Gatsby thing and so,
you really got to make a change
here.
Let's go to 11ty. But we wanted
to keep the developer
experience we had from the
tooling . We wanted to keep
some of the author experience
that we had.
So we went away and added some
of the
things to 11ty and
realistically, that's the talk
for today, what did we do with
11ty to support things that
you might want to do with a
Gatsby
. Things you might want to do
with a CMS. Things you might
want to do with a larger
system.
What do I mean?
We rolled out a codebase that
used typescript and used a
templating language, TSX.
JSX, TSX. As an 11ty template
ing language, not as a browser
rendered templating language.
We also added in, I like to do
tests
-first development, we added in
V test, and friends, the
friends we'll cover in a
moment.
And some other stuff I hope
we'll have time to get to about
improving the author experience
with automatically generating
JSON schema, and then, one of
the things I kind
of was intrigued about from
Gatsby was its GraphQL query
model.
One little point, if you're
ever doing GraphQL
and you -- and Gatsby, and you
think you want to do custom
GraphQL schema extensions,
don't.
All right.
The real philosophy P behind
this is, doing your web
development in small little
chunks so you can stay in the
flow. And you're not like doing
a whole build with console
logs and poking around hoping
to stumbling across the problem
that you're having.
Instead, it feels like
development with joy.
As I go through this, you don't
have to follow
along too closely, I'm going to
go pretty fast through the how
and try to get more to the
demos that show a little bit
more of the why .
And the reason you don't have
to is because we put up
an 8-part tutorial with text
and code and
videos walking through each one
of the steps that I'm going to
go through a little bit today.
I'll take a look over here and
see if there's anything I need
to catch up on in comments, as
well.
With that in mind, let's do a
quick tour of how we got to
tooling.
For 11ty. First in the package
.
json as Zach mentioned in the
opening remarks, we started
with ESM modules.
This was something in 3. 0 that
we got when we did this in 2.
0, we had to stick with
CommonJS.
The hero of the show is a
package called TS X, and it is
a layer on top of ES build
that gives you a bunch of
sensible defaults so that you
don't have to think about it so
much, which is good because I
don't really understand a lot
of these decisions.
And it winds up feeling like a
Node replacement.
The command node, obviously,
it's running node under the
hood,
but you run TSX instead and you
inherit all of this stuff.
Then, we needed something to
render a VDOM, I guess, is the
best way to put it
into a string, and this is the
package we used. It had a
number of things that we really
needed.
Versus a package we were using
before.
What this means, we're not
using React anywhere.
There's no React, Preact,
this package renders or JSX
into a string.
And then for the component
driven development workflow, we
like to sit in tests . So V
test is a wonderful package and
it's super speedy. Friends came
along for the ride with V test.
A browser called Happy DOM and
testing library that has a
philosophy of testing your site
the way people use it.
In an accessibility oriented
way with rules and stuff like
that.
And then, finally, in the
package. json, these are the
two build scripts. You notice
the TSX in front and the
config file is written in
typescript.
I won't go into TS config
because I frankly don't
understand it that way.
But typescript has support for
JSX, so we turn it on with the
misnamed value React JSX.
It doesn't actually have any
React.
And then, second, pointing it
at our package, the JSX async
runtime which then teaches the
compiler where everything is so
we don't have to manually
import.
Here is our 11ty config file.
11ty has support out of the box
for JavaScript templates.
And what we want to do is say,
these file extensions are
actually JavaScript.
Even though it says jsx,
THOECHB it says ts.
Because that tsx package is
going to transparentally
convert all of that into
JavaScript.
Finally, in the config, this
was the big breakthrough
eleventy.
config gives us a plug point to
do transforms, and in one
central location instead of
doing it throughout the code,
we were able to transform a jsx
node into a
string asynchronously, and
then, just for fun, we
centralized the placement of
a dot.
One last step, we wanted to do
testing and so in vtest, it has
support for the fake browsers,
out of the box, it supports
happy dom, this was the line
that we put in to get our good
testing. I'll take a look over.
And see, no, not a lot
of dependencies. We removed
dependencies, in fact, as we
went along.
OK. Over to some demos.
I'll go ahead and switch over
to...  the sample repository,
and then, I'll go back to our
repository to show some of this
in action.
I'm going to show you an
end-to-end of the smallest
possible thing without a lot of
extra concepts.
Here is the home page or my
site, and you see that it's got
layout, front matter,
everything we understand, but
because I've switched over to
this tooling
friendly approach, I don't have
to think too much about files
anymore, and I can think about
symbols.
And so every page on the site
has a main layout, and I can
navigate to this main layout.
This is what the file looks
like.
If you've done any of the ESM
stuff, this line will look
familiar to you.
You need to export a named
export called render.
I rename everything so that I
can have similar bombsymbols so
everything isn't
named render. I've got a
function called main layout.
This might look a little
React-y to you. And what it's
doing is saying, hey, I'm going
to
be passed these two things, I
know what I'm going to get
passed,
and any caller can get
auto-complete for this .
You can get auto-complete
because we
do props and prompts in a
typescript type.
And now, tooling can help me. I
can mouse over this and see
what is the
contract that needs to be
obeyed? And what I can
destructure from it?
I can get auto-complete,
obviously.
I can get a squiggle if I make
a mistake . I could even
decide, no, really, I want this
to be
called "heading. " And
everywhere in my project that
uses that will
now use heading, including
the prompts because there's
great tooling support for
typescript.
There's great tooling support
for jsx, and if I don't like
that, I undo it. And everything
in the universe goes back to
what I had
before I did the refactoring.
Again, this is stuff that
people are familiar
with in the frontend
world, and we're getting the
good parts of that while
leaving the whole agenda of
client-side rendering.
I'm returning jsx instead of a
template, I
get all of the stuff like
auto-complete in here. And
then, this is a fun one,
I'm showing -- writing my site
in
a reusable component-driven
fashion . So I do little units
of increment.
And I can get auto-complete of
my headings.
And when I do the
auto-complete, generates
the report for me, and I get
all of the things that you
would expect from good tooling.
I can then navigate to the
heading, see how it's
implemented, and then, I can do
the way I
do development, which is in a
test.
And so, I'm working over here,
I've got my test over here .
And if I
changed this word to "Zach "
and run this test, it's going
to fail, and I might be
confused why it failed
. Well, I can go into the
debugger, stop on this line,
that's the first time
through, and I see, oh, yeah,
duh, I passed in --
I didn't pass in tsx, I passed
in Zach, that's why I ran into
the problem.
So that's a little bit of a run
through of the test-driven
development approach on this.
I'll look over here. And see.
Some comments.
Hey, Collin, thank you for
helping me out here.
I do like the minimum layout in
my IDE in here.
And with all of that in mind,
here's the way I actually work.
I run vtest in watch mode.
Because it's so fast.
And I run it in watch mode
under the debugger.
And so, I've got my entire 11ty
development that is running at
all times
whenever I make a change. And
so, if I fix
this, that's my turn around
time. I didn't go to a browser
and hit reload. I didn't run an
11ty build.
In fact, if I wanted to, and
I'm like, I'm confused here, I
don't have a bug, I just don't
know what's going on here. Set
a break point, press space, and
you will stop there.
And sometimes, 11ty hands me a
lot of
data, a lot of surface area in
page, a lot of surface area in
data, and I get confused, I'm a
man of a certain age.
I just want to see what's
available. And this is what I
do to stop at a certain point
in rendering and see what is
available to me at that point.
All right. I will continue.
Obviously, we want to see does
this
thing actually render a
template that can be used in a
browser?
So after I've done all of my
development, that's when I
actually
go over to a browser and look
at it . And, yes, actually,
it is a very nice size. It did
render, it could use a little
bit of help from Miriam on the
styling, obviously.
That's an end-to-end
tour of the minima with about 5
minutes
left, I'll take a look at what
we're doing in our knowledge
base . Feel free to ask any
questions, Collin is show
runner with me on that project,
and he can answer anything over
there.
I'm going to switch over to our
actual project . This is our
knowledge base.
It's pretty big.
So this is all the content, or
all the programming languages
that JetBrain supports.
These are all of the components
that we have that are isolate
d and easy to test and stuff
like that we can use wherever.
And so, this is, again, test
driven development
. What I'm going to do this
time is I'm going to run all of
the tests in the entire site
under the debugger.
Vtest will fire it up the first
time, it'll take a few seconds
to fire up the first time vtest
has gotten faster. I could
speed this up.
Once it's running, all of my
tests pass, I have 131 tests.
And I make a mistake. Here is a
usage of a test. I'm calling
the heading.
Passing in the two values. I
make a mistake.
And then, my test no longer
passes, I get a little squiggle
here.
I can mouse over it and get
more information for exactly
what the problem is.
But that's a pretty fast turn
around time under the debugger
for working with your site.
And we never went to the
browser, and we never did
console log.
The part that I wanted to
finish with is the other stuff
besides just developer
experience. We also added some
stuff from an authoring
experience.
So if you were interested in
leaving Gatsby, these are some
of the kinds of things you
might also be interested in.
For example, I'm sitting in a
markdown file.
This is actually the tutorial
that we wrote for this
conference . And I have front
matter up here.
Well, my front matter actually
has a schema.
And so, if I were to write
author, I get auto-complete.
But I don't get autocomplete
just of the keys, I
get auto-complete of the
values, that is actually
i... y...
markdown file. PWE was the
thing, it's in content
space, it's not in software
space.
How are we doing that?
We have a bunch of resources
that we define in typescript,
and let me go to tip model.
Tip models, yeah. We define our
schemas in typescript.
Here's the schema for a tip.
And then, we use type box to
convert that to a JSON schema
we can enforce.
And then, every single time you
hit save, we rerun some
code that writes a JSON schema.
We dump all of the schemas to
disk. And here's what the
schema looks like.
And so the IDE sees this, it
sees that
these are all of the possible
values, and we give an
authoring experience where an
author.
This was the thinking that
killed us in Gatsby. You would
put in a wrong value, and you
would fail.
And you would fail obscurely,
and you would have no hope
other than coming to me and
getting me to look at your
branch.
We really wanted with the
embrace of 11ty, we really
wanted to give a better
authoring experience on this.
Some other things we would like
to talk about at a later
date, things such as the
content model that has plugable
resource types and the queries.
Zach is adding in 3. 0, more
hook points that are exactly
the hook points
we need for validation, for
custom collections , and things
like that.
And then, we also were
confronted with something for
client side rendering where we
wanted to keep the templating
that we had and had to do a
work around for that.
With that in mind, this has
been a wonderful experience for
us.
Any of you that are interested
in moving from a larger system
with all of this tooling, such
as Gatsby,
over to 11ty, please reach out,
let's see what we can do
working all of this stuff
together.
.
≫ MIKE: Thank you so much,
Paul, it's always interesting
seeing, like,
how these big use are cases --
how 11ty
can and does a very good job of
it, of adapting to handle
something like that.
It was really interesting
seeing that workflow.
Which like a site, the scale of
your knowledge base,
it makes a lot of sense that
you need all of that tooling.
What was the buildout time?
And how long did it take you to
transition from Gatsby to the
11ty setup?
≫ PAUL: Collin and I did a
first shot in 11ty 2 and got it
out the door. And then in the
second shot, we did a lot of
just
redesign the user design and
user experience and stuff.
And along the way, as we really
got into what 11ty
could do for us, it changed the
idea of the knowledge base
completely.
You know, we'll let authors
create their own channels, and
they can write templates
because this is simple enough
that it can be put in the hands
of mere
mortals.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
So the workflow and GitHub
pulling in those --
≫ PAUL: Indeed.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
≫ PAUL: Just -- to reinforce
the point you're
making, people might have this
idea that 11ty is for personal
blogs. Let's change that.
Let's tell people that you can
do big projects,
Zach continues to add what's
needed for that. And let's see
how far we can go before 11ty
runs out of steam.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, it's actually
ideal for doing something like
that. Like, what other kind of
benefits have you
seen from move inging from
Gatsby to 11ty? I imagine your
build time came down?
Yeah, did it come down?
≫ PAUL: It came down from
infinity. What happened was,
you couldn't trust the Gatsby
cache,
so you had to do a full build
all the time and in our CI, it
would never complete before the
CI canceled the job.
≫ MIKE: OK. That's a lot less.
[ Laughter ]
So you'd have to build locally
and push it up?
≫ PAUL: Yeah, right.
≫ MIKE: Wow. Incredible. Yeah,
that's a big win.
CI being able to build your
site.
≫ PAUL: Indeed, and from an
authoring experience
perspective, I know we're going
to be thinking -- actually, the
talks at this conference are
very author-focused. And that's
great.
It's not just machinery.
When you can build sites that
give you the feedback that
instantaneously
and provide the hook points for
people like me that are
interested in content
management systems, you can
have an authoring experience
that is really fantastic.
There's nothing worse than an
author that feels dumb, right?
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
And ultimately, like, most
websites are managed by
nontechnical people.
It's so important to think
about the workflows and empower
editors .
≫ PAUL: They're not developers,
they're humans.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, again, for
joining today, Paul. Fantastic.
≫ PAUL: Thanks for having me.
≫ MIKE: All right.