So as I was just introduced,
I'm the director of product
management, I've never been a
professional web developer but
always worked with developers.
I've always loved hacking web
stuff, and I think that --
for people like me, who have
always been sort of adjacent to
technology but not like always
like knee deep in it, this is
sort of like who it's for.
Some interesting stats.
Before I started learning 11ty
, I had maybe built one site
over five years . It was a
Gatsby site, and it made me
cry, and I just sort of like --
never went back to it. Never
wanted to do anything. Didn't
want to update it, I was
fearful  I would break stuff.
And for various reasons, I
started following Zach on
Twitter and
I was like, well, this seems
cool, I should give it a shot.
And I've actually built maybe 5
sites over 5 months. So that's
been really, really fun. And I
started thinking, why is that ?
Why is it I got so far with one
tool but not others?
I've tried tons of different
frameworks, site
generators, and I think for me,
it's that it was just -- it
feels so much
harder, not easier to build a
site in
2024 compared to 2000 when, I
guess, I built my very first
website, you know, hacking
around, changing HTML
and the CSS and stuff and being
like, this is really fun.
But then, at some point, it
stopped feeling
fun or it started to feel like
it was harder to find fun
things. And getting to build
sites with 11ty
brought back some of that joy.
So then I started thinking, why
is that? And how can we help
other people feel that way?
The same sense of, OK, this is
something cool I want to learn,
again.
And my theory is that there's
probably too much to learn,
people are not sure where to
pick up if you're not in
industry, there's so many
tools, so many frameworks, you
need to know a bit of JS to get
going to get anything done at
all.
There's also a lot of conflicts
advice on what you should do
and a lot of
this advice is about how to get
into the industry and how to be
a web developer ? How to make
money? And many of us got into
it because it was fun. So can
it be fun, again?
So I actually really think so.
I think that we can sort of
tweak maybe through
documentation and through the
way we like approach
tutorials to make 11ty
approachable to people who are
not web developers who don't
think they are . And, you know,
sometimes,
I don't like the word like
nontechnical because it feels
like it excludes people who
don't feel they're technical
enough and certainly, for me, I
think one of the reasons why I
didn't really
like go knee deep into web dev
because growing up, I was told,
you're a girl, you can't do
math, you don't know how to do
stuff, you shouldn't be a web
developer.
I do think having more
inclusive approach to things
will
help other people want to learn
this and this seems doable.
And when I announced I'm moving
off my
microblog, I was using a
microblog thing, which is good,
by the
way, I recommend that to people
who don't know how to build
sites from scratch.
For my photography website, and
someone emailed me and said, I
want to microblog because you
used it, it was really cool,
now 11ty, I also want to try
that. But I really don't know
where to start.
So how do we get people to
start here with 11ty?
So I think that this was the
right tool because a lot of
things are like you said, like
Zach said earlier, HTML first.
Many things work like expected.
It's not filtered through some
opinionated thing.
You can learn as much or as
little as you want. So could we
find a way to help people like
go, here's a bunch of starters,
here's where you deploy it and
if you want to know more,
figure it out later. And we
already have friendly
communities.
So how do we, then, sort of
take that and go maybe a
different set
of people who see themselves as
not web developers need
different sort of, like,
knowledge base or different
sort of documentation or
simplified versions of it.
Or they need to ask questions
at sort of happy hour thing
maybe on Discord,
maybe these are things we can
do. And I started thinking that
what would have helped me?
Even just how I got started in
January when I was learning
11ty, I found
that I was referencing
Stephanie
, I was referencing Bob, like
11ty from scratch.
So there's a lot of stuff that,
you know, I kind of have to put
together and figure out what
worked for me. But maybe we can
sort of help
curate them for someone that
feels like an absolute
beginner. Maybe we could have a
far more opinionated walk
through. Here's a bunch of
starters, click here, host
here, you know,
sometimes there's decision
paralysis if we could sort of
help to recuse that, maybe
people could get further with
the idea that they can, if they
can get early success, then
they might be inclined to want
to try to learn even more.
I also think it would be cool
to write more blog posts about
things that I learned when I
was
learning web dev as well as
11ty.
Really, just beginners, there's
a lot of content out there
obviously is very centered at
web developers.
But what if we could talk about
why we picked this thing, why
we used this tool, what you can
do, and really
simplify accessible ways. I
think that would be very
explanatory and
reach a far bigger audience.
Maybe there could be pairing or
like buddy system and we could
have a special channel just for
like newbies to get help
. Those were just ideas that
came to mind, and I'm
presenting this so we can
discuss what possible paths we
could pick up in the future, I
certainly volunteer myself for
a part of it.
And, you know, really, I'm
interested in doing this
because I think it's important
to spark joy, again, with the
web, that right now, if
the default option for someone
who doesn't perceive themselves
to be a developer is to put up
a squarespace site.
They don't have very much
control.
I think it's hard to go from
that squarespace pipeline to
I'm actually going to learn to
become a web developer
or build stuff for fun
pipeline.
And so, how can we sort of help
give people
the tools or at least
handlebars to get started,
again? On this sort of journey?
So I personally want to see a
world in which I
can build things that are fun,
maybe even pointless. I don't
want to just be productive, I
don't want to just build work
things. I also want to build
websites, too, for example,
I'm someone that documents a
lot of Asian Potato chips I
eat. And someone would love an
Asian potato chip website.
If I genuinely believe that
11ty empowers me
to do fun stuff like this, I
think it'll be the same for
other people.
So I'm putting myself out there
as someone who wants to sort of
help bridge this divide and to
maybe work on new stuff with
the team, either in like
writing more blogs or blog
posts to help other people get
started.
So that's all I have.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, thanks,
Adrianna, that was great. And I
think you highlighted that step
really well where going from
Squarespace where everything's
taking care of you to
understanding some of the
fundamentals and being able to
build your own site and through
that, having more control, it's
such an important
one that we need to figure out
how we can help people make
that jump.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah, exactly.
≫ MIKE: The web's for everyone,
it's an open platform. And if
you're confined to the CMS
platforms, you don't get to
experience that.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah and it's part
of taking back control aspect
of, you know,
building an open web that so
many of us are really big fans
of .
≫ MIKE: Yeah, and it's so cool
hearing about your journey, as
well,
like five sites in five months?
≫ ADRIANNA: Five months.
≫ MIKE: Really cool. I hope you
keep doing that and posting
them.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah, I definitely
will, thank you.
≫ MIKE: Thanks for joining us
today, Adrianna
. All right.
So we've got our next talk
coming up. In five minutes.
So, yeah, that was --
I feel like Adrianna really hit
it on the head there.
Like it's a big -- ask that
question to the chat . I think
she had good ideas
. But how do we make
technologies in
and the web as a platform more
accessible? Outside of like web
developers?
I think,
I think learning computer
science and web development at
high school should be
mandatory.
It's such an important part of
the world now that, like,
understanding these
technologies, at least to the
high level how they work is
really important. And it would
just give a lot more knowledge
and control to everyone .
As a nondeveloper, use GitHub
is
not an answer that speaks to
nondevelopers. Yeah, it's like
they can be a big -- it can be
a
big jump, for sure. A lot of
the, I think,
that's the other thing about
Git is
, like, where else do you have
a workflow
that -- that Git can do?
Google Docs, you can have some
of those elements
of a Git workflow, you have
some sort of versioning, yeah,
and like a history of changes.
You can collaborate with other
people.
Those are great.
And like a lot of those ideas
come from
collaboration sort of workflows
from a version control system.
But when you get into branching
and merge
ing and pull requests where you
don't necessarily have
permission on that document,
but you can still contribute to
it, like, Google Docs falls
down there immediately.
So, like for the web and
for Git, how do we enable these
technologies
for technical people
? Git is terrible for new
folks. Yeah, it can be.
It can be, like, it can be
scary
. You can
compare Git to DropBox, it's
easy to get your head around, a
magical folder, whereas Git,
I'm suddenly introduced to the
terminal or some sort
of application, is like these
branching lines everywhere,
there's like a lot of concepts
that you have to be introduced
to.
Getting comfortable with the
terminal interfaces is a hurdle
in my opinion. I'm fine with
it, but it can be a challenge
for newcomers.
Yeah, well said. Maybe we can
show nondevs how to run build
scripts
inside VSCode, yeah, that's
true, but still
need VSCode and, like, to use
the terminal and, I mean, it's
also not
an all or nothing approach.
Like, if we can make it...
every step we can make it a
little bit easier, then more
people can access this
technology.
So many don't (inaudible) with
Git.
I agree, it's hard to get
folks,
I love when all this Git stuff
involved, running commands and
CLI.
Git is awesome, but
intimidating, maybe 11ty
community can provide a real
simple introduction.
Yeah, it's like something we're
thinking about a lot is how can
we give the power of Git
abstract a lot of the
complexity and then introduce,
we've had a big debate whether
we introduce new terms or
educate on Git terminology.
So, like, think of a save
versus a commit.
I think it would be more ideal
if everyone used the same
language, which would be
commit, then there's
no ambiguity or confusion
between those.
Trust me, it would be better,
too many ideas where the
product is harder to understand
and use, we've got to speak to
direct impact. For sure.
Nice. Yeah, good ideas there.
DropBox is file storage first,
yeah, that's a good way to put
it. And different tradeoffs
because
of that.
I worked with
norm engineers at previous jobs
and they used Git GUI.
I mean, I use a Git GUI.
I just like seeing on the
screen exactly what's happening
and, like, I use the GitHub
desktop and
that gives me confidence I'm
not going to miss something.
Welcome to the terminal, it
doesn't say anything if you get
it right and screams at you if
you get it wrong. And also, you
completely break your computer.
Good luck.