So this talk is titled don't
fear the cascade.
And I want to talk about not
the dish soap, I want to talk
about CSS, specifically the C in CSS.
The cascade is probably the
reason why CSS gets such a
bad rep among developers. And it can be genuinely
puzzling if you don't take the time to understand it.
But that's why I'm giving this
talk. The cascade doesn't have
to be this unknown, scary
thing.
If you haven't been keeping up,
CSS has legitimately become
awesome.
We have the :has pseudo-class
and
nesting built into CSS now and
we're even scope styling!
How awesome is that?
And for the first time ever, we
have the tools to manage the
cascade in a way that feels
more…
hinged, for lack of a better word.
Yeah, this is a vast topic with multiple
layers of rabbit holes. So,
To keep things digestible, I'll simplify
my explanations and
provide practical suggestions along the
way.
So, to understand the cascade,
we're going to start with a
completely blank slate
with the minimum amount of
HTML required to style a page,
or create a page rather.
We're not even going to style it.
And, let's put a humble button
element in there.
Immediately, we can see that
this button element still
has some default styling, even though
there's no CSS on the page.
Earlier, Miriam already explained this
in more detail, but
These default styles come from the
user-agent style sheet.
And yes, these default styles
do respect the light and dark theme.
So like, my system,
operating system uses dark theme, so this
button is styled in a dark theme.
I won't spoil the
surprise, because
I'm sure Sara's going to talk
about this later today.
But yeah, you can have dark
theme without writing CSS.
Yeah, the user-agent style sheet is
literally a CSS file but built
into the browser. This is where
the cascade starts.
On this slide, I have a screen
shot of Chromium's user agent style sheet.
I went to their source code and
found it there. Thie file is some
hundreds of lines long.
Specifically, I'm showing a
small subsection
where this rule affects input, textareas,
and buttons. And
This rule sets the font property.
This font property is probably the
reason why every CSS reset
that you see uses something like
font:inherit on buttons and inputs
just so these elements will
match their
font size and font family of
their surroundings.
So, yeah, this is the first
step in the cascade.
And then, come author styles.
This is the more interesting part.
This is where the party
happens.
Before that, I want to talk
about shadow DOM really quick. Bear with me.
Shadow DOM allows you to attach
an internal DOM tree to an element.
This internal tree can have any arbitrary DOM structure,
which is hidden from the main DOM.
SO that unlocks some cool things
like encapsulated styling.
Even if you don't like using
Shadow DOM directly,
which is totally understandable,
it's still good to know
because many built-in elements
elements use Shadow DOM underneath,
And I've written this handy blog post,
if you want to learn more.
But yeah, essentially, I explain how
shadow DOM works here
and I have this animation showing
how the light DOM and Shadow
DOM are interleaved together.
Ok it's playing, cool. I have a
screen shot of the
details element, which shows that
The details element, which is built into HTML itself,
also uses Shadow DOM.
So even if you don't use it
directly,
you are using shadow DOM indirectly.
And yeah, the reason I bring
this up is
Shadow DOM styles cascade after the user-agent styles.
but before the rest of the page styles.
So if you have my-button component, which slots a
regular button, and you
style this button both from inside and
outside Shadow DOM,
the outside styles will win.
So the overall cascade order,
so far, goes something like
The user agent styles, the author styles.
And within the author styles, the Shadow DOM styles,
and then rest of the page styles.
There's also the inline style
attribute, which comes after these.
But that's like, not really part of the cascade.
The browser doesn't need to
resolve
the cascade in order to get the style attribute.
Because it's literally attached to the
element itself.
But yeah, now that
we understand Shadow DOM, we
can talk about the rest of the page.
The first and most simple concept
is order of appearance.
So for example, you can style a
button using an
an element selector and you can
make it hotpink. Pretty straightforward.
But what happens when
there's two of these rules?
The last one wins. This makes sense.
CSS is written, it goes from
top to bottom and the last one
overrides anything before it.
But these
element selectors aren't super useful
on their own.
What if you only want to style this
one particular button?
This is where I would use a
class instead of an element selector.
But when we do this,
we find that
the order of appearance seems
to not matter anymore.
The class selector wins over the element selector,
even if it comes before.
So what's going on here?
And the answer to that is
specificity.
Hopefully, I said that right.
Specificity.
I'm not going to go into too much detail here,
because
it's a complex, but pretty easily understood topic.
The gist of it is…
Specificity is a score made of three parts.
Starting from the right side,
elements and pseudo-element selectors
contribute to the
least significant part.
Classes, and attribute selectors,
and pseudo classes
go in the middle; and IDs go in the
most significant part.
So the browser will take this
score and
use it to determine which selector wins.
Chrome dev tools even shows you
the specificity
when you hover a selector.
So If I go and inspect this,
and I hover over a selector, you
can see it says, 2-0-1.
That's the specificity score.
So yeah, you don't have to
calculate it by hand,
essentially.
So in the previous example,
specificity of the button selector,
the button class was 0-1-0, but
the specificity of the element was 0-0-1,
so the button class wins because it's more specific,
despite order of appearance.
As you can imagine, with really large selectors,
the specificity would become a bit
cumbersome to manage.
That's why the general advice given to us is
keep specificity low.
And this is good advice.
We should almost certainly
avoid ID selectors, for example.
And we can still use them.
Like, instead of using #ID,
we can just use an attribute selector.
Or we can just make it a class
specifically for the thing
that we're selecting.
So it's easy to understand the problem with
high specificity, but…
Keeping specificity low can sometimes be challenging,
especially when you want to share styles between different
elements.
So you might, like,
you might be tempted to make
a single class for every variant of
the button.
But then each variant needs to share the
base styles of the button, right?
and that starts to become complicated.
Sometimes, we tend to go too
far with this advice,
where we want to keep specificity
not just low, but
totally flat, by only using
single class selectors.
This usually is done through a
convention like BEM,
or through tooling like CSS Modules.
And yeah, I've always just
found this kind of advice
a bit restrictive.
It kinda feels like using CSS
without the cascade.
So, yeah, for the rest of the
presentation,
I want to show you how much better things can
be with modern CSS.
The two topics that I would
broadly cover are
controlling specificity and
controlling the cascade itself.
Let's start with the easy one.
You might already know that you can
increase the specificity of a
class selector by chaining it
to itself.
You can even use CSS nesting to
chain nested ampersands,
and that way you avoid repeating yourself.
This can be be pretty useful when you need it,
but it only
increases the middle portion of the
specificity.
Now, this next part might kind
of blow your mind, but you can
use the :is pseudo-class
to make a huge
jump in specificity.
This :is pseudo class, it's
interesting.
It lets you group multiple selectors into a
select selector,
but it changes the specificity of the whole thing,
so that
only the strongest selector in the group counts.
What this means is, you can
have a class selector act
like it has the specificity of
the ID selector.
And this ID selector doesn't
even need to exist.
It can just be there, hanging by itself.
You can do the same thing even
easier
using the :not pseudo-class.
So this one requires you to use
the impossible selector, where
you can use two IDs because, remember, an
element can only have one ID.
So this selector would never
match, and we're saying,
never not match this selector.
So this will match the thing you chain it to.
I love this because
you can chain it to anything to scope it down, just
how much you want
while retaining the super high
specificity.
And if you chain it to the
universal selector, it'll match
everything while having the high
specificity that we want.
You shouldn't need this very often.
But it's so handy when you just
want to have certain styles,
have the highest priority.
So with that out of the way,
let's talk about decreasing specificity.
We know how to increase it,
but how do we decrease it?
Because that's kind of the goal, right?
We want to keep specificity low.
At least that's what everybody tells us.
So that's where the :where pseudo-class comes in.
:where is just like :is,
except it doesn't add to the specificity.
We can put an ID selector in
there, and it'll still have
zero specificity.
And just like :is, you can chain
it to other selectors
So you can have some parts inside the :where.
They don't count towards the specificity.
But the things that are outside do count.
There's one restriction here,
You can't put a pseudo-element selector
inside :is and :where,
but that's just a thing that you'll
get used to.
But yeah, in other words, we now have a
CSS-native way of writing any kind
of selector we want
with just the right amount of
specificity. That's awesome.
CSS is awesome.
The most obvious way to use
:where is when you want to
create zero-specificity selectors
for a CSS reset.
This kind of makes sense
becase you want the reset to have the
lowest cascade priority.
So you just put everything in :where.
And I actually built my own reset that
uses this technique.
And you can find it on NPM
under the @ACAB namespace.
With :where, you can make everything
zero specificity, but
maybe don't do that?
Zero is fine for resets, but
I would actually suggest coming up with
a desired specificity for
all of your other styles.
So you might want your global
style to be
no higher than 0-0-1.
And you can still use longer selectors there,
while restricting the specificity.
And yeah, you can--
The point here is, you can kind of just
control the specificity
while not having any restrictions
on how you're writing your CSS.
One thing I like to do is
Put everything that is nested inside the main rule,
put :where.
So that the whole block has a flat specificity,
and everything inside it has zero specificity.
So you're like going top to down,
everything is like using source order,
or order of appearance
and everything inside is flat.
So you have some specificity,
just not too much.
So yeah, if you haven't used :where,
give it a shot.
It'll probably solve many of your headaches, and
it's very well supported, all the way back to Safari 14.
And that brings us to my favorite topic:
Controlling the cascade using layers.
If you have a CSS rule, you can
wrap it in @layer.
This is an anonymous layer.
You can give it a name
and you can put other styles in it, too.
So far, so good.
But the interesting part is when
you use multiple layer statements
and put different --
or multiple layer blocks,
and put different styles in them.
So here, the second layer will
always beat the first layer.
It's kind of like order of appearance
but without the specificity part.
So here in the second layer,
we're using
the :where pseudo class,
but the first one still wins.
Or actually, I misspoke.
So in the second one, we're using
the :where pseudo-class
so it has a lower specificity,
but it still wins
because it's in a layer that
comes later.
So the layer order is kind of
resolved in the way
in the order that is defined.
Then there's unlayered styles
which always have the highest priority.
They'll win over all layered styles.
This might not feel intuitive,
but it kind of makes sense
and you'll get used to it.
The way I think about it is,
you want to start with
your lower-priority layers.
So you can put your CSS reset
in a layer
and leave everything else unlayered.
This kind of allows you to
slowly add layers to your codebase.
So yeah, that's kind of an
introduction to layers.
I still have some time so
I'm going to dive a little
bit deeper.
I mentioned layer order, it's…
The layers are prioritized in the
order that they first appear.
So if you have layer A and layer B
and then you write layer A again,
the rules inside the second occurrence of
layer A will still lose to layer B.
Because the layer A was already
defined all the way up there.
To make this more predictable, we can
separate layer statements from layer blocks.
The layer statement will define the order
and the layer blocks will contain the actual rules.
And you probably want to define the layer order
up front,
because all of your other styles, or --
before all of your other styles.
You can put the layer statements in the
beginning of your first style sheet,
but what I like to do is
I put it in a style tag, and I put
that style tag
all the way up in the head.
Beacause…
I don't trust bundlers to put my first style
sheet in the correct place.
So I just like, do it myself
before any other style sheets are linked.
So yeah, let's go even deeper.
So we can nest layers.
This functionality is built into layers,
so it's separate from CSS nesting.
You can nest layers without using CSS nesting.
And if you only want to
reference a nested sub-layer,
you can also use the dot syntax.
But it gets even more interesting
when you do use CSS nesting.
Because you can put a layer block
inside another CSS rule, like a class selector.
This is useful when you want to
style different parts of the same component
using different layers.
I do want to point out that this
CSS nesting
is a relatively new feature, so you
might want to use preprocessors
like PostCSS or Sass to transpile
this part out for you.
This pattern I find this useful, especially
when different part of the same component
need to have different priorities.
For example, I might have overrides
as a sublayer where I put
all my forced-colors styles
and print styles.
Because these should always beat
all of the other styles of the component.
Moving on, layers transcend
the idea of style sheets.
So you can reference the same
layer name in multiple CSS files
and they'll work just
like you expect
regardless of how they're imported.
So you might have a giant
components layer that is
referenced in every single one
of your components
and even within single file components,
in Svelte or Vue or Astro.
You can also import an external CSS file
into a layer.
The external CSS file doesn't even
need to contain any layers
And I want to give a shout out to
PostCSS-import here.
It can transform these import statements
into layer block statements,
and inline all of the contents of
the style sheets. And it even works
for remote URLs.
This is great for performance, mainly.
And I want to talk about Sass real quick.
Layers work just like you'd expect in Sass.
But when you want to combine
multiple Sass files into a single layer,
you need to use meta.load-CSS.
You can't use the use statement.
This was a recent update made
to Sass to ensure that
meta.load CSS is the canonical way to
use layers in Sass.
And finally, the most important slide.
You might have used the !important keyword to
win specificity battles in the past.
But we all know it's a
shameful hack
and the general advice is to
avoid !important.
And earlier, I already showed various ways
to increase specificity.
So if you want to just win a
specificity battle, then
use one of those techniques
instead of !important.
But the reason !important is interesting here is
it works kind of differently in layers.
The !important keyword is more
important
when used in lower priority layers.
This feels strange, but I think
Miriam was explaining earlier
that user-agents and user preferences
might want to declare some styles that
are legitimately important.
So even though all of the other
user-agent styles are less important,
they want to say
this particular thing should be more important
So it works similarly in layers.
So in a CSS reset, you might have a
rule that says
display: none !important
if the dialog is not open.
This kind of helps ensure that
subsequent layers can't accidentally override
the display when it's always meant
to be hidden.
I've done that accidentally
so many times where I set a
display: grid on the dialog
and it shows when it's not
supposed to be showing.
So now I handle that in my reset instead.
If you take everything we've
seen about layers so far,
our cascade order looks something like this:
the user-agent styles, then the page styles
and the Shadow DOM styles
with their layer order and unlayered styles.
And then the inline style attribute.
And then the important styles come
after all of that.
And since I'm running out of
time, I won't go into
too much detail here, but
important styles also have their own quirks,
in that
The user agent !important styles are more
important than inline style attributes
for example.
But yeah, I'm going to talk
about browser support real quick
So browsers…
I think, 2022 February is when
all browsers shipped cascade layers.
It was like a coordinated rollout
and it was very impressive to watch.
But if that still makes you uneasy,
there's PostCSS-cascade-layers
which polyfills
everything that we've
talked about so far.
And then, there's revert-layer,
I haven't talked about it so far
because it's such a vast topic.
But more importantly, it cannot be polyfilled.
So you might not want to use it yet.
I have a blog post on this topic.
And the only part I want to
mention just right now is that
if you're trying to use revert,
consider using revert-layer instead.
It works even when
you don't use cascade layers.
Then, there's some best practices.
I think I'll skip that.
Slides are stuck.
Oh, no. OK, sure.
There was an iframe here where
I was going to show that layers
and scope are different.
This is a CSS-tricks article
written by Miriam Suzanne.
And yeah, I really want to
emphasize this point, it's that
layers and scopes are different
things.
You don't want to create a
layer for every single component.
They can overlap.
So you can have
layers within the component.
But don't use it to
scope your CSS.
And I think we can wrap it up
here since I ran out of time.
I just want to mention one last
thing, that I think
Peter Griffin would really enjoy
using cascade layers.
So yeah, that's all.
If you want to learn more,
subscribe to my RSS feed,
and that's all from me.
≫ MIKE: I just learned so much
there.
It's like a pain I didn't know
I had where I feel like in a
lot of situations I add a
lot of specificity to kind of
wrangle the browser to do what
I want
when, actually, what I want is
layers, which
not aware of at all.
Yeah. It's going to take me a
while to get my head around
that.
≫ MAYANK: Yeah.
≫ MIKE: It's a completely
different paradigm.
≫ MAYANK: The thing I tell
people is, start with just the
reset . Put that in your, in a
layer, and if you have some
third party styles, put
that in a layer, you don't have
to migrate your whole codebase
to layers right away.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
And so the advantage of doing
that is -- let's take a
really basic reset of, I'm
setting the margin of HTML
element to zero.
So that's in my reset in a lay
er.
But now, I decide I actually
want some padding on my HTML
, so then, I can have HTML and
what's a nonlayer called?
Called the root?
Or?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah. HTML and :root
are going to be the same thing
usually.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, now I can set my
padding on the HTML and
it'll just work without any
more specificity?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah, and if you wrap
it in :where to make it zero
specificity, it'll still work.
Because unlayered styles win over
layer styles.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome. Very
cool.
Mayank, thanks for sharing that
today, I learned a lot. I'm
glad you're here.
≫ MAYANK: Thanks for having me.
≫ MIKE: All right.