We're going to talk about web
components today.
Full disclosure, I have ADHD, I
might bounce off screen as I
move around a little bit today.
Web components sit in this
uncanny valley.
Not quite react React
components, not with the grain
of the web either.
I think a lot of that is really
because we've been thinking
about and using them wrong.
Today, I want to show you what
I think is a better way to use
web components, or at least one
that works with the grain of if
web rather than against it.
Mike, thanks for that great
introduction, I'm
Chris Ferdinandi, you can find
me on gomakethings. com.
I teach how to make things in
the web through courses,
workshops , and daily developer
tips newsletter, and
I consult with amazing
companies. These days, that
means building custom web
components, like
I recently did for a project
with NASA.
The thing with web components,
they've been around for a
really long time. They were
first announced in 2011, which
is over a decade
ago, and they've been
supporting major browsers for
years.
Now, when they first came out,
a lot of folks thought they
were going to be the thing that
finally killed React.
And if you're watching in 2024
or beyond, you
know that they weren't. React
started to swallow up
everything.
And people often use them like
you would a React component.
So a lot of tutorials that you
see start with an empty custom
HTML element and then, they use
JavaScript to inject the HTML.
And don't forget about the
shadow DOM, there was a lot of
hype around using the shadow
DOM
to keep the HTML isolated from
the rest of the UI. This was
promoted as a key feature of
web components.
Of course, once you do that,
your HTML doesn't have
access to your global styles
sheets, so you need to inject
your CSS with JavaScript, too.
This approach feels a lot like
React but native
. But if you want React-like
components or React-like
experience, React and smaller
libraries
like Preact, honestly in my
opinion, they do it better.
That sounds weird coming from
someone who spends their whole
career
evangelizing vanilla
JavaScript, but the reality
that web components don't have
data reactivity, although you
can hack that in with
proxies, they don't have DOM
diffing. And they don't have
support for single- file
components.
Although, if you use a plugin
like Zach's web C,
you can kind of sort of make
that work. If you're a
developer who likes React, web
components often aren't React-y
enough.
But because this approach often
starts with an empty element
that relies on JavaScript to
render its content, web
standards and progressive
enhancement evangelists like
myself also dislike this
approach.
I think this is why it feels
like it's taken so long for web
components to catch on. For the
rest of this talk, I want to
show you a better way.
It's the approach that I use
with NASA and various other
clients to build web components
that are simple, reliable, and
that work more with the grain
of the web.
Here's the agenda for the rest
of this talk.
We're going to start by talking
about a new way to build web
components
or a different way to build web
components that's more with the
grain of the web. We're going
to dig into tips and tricks
that make working with web
components easier and we're
going to round things out by
looking at specific
examples, including building a
web component this way from
scratch .
Let's start by talking about a
new way about thinking about
web components that honestly
kind of old school. November of
last year, Jeremy Keith wrote
an article about this approach
. And he wrote, try not to
bring React mindset with you.
Do you really need to invent a
new component from
scratch or can you use HTML up
to the limit
and unHans enhance the markup?
It's a name that started to
stick and I'm seeing it pop
up more and more around the
web.
HTML web component is about
progressive enhancement.
So rather than an empty
element, you start with
perfectly functional HTML
. Here, we have a collection of
headings and some content that
goes with them.
Let's imagine we eventually
want this to be an accordion
component where clicking or
tapping on the heading causes
the content that goes with it
to get expanded or hidden.
We can use a web component for
that. As a convenient way to
enhance what's already there
into something more powerful
and interactive. And we start
that process by wrapping our
content in a custom element.
In this case, we'll call it
accordion group because that's
a very easy and obvious
description of what this thing
is going to be.
When the web component runs and
does its thing, the HTML and
the DOM ends up looking
different.
You end up with button elements
around the heading texts so you
have a focusable interactive
element, you get
some ARIA
attributes so that screen
readers understand the
interactions on the page . And
the content gets hidden by
default using the hidden
attribute.
But if this never actually ran,
you would still
have perfectly functional
markup. And that's really the
big difference between HTML
web components and the way they
were historically presented in
a lot of older tutorials talk
about them.
Now, this probably looks a lot
like old school DOM
manipulation. If you've been
around for a while, this is how
we used to build things.
And honestly, it really is, but
web components bring a lot of
benefits that make building
interactive UI a lot easier.
For starters, they're, in my
opinion, easier to write.
You get to write your HTML as
HTML rather than HTML in JS,
yuck.
And rather THARN
than unique selectors, yo you
combine your components once
and wrap your HTML in your
custom element.
You can even have multiple
versions on a page.
Each one automatically
instantiates as its own unique
instance.
Because functional HTML is
there, people get a usable
experience immediately.
And if your web component fails
to load for some reason, users
still have a perfectly
functional experience instead
of one that doesn't work.
Web components also let you
provide options and settings
declaratively in the markup.
This makes it a lot more
obvious what's happening just
by looking at the HTML.
The behavior isn't hidden away
in a JavaScript file somewhere.
And you can include multiple
instances, each with their own
settings , through the HTML
alone.
No more instantiating with
different selectors and
settings , often some
JavaScript file you have to
hunt down every time you want
to make an update.
Let's look at tips and tricks
that make working with web
components even easier.
Now, if you've never created a
web component before, I think
it's worthwhile to start by
kind of building
one, and we're going to start
with a custom element.
Here, I'm going to use the most
cliche of examples, a
countercomponent. So you get a
button, you click it, and the
text updates
to indicate how many times it's
been clicked or tapped or
activated.
This is honestly kind of a
terrible example for an HTML
web component, you're not
progressively
enhancing anything, the button
is absolutely useless without
the JavaScript. But it's a
really simple tutorial to
explain. So if you've never
worked with web components
before, it's a great way to
kind of wrap your head around
some of the concepts.
We're going to roll with it. We
start by wrapping some existing
HTML with a custom element. In
this case, count up.
And then, in our JavaScript
file, we use the custom
elements define method to
define a custom
element and associate behavior
with it.
You pass in the name of the
custom element as a string.
And just as a quick aside, web
component
, custom elements have to have
a dash in them, single word
elements are reserved for
browser native elements
. When you make your own, it
has to have one dash. We pass
the name in, here it's count
up.
And we pass in a class that
extends the HTML element class.
Your class needs to have a
constructer method in it. And
that runs automatically on each
element and creates
unique instance of your
component. And then, inside the
constructer, you always run the
super method first. This gives
you access to the properties
and methods of the HTML
element class that this class
is extending. And then, after
that, you can run any of your
custom code .
Now, web components provide
some useful ways
to handle that, and in
particular, they make
encapsulation really easy.
It's built in, even without the
shadow DOM. So while light DOM
elements, so things not in the
shadow DOM
will still be accessible,
they're scoped to your custom
element . And that provides
some unique benefits.
For example, in your web
component, this keyword refers
to the current
instantiation of the component
and the custom element wrapped
around it. You can define
properties on it. In this case,
we're setting a count property
of zero and we're going to
increase that every time the
button is clicked.
And, you can search for
elements inside
your custom element by scoping
them to the this keyword.
If I use the query selector
method on this, I'm looking for
the button inside my custom
element rather than everywhere
in the DOM. So it makes finding
elements in your component and
manipulating them way easier.
You don't have to use any
weird, special tricks.
You also get built in CSS
scoping, if you want it.
By using the light DOM instead
of the shadow DOM, your web
component will automatically
inherit your style sheet
styles, and in my opinion, one
of the biggest wins of this
approach because
shadow DOM styling, is a
painful experience. This gets
around this. But if you want to
scope styles in your web
component, you can use the
custom HTML
element as part of your
selector string.
Here, our button is going to
inherit all of the button
global styles and we can
override or modify
by prefixing with the count up
element.
You can even use CSS to detect
when the JavaScript is ready
with the defined pseudo class.
And if you define it with the
not pseudo class,
you can detect when the
JavaScript for the component is
not ready. If you've ever
written a DOM manipulation
library before and done
something like add a class to
the document or the body
element, that way you can
modify your styling depending
on whether the library has
loaded, or not, you don't have
to do that anymore.
Web components provide a
built-in way to detect that.
Using the defined pseudo class.
Web components also have some
built-in methods that make
handling events easier. With
the add event listener method,
you can pass in an object
instead of a callback function
as that second argument .
If the object has a handle
event method, that method will
automatically run response to
the event and receive the event
object as an argument.
Now, why would you do that
instead of a callback function?
A lot of it has to do with this
keyword we talked about
earlier. In a normal callback
function, the "
this" keyword doesn't refer to
the instance, it refers to
either the element
or the window object depending
on the context in which it's
used.
But in the handle event method,
this is the instance, which
means we can access those
properties like count that we
need to manipulate some things,
as well as if we had other
methods in our class, we could
run those, too, without having
to do things like use the bind
method
or some weird hacks with arrow
functions and timing around WHN
when we create callback
functions .
And in this particular
instance, we are increasing our
count by one. And then, we're
updating the text inside our
button to show how many times
it's been clicked.
If you need to listen to more
than one type of event, you can
create "on" methods in your
class with each of your
different event types and use
the handle event method to
automatically route them
. Here, I have an on click
event. And whenever that event
type fires, my
handle event method is going to
automatically
run that for me so you don't
have to use a bunch of if else
statements.
Set handle event to do the work
for you .
With web components, you use
custom attributes in
your HTML to define your
options
and settings . Say you wanteded
to define,
42, you could add a start
attribute and give it a value.
In your constructer, you can
use the
get attribute method to get
that attribute and the parse
float to convert it from a
string into a number, and
if that attribute exists and a
valid number, you use it for
this count instead of the
default of zero.
If not, you fall back. Users
don't have to use it but they
have the option.
What had makes this approach
particularly nice is you can
now have
multiple instances of your Web
Component on a page, each one
can have their own options,
settings, and properties
, you never have to write any
additional JavaScript.
And you can tell by looking at
the element what its specific
settings are and how you expect
it to behavior.
And while Web Components don't
have reactive data like React
or Vue does, they do have a
built
-in mechanism for detecting
attribute changes.
For example, let's say you
wanted to stop the count up
component from counting when
the pause attribute is added to
it.
First, you define an
array of attributes you want to
observe and assign them to the
static observed attributes
property. And you do this for
performance reasons. So if you
were watching every single
attribute that
could or could not be added or
changed on an element, it could
start to bog down the memory
and create performance issues.
You say, just pay attention to
these.
Whenever one of those
attributes is changed in some
way, the attribute changed
callback method runs. And this
will be triggered whenever an
observed method is added,
removed, or changes in value.
And it receives three arguments
automatically.
The name of the attribute, its
old value, and its new value.
If you want to detect whether
the attribute has been added,
removed, or changed, you can
check the old and new
value properties when an
attribute was just added, the
old value will be null because
there was nothing there before.
When it's been removed, the new
value will be null
. In all other situations,
where the value's just
changing, it will be a string.
It could be an empty string,
could have some sort of value
with it, but it'll be a string.
In this particular case, if the
attribute was removed, so if
the -- I'm sorry, if it was
added, rather , if the old
value was null, we're going to
remove our click event
listeners. We stop detecting
clicks.
When the attribute gets
removed, we are going to add
our click event listener back
on.
Let's look at some examples of
things HTML web components are
particularly great at.
Let's say you have a button and
you want to show or hide some
content when it's pressed.
This is a classic show/hide
disclosure component.
First, we'd start by wrapping a
custom element around it . The
obviously named show/hide.
Now, you have an easy way to
associate a button and content
that goes with it. But if
there's no JavaScript, users
still get the content. In our
JavaScript, we'll start by
defining our custom
element, we'll pass in
show/hide and our class that
extends the HTML element.
And then, inside the
constructer for that class,
we'll run the super method and
we'll define our properties.
Maybe we'll get the button
using the query selector method
on this . And then, we will get
the
content, the next element
sibling, and assign that to a
property, as well. That way, we
can access them later. Next,
the initial UI.
We'll add an ARIA expanded
value with the value of false.
This is an accessibility
requirement. So it conveys to
people who use screen
readers what type of
interaction they could expect
from that button and what the
current state of it and its
content are.
And then, we'll hide the
content using the hidden
attribute.
Now, the HTML UI looks like
this after a Web Component
instantiates and runs.
Next, we will add a click event
listener to our button.
And we'll do that by passing
the instance, this, into the
add event listener. That way,
we can take advantage of the
handle event method.
Under the ARIA show/hide
pattern,
it should have an expanded
value of true when it's visible
and false when it's hidden.
Inside our handle event method,
we can check the current value
of that attribute on our button
and show or hide the content
accordingly. If it has a value
of true, content is currently
visible,
we'll change it to false, and
we'll set the hidden attribute
to hide that content.
Otherwise, we'll set it to true
to show the content and
remove the hidden attribute so
you can see it.
Now, that we have a functional
component, we might try adding
some styling to make it look a
little bit nicer.
We might, for example, change
the button color based on
whether the content is hidden
or visible.
We'll give it maybe a blue
color as the default, and we'll
make it darker when ARIA
expanded equals true, which we
can do by using an attribute
selector in the CSS.
Because we only want this to
apply to our show hide
component, we will scope our
CSS to
that element. And maybe we want
to hide the button element
until our web component
JavaScript
loads since it requires
JavaScript to work.
It's functionless until the Web
Component starts. We can use
the not and defined pseudo
classes for that
. And display none on our
button to hide it.
Another example, we talked
about little bit earlier, Web
Components are great for
transform LG ing headings and
content.
No worries, users still have
access to all of the headings
and all of the content.
I'm not going to walk through
the code for the rest of these
because we would be here all
day. Just some more examples to
kind of get your brain going on
what
you can do with this approach
to web components.
You might also take a list of
anchor elements and their so
associated content and turn
them into toggle tabs. No
JavaScript? Users get a
perfectly functional collection
of anchor links and content.
One of my favorite uses,
though, is forms.
The project I did for NASA
involved building out an entire
app and it was done almost
exclusively
through Form Interactions. I
like to create forms that work
with old school server submits
and full page reloads by
default. So you provide an
action that points to
some sort of server pass, the
form sends its data
to that path and the server
does some stuff . And then, I
use Web Components to turn them
into
a A
JAX forms and show a status
message or update the UI
instead of reloading the entire
page.
Without JavaScript, you still
get a perfectly usable form or
in the case with the NASA
project, a perfectly usable
app. But with it, you get
something even better, faster,
snappier . If you
forget everything else about
this talk, and I really hope
you remember more than just
this, but if you only remember
one thing, I hope your key
takeaway is to start
with functional HTML and then
enhance with Web Components. If
you found this interesting, I
put together a bunch of
additional resources for
building HTML
Web Components on gomake things.
com, you can find boilerplates
and more. Thank you all so
much. This was a lot of fun.
≫ MIKE: Chris, that was
incredible. I'm going to agree
with a lot of the chat.
That's probably the best
introduction to Web Components
that I've heard.
≫ CHRIS: Thank you.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
I feel like just seeing that
and a lot of things click into
place.
Particularly, like the defined,
not defined, I haven't -- I
wasn't aware of that.
But it's such an elegant
solution to that problem .
I've just been adding classes
to things recently to -- JS on
or something like that.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, thank you.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
So yeah, what do you think the
-- what should we be excited
about in the web component
space
? Clearly we need more adoption
and awareness around this.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, so I'm
particularly pessimistic about
shadow DOM, in general, it has
valid uses.
But if you're someone who
enjoys that or wish you could
do more with
Shadow DOM but also you wish
you could do the HTML first
approach I described today,
it's now possible to use
declarative Shadow
DOM, so you can write the stuff
that's going to end up in the
Shadow DOM in your HTML rather
than having to historically
they would all have to be
generated through JavaScript.
So, you know, there's now a way
to do that without it. I think
that's pretty exciting.
Not specific to Web Components
itself, but one thing I really,
I think the biggest thing that
we're
missing from the web platform
as a whole is some sort of
method that allows diffing the
DOM and
selecting the API without
clobbering everything, right?
Where you say, here's an
element, what it should look
like, change just what needs to
get changed. We need that.
That, in my opinion, would be
the thing that really kills
React
. You know, until then.
≫ MIKE: Where do you think that
comes from?
The browser specification and
...
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, I don't think
I've even seen a specification
for that . I know there are --
I heard rumors there's maybe
some specs specific to Web
Components for doing something
like that.
Maybe, as a proposal, not like
anything that's on a track to
get built. But I would love
that just as a general, like,
thing for the
web, not just Web
Component-specific .
≫ MIKE: Yeah, that would be
incredible.
Zach was telling me recently
that React, latest version of
React has custom component
support, so maybe React --
≫ CHRIS: Finally.
≫ MIKE: Kind of meets in the
middle of Web Components and
brings a lot of the ideas to a
broad
er audience of web developers.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, that would be
wonderful. I think the toughest
thing with Web Components in
general is
really just if you're used to
thinking about things in a
React-y way, wrapping
your brain around the whole
this is
more...  React components are
everything in one place and Web
Components are separation of
concerns and each thing does
what it does best .
And it's a mental shift.
So, yeah, I would like to see
more of that.
I think one of the -- we're
starting to see more big
companies use Web Components,
maybe bigger open source
projects around it, I'm hoping
the tide is starting to shift.
And you have projects like
Enhance that use Web
Components as the foundation
for an entire static site
generator. That's pretty cool,
too.
≫ MIKE: Well, appreciate
everything you're doing to
evangelize
Web Components, that was an
incredible introduction to Web
Components.
≫ CHRIS: Thank you so much.