It's 11:11.
[Cheers and applause ]
11.
It's 11:00.
[ Applause ]
11.
I think it's 11:00.
[ Applause ]
It's 11:00.
11.
≫ Welcome. Welcome, welcome.
All you amazing 11ty people.
I'm incredibly excited to be
here today.
Hosting the first 11ty
Conference.
The inaugural international
symposium of making websites
real, real good.
I'm Mike. I'm going to be the
host for today.
And I'll be joined shortly by
Mr. Zach Leatherman himself,
creator of 11ty.
We have an exciting range of
speakers, developers and
technologists from across the
web joining us today. And I
can't wait to get into it.
The 11ty community is an
incredibly supportive and
welcoming community.
We have a couple of first-time
speakers presenting today.
So, please show your
appreciation and support and
encouragement for all of the
speakers.
Code of conduct is listed on
the conference website. If you
haven't already, check it out,
take a moment to read through
it . And In brief, we're
committed to being
as accessible as possible and
kind and welcoming to everyone
involved in the symposium.
All of today's talks are being
live captioned by White Coat
Captioning.
Which we're really grateful
for, it enables more people to
engage with
today's amazing speakers and
their ideas for the future of
the web.
So feel free
to share on the board and ask
questions in the
chat and engage in social media
. Speaking of social media, if
you're wearing your 11ty
T-shirt, do feel free to share
that on socials
. With the hashtags 11ty or
11ty Conf, we'll be running
sticker giveaways with using
those hashtags.
So, we've got Zach coming in
about ten minutes to do the
keynote for today.
So, let's do two things
before then. I want to hear
from chat, what is your
favorite 11ty feature?
And where are you pulling from
today?
We've had a few people talk
about that. So let's have a
look.
Plymouth, UK, Switzerland,
El Salvador. New York City,
Puerto Rico, Ukraine
, Detroit, New York City
.
Past Pasadena, New Zealand .
This is a global conference,
isn't it?
And I think that's one thing I
really love about 11ty is, is
it's the community
it's so supportive and
welcoming. Right.
Let's see what people are
saying. Hello from France.
Ireland, Pennsylvania,
Argentina,
Germany,
my favorite is
Dartacascade. I think it's the
first thing that blew my mind
about 11ty.
Just coming from a world
where you basically had data
files and collections.
And getting to experience the
flexibility and control you
have
over the data cascade is just
incredible .
Hello from Greece.
Dynamic Global Data Files.
Yeah, another amazing one.
That's something I've been
messing around recently, like
pulling in external
data useing fetch and turning
it into a data file and doing
all sorts of interesting
processing on it.
That's, yeah. Another one
that's blowing my mind.
Tampa, Florida,
UK, Louisiana, hey, Raymond.
Pagernation, another one in
most other esthetic site
generators is tricky or it's
bolted on.
Yeah 11ty, using collections
and , it's nice.
So many templating, tuning in
from Detroit. Hey, Brian.
Yeah, just the flexibility you
have on those templating
languages . You get to use --
you're
not prescribed a particular
template language, use what it
is for you.
Bingo cards, hey, David.
What else we got? Texas,
London, another New Zealand,
Colorado. Northwest UK. Lots of
UK tuning in.
Very cool. Seattle, Washington.
Switzerland, Austin,
Pagernation in Chicago.
Utah, Belgium, Switzerland,
Chicago.
This -- seems to be 11ty hubs.
I wonder why that is.
Norway, Maryland, Mexico,
Vancouver, Boston, my favorite
feature is the possum.
[ Laughter ]
Upstate New York, Arizona,
France,
[ Laughter ]
I don't actually use 11ty, but
I love your community and I'm
in Hamburg , Germany.
El Salvador. Germany,
Argentina, Charlottesville,
yeah, incredible. I can't, I
can't, there's
way too many to read here.
That's awesome.
Favorite feature for me is how
it fits my way of thinking,
to know what I do, now only it
does it.
Yeah, that's the beauty of it.
Kind of gives you the tools to
do what you want and you can --
in a lot of ways, you're
putting together your own
esthetic site generator.
My favorite feature is the
docs, so easy to get going,
such
a cool community, cozy vibes.
Yeah, well said.
I Loe love I can template all
random templating languages are
picked up here. Nice.
11ty image is good stuff.
Yeah, hey, Wiz.
Yeah, it's after doing this
kind of manually and building
my own plugin to do image
optimization, I wish I
knew about 11ty image sooner.
My favorite feature's being
able to write so easy.
You know, that's what we're all
here for.
The before/after processing
hooks. Yeah.
Like, I haven't done a huge
amount with those.
But just being able to pull in
data and process it after the
build .
I've been exclusively using
WebC, I've just started
dabbling. And it's just a
completely different way of
thinking about
static site generation. Very
cool. The speed, the best
thing.
Just
use Esther, you know what I
mean. Not sure what that means.
[ Laughter ]
I love writing markdown but
web component support might be
off (inaudible) myself.
From the US government, 11ty
has
made it so personal . Do not
have to think about responsive
images anymore.
It's massive, right?
If you think of a technical web
page, like most of the transfer
's probably going to be in
images. And the probably
there's a good chance they're
not going
to be super optimized.
Whereas 11ty image gives us a
lot of that for almost free.
So many great features, just
choose one. Just choose one.
The speed.
Is that the speed of the build
or the speed of the website
? Both?
The amazing wealth of plugins
cannot be overstated. Hey,
Chris.
I love global data files.
Here we go, the docs, let's
make the docs link a little
bigger.
Yeah, I think I was looking at
it last night.
It's -- I was measuring like
120, 130 pixels, maybe
by the end of this conference,
we can convince Zach
to -- I mean, maybe doubling
it's a stretch goal, but I
think if we can
get 20% bigger out of this
conference, I think that's a
success.
Stability . I'm here for
comments, me, too.
The fetch plugin is amazing. It
makes pulling in data so easy.
Yeah.
And just having the caching
all kind of handled very nicely
and seamlessly, and yeah.
Just takes a lot of that load
off. Like, I've been finding
just putting 11ty in front of
an API that maybe
you have some sort of limit
that you can only do 50
requests of this API.
Like putting 11ty fetch in
front of it and having it is
almost like a cache in front of
the API.
Really interesting, cool use
case, and you don't have to
necessarily output HTML.
. You can output the responses
of API and JSON.
11ty is my go-to, so easy and
fast to get projects up and
going. I heard about images.
There's another docs. Docs dig.
Should scale the docs link with
scroll animation. Yes.
So it just -- maybe it starts
off as a pixel that by
the time you reach it, we're
looking at a full page. Yeah.
100VH docs link.
Make it the viewport.
Yeah. Why not match the size
the font size of these?
Yeah.
The 11ty T-shirt is so comfy,
that's what we love.
Does the docs have an IPO ? I'd
invest in it.
Yeah, what other open source
projects has a bigger docs
button? That's what I want to
know.
I think 11ty's probably top of
its class in that category.
All right. Thanks for all of
the great responses. We're
going to move on to the keynote
speaker for today. We've got
Zach Leatherman, creator and
maintainer of 11ty.
Zach is an international
speaker at 25 different
conferences in 9 countries and
topics
including Jamstack, web
components, responsive web
design and web performance.
Anyone that follows Zach on
social media also knows
he's self-proclaimed number one
super fan of React . Today he's
here to tell us about current
and future state of 11ty.
Let's do it.
Zach?
≫ ZACH: What up?
≫ MIKE: Welcome, welcome, so
excited for this talk.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, this is going to
be amazing.
The chat is just kind of
blowing my mind right now.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
≫ ZACH: What a way to start.
Just hearing all of everyone's
favorite features is just kind
of, I don't know, humbling me
right now.
Because I remember the origin
of all of those things that
people are talking about .
So it's wild to see it resonate
like that with folks .
≫ MIKE: Very cool. All right.
I'll let you get into it.
≫ ZACH: All right. Let's do it.
All right, what's up,
everybody? Thanks for joining,
this is incredible
. I'm just kind of blown away
at what's happening right now.
I never would've thought I
would have -- I would be
attending a conference about
11ty .
It's just amazing to think
about.
We've sort of been around for 7
years now.
It's a long project, and we've
got more to come.
So as Mike said, I'm Zach. This
is my visual resume.
I started 11ty back in 2017.
And in some respects, it was to
facilitate my personal website
. And,
yeah, it was originally on
WordPress back in 2007. I
switched to Jekyll
around 2012, 2013, and yeah,
migrated to 11ty shortly after
launching. I do have some more
background in the JavaScript
world.
I ran a JavaScript meetup for
many years.
And we did a conference,
Nebraska JavaScript conference.
So yeah, sort of been in the
JavaScript ecosystem for a long
time. I think a lot of folks
might be aware of my work
with web fonts and web
performance.
And yeah, hopefully, we can
bring that to 11ty in the
future . And so, maybe
some folks are also familiar
with this meme from XKCD.
It's sort of this teetering
structure
. And the caption is a project
some random person in
Nebraska's been
maintaining and, yeah,
I think that in some respects
represents 11ty.
But I also think that 11ty's a
little bit more stable than
that little, tiny block may
represent. We've been around
for 7 years.
We've had so many, so many
releases.
And folks have really
identified with how stable it
is and how few breaking changes
that we
ship. Because I don't like
breaking changes myself.
I use 11ty for so many projects
and I don't want to have to go
back and update those either.
So, hopefully, you also feel
that. And there are kind of
many frameworks and tools and
site generation things that
exist on the web right now.
And there's kind of something
for everyone, right?
You can pick your flavor of
tool that you identify with
most, that you get the most
benefit out of.
That you get the most value
from. And I think that's a
great thing.
There are frameworks that maybe
represent someone that might
want to send a billionaire to
the moon.
Not for me, there's a framework
that might represent someone
that thinks this social network
is still cool.
Not necessarily for me.
A framework that maybe it wants
to live in a world in which
this is a normal thing. Not
necessarily for me.
And then, there are other
frameworks that really see the
value in Google Reader and
Indie web and having
information accessible for
everyone, and RSS and sharing
those things online and a root
in HTML and not necessarily
trying to funnel everything
through JavaScript first.
In my mind, there's kind of
this two dimensional graph
here.
And you can place all of
different tools in different
spaces on this graph.
On the left, you can see
dynamic servers
. This sort of moving away from
static site generation. On the
right, we have static sites
. Folder full of files, as I've
said.
And then, the top represents
HTML first, multi-page
applications that we've
seen the marketing pivot to and
then, on the bottom, we see
JavaScript first tools
. BUND
Bundler based tools, that
everything flows through
JavaScript code you write and a
lot of those are
application-based.
On the bottom left, we have the
most popular
site generation tool right now,
NextJS. It lives in that
JavaScript-first world. And you
can use Next. js in kind of
different ways.
They've added what they call
server side rendering mode,
which allows you
to serve HTML first in your DRK
-- and
code downloaded by sites that
you build. But it still has its
roots in single page
applications.
Next also has a static export,
which kind of goes more to the
right as a static site.
You can use Next to import a
static site.
Importantly, I've learned that
does not include Next image and
we'll go into that a little bit
later. I thought that was very
interesting that you can do
HTML, you can do JavaScript,
you
can do CSS, but you can't do
images. And that doesn't come
out of the box.
And 11ty wants to exist in this
top right quadrant, right. We
want to be HTML first.
We want to create websites that
are multipage applications,
above all, we want to be a
static site generation tool
. That's what our roots is.
That's what I really believe is
the place that 11ty does the
best work.
And, at the end of the day, I
think, static sites
really have this amazing
benefit of being the most
secure, the fastest to serve,
and they have a lot of these
very
great benefits that, yeah, I
think we are really doubling
down on right now
. Now, 11ty has kind of dipped
its toes into more dynamic use
cases.
We had an Edge plugin and
Serverless plugin.
But we're sort of regrounding
ourselves into the static
world.
And trying to be the best that
we can be. And so, there's all
of these
different site generation tools
that exist. And some of them
have sort of created
different modes of use. Most of
developing sites to where
they can serve more than one of
these
quadrants simultaneously, or at
least with the same or similar
codebases.
But importantly, 11ty really
wants to be the best that we
can in the top right.
We want to be the best static
site generation tool that we
can be.
And it's been so amazing to see
the response to 11ty over the
years.
We have over 72,000 open source
repositories on GitHub.
People that are using 11ty.
Over 16,000 GitHub stars ,
which is amazing. We have over
21,000 friends online across
all of our social media
accounts.
And we're now up to 8. 7
million downloads on NPM, which
I think is
incredible.
And a lot of sort of larger
enterprise customers have
started to use 11ty, too.
Some big names,
like CERN has a web site use ing
11ty, NASA,
their website is built with
11ty.
And it's, yeah, again, so
incredible to see.
To see the logo cloud that you
can find on 11ty. dev that has
all of these
. And I think one of the core
features of 11ty are
the secret sauce to 11ty is
that we don't have a moat by
design. A lot of times, when
you have frameworks
that have investors or some
monetization behind it, some
more aggressive monetization
behind it, they want you to
have a moat.
And a moat is something that
exists in this framework to
keep you using the framework.
Whether that be a --
a language format that only
runs in your tool and doesn't
run independent of your tool.
Or that be some more runtime on
request pieces , like image
optimization.
Maybe, the vendor that creates
the framework also sells you on
request image optimization. And
they charge you by the image.
And, again, we'll go into that
a little bit later.
And, the thing we've been
working
on for so long, I want to say
almost a year now is our next
major release, 11ty 3. 0.
It runs in Node 18 or newer.
And yeah, I'm super excited to
tell you all about it.
Just the number one thing, and
I'll maybe have a very
interesting number of points to
make in this talk. But the
number one thing is that it's
written in ESM. ESM is sort of
the more standard way to write
JavaScript that works in a
variety of different contexts
and runtimes.
So this is sort of a way for us
to prepare for the future.
To allow 11ty to run in a bunch
of different ways. And a bunch
of different tools.
And yeah, I think it's an
important thing. Although, the
subtleties of it may not be as
convince ing as we might want,
as
developers. Practically, it
just kind of means that you're
converting module
.exports in your code and
JavaScript code
to be export default or named
exports at the bottom.
You just can change it to
export.
So it's -- there isn't too much
change that happens when you're
migrating your code to ESM. But
I think it is important for the
future. And if you look at the
NPM ecosystem
right now, there's this graph
from Titus,
sort of maintain statistics on
how many projects are using
what mode. There's only 11. 7%
on NPM are using ESM first.
There are some people that are
dual publishing as the other
alternative in the thing that
most folks use is common JS .
So some folks are publishing
both
ESM and common JS
simultaneously. Not going to do
that.
And, some folks are using a
bundler to precompile their
common JS to ESM for usage.
And so, if you look at this
graph, you might be a little
worried that 11ty is using ESM,
right, because it doesn't
seem to be all that common in
packages that are published to
NPM.
And if you look the a some of
the existing frameworks out
there right now, you can see
11ty and Astro are kind of on
the left.
We're doing ESM first . Next,
Gatsby
, sort of use a bundle r
approach . And Next. js is
still using common JS. And so
there's sort of a wide variety
of things here.
So what does this mean for your
project?
You can still keep using your
existing configuration file.
project as is, you can still
keep using CommonJS with 11ty.
So you don't need to worry
about that.
So if you look inside of your
11ty configuration file right
now, you can keep using this.
It isn't a problem, you don't
have to migrate your code over
to use ESM, just because 11ty
is using ESM, doesn't mean that
you need to.
And yeah, just practically
speaking, you can import 11ty.
So one of the main problems
that people see when they're
using ESM and
CommonJS, you can't require an
ESM package.
So if you use any of the
bundled 11ty plugins that are
already included.
You will need to change your
configuration file to look
like this if you are going to
be using Node 18 . Now, Node is
actually adding support
for importing
, requiring ESM packages to
Node. It's an amazing thing.
It's come out in the last month
or two. And you can use this
today with NOED 22
with this command line flag
experimental requirement module
.
So if you want to not change
any of your code at all, you
can use this approach.
It really doesn't take much to
upgrade your project to use
11ty 3. 0.
Here's my personal website
. It is, I think, three files
were changed. I changed my node
minimum.
I changed the import to be a
dynamic import inside of my
configuration file.
And then, my package JSON, I
pointed to the new version. And
again, your existing
CommonJS code should work
pretty much as is.
Especially, if you're not using
the bundled plugins.
So you can use ESM if you want
to convert your
configuration file to ESM, you
can do that, and this is what
the new syntax will look like,
export default.
And, this might be the most
straightforward way to do it
because
there isn't any special dynamic
import that you need to do, you
just import your plugins
directly from the 11ty package.
And yeah, this is great. This
is maybe the most
straightforward way to do it.
But importantly, you can
incrementally migrate to ESM,
too . You don't have to -- it's
not an all or nothing thing
. On the left side, we see your
existing project might be using
CommonJS
. You can use ESM with a . an
extension.
If you want to start with ESM
first, you can add type module
to the package JSON, and then
use, then the default .
js will be interpreted as ESM
and you can use .
CJS to fall back to the common
JS format in Node.
So you can really sort of use
either of these approaches .
And it really, I think, gives
you an incredible amount
of flexibility when you're
dealing either with legacy
projects or new projects from
scratch.
So one of the things I'm most
excited to tell you all about
today is the new features that
we're shipping that we've
already shipped to 11ty image.
And I think this is just super
exciting . I'm very excited
about it.
We have this new image
transform plugin.
So with just a couple of lines
like config,
we'll automatically transform
your HTML and do image
optimization and image
processing for you.
And it's all sort of handled
for you out of the box.
Which I think is incredible.
And I'm using it everywhere.
So this means, no more worrying
about short codes, no image
short codes, no worrying about
asynchronous context versus
synchronous context.
A lot of people that used
handlebars, that's
a synchronous language, it
couldn't do asynchronous short
codes. We had this complex way
to do it. We don't need to
worry about that anymore. Use
the transform method and it
handles with all of your
templating languages .
So you never have to manually
add a width or height attribute
to an image, again, not even
for mode images.
This is a super unique feature
that isn't available in a lot
of alternative frameworks. A
lot of them require you to do
static imports or for
remote images, you have to add
your width and height manually.
Not at 11ty images, we do it
all for you, you don't
have to worry about it.
And the super really cool,
exciting thing that we shipped
just very recently is this new
transform On
Request feature. This is given
to you, it's automatically
enabled for you.
When you use 11ty in serve
mode,
we have a dynamic on request
piece that will transform your
images for you when they're
requested in the
browser, not as part of the
build.
So when you do dash dash serve,
we only optimize images that
are visited in the web browser.
And then, on the right, we have
the same when
you run a normal 11ty build,
not in server or local
development mode, when you run
a normal 11ty build,
you get this full standard
build output that you'd expect.
So the right side is sort of
the way it work ed before, the
left side is new for Serve
mode.
And you can set your own widths
here, if you want to do is that
that. And we sort of handle all
of that for you, right ?
It works the same. If you want
to set specific widths
for an individual image, you
can do that with the 11ty
: Widths attribute .
And you don't have to worry
about image versus picture,
either. We automatically swap
that for you based on how many
formats you're using, how many
sizes you're using, you don't
have to worry about that.
So as an example, if you only
want to output a
web P by default, 11ty does
JPEG.
But if you want one format, you
get the image tag, if you want
multiple, we switch to the
picture tag.
And what this gives us is near
zero build cost for local
development , which I am super
excited about.
Here's what it looks like. If
you have a thousand images
running through the 11ty
image pipeline right now, it
would take about 6 seconds to
build on my personal machine.
These are just benchmarks. I
ran on my machine.
And then in serve mode, it
takes less than a second to
start this the server.
Even with 1,000 images going
through that image optimization
pipeline. Which I think is
incredible.
We have another great feature
called sv
gShort Circuit.
A great new feature where it'll
actually compare the size of
that svg
versus the counterparts, the
web P, your JPEG or whatever.
And will throw out the ones
that are bigger than the svg.
So we do a file size comparison
and say, hey, is this svg? So
we have this complex Mexico
flag here.
Is the version of that flag
smaller in a vector format? We
prefer one over the other.
You can upload as many, or you
can get a small svg, and we'll
keep that for you.
So here's the classic tiger,
only about 20
kilobyte, we keep just the svg
in an image tank for you, which
I think is great.
We have some cool configuration
options coming in 11ty 3.
0, asynchronous work in your
callback function, which I
think is great.
We have this new config export
that you can do. So a lot of
times folks will
return an object inside of
their configuration callback.
And now, you can export that
and save your configuration
file.
And that is just an easier way
to organize your code and
allows us to access that a
little bit earlier and keep it
consistent in your config.
We have new set import
directories, set
output directory methods. We
have, also, those for includes
and layouts and
every directory you might want
to set, we have a method for
that.
We have a new virtual templates
feature, which allows you in
configuration
to create a virtualized
template. And this is a super
exciting feature.
Now, it allows you to create,
and will allow plugins to
create content in your 11ty
sites,
as well, which I think is
great. There was sort of an
example of how to block all of
the
AI spiders that come to your
site, and now, we can have a
plugin that does
that for you and generates your
robot txd for you.
I think that will be great for
the RSS plugin, as well.
There's a bundler, plain
text bundler, and you can add
plain text to
that bundle and we'll create
page-specific bundles for that
code.
To add a page to CSS bundle.
And web CSS is using this, but
it's coming to Core, as well.
This is how you output those
bundles.
Yeah, gets all of the CSS
that's added to that bundle for
the page, and then, you can add
it to a style block.
Or you can create your own
bundle file, if you want to
bundle that into an external
file, as well.
We have a great new plugin that
allows you to link to input
files . So files on your file
system, which I think is
amazing
. You can link to your markdown
file and it'll translate that
to the URL for you, allows your
project to be a little bit
more stable and less brittle
with your URLs as you change
them.
We have great new things coming
to data. We have sort of Node
front matter syntax.
Importantly, you can do
JavaScript data using the 11ty.
js template syntax type.
But now, you can do this in any
template syntax language.
You can use arbitrary
JavaScript. Which I think is
super powerful.
I first noticed this in the
Astro project, and I really
like it. So now, we have it.
You can also get act says to
the raw input of a
access to the raw input of your
file.
11ty works in Deno, which I
think is really great . Here's
an example of that.
And because it works in
Deno, now have actcess to JSX.
And here's an example of adding
a custom template
syntax that uses the render to
string
API to render JSX in your 11ty
project .
Bundlers. 11ty is still bundler
compatible, but we're also
bundler decoupled. We don't,
sort of, buy into
first party bundler at 11ty's
core. And I think that's
important to keep 11ty
independent moving forward.
But you can use bundlers in
11ty,
if you go out to our docs right
now, there's a great section on
using custom templates to do
that.
And just some stats on the 11ty
3. 0 version.
Again, dropped our node
dependency on additional 13.
3 megabyte, at about 22
megabyte for node modules right
now, which I think is great.
And this is far smaller than a
lot of the alternatives out
there right now. We've reduced
our dependencies to 176
, and I think that's not
necessarily the
most important metric, but I
think it is a great way to have
stability on the project.
We are pretty fast to install,
as well.
So just some benchmarks, it's
about 4. 3 seconds to install
11ty 3. 0.
And almost a minute to install
Gatsby, which
adds up, for sure.
I did run -- update the
performance benchmark. So we
had some interesting numbers
there.
How long's it take each one of
these tools to generate 4 ,000
markdown files? 11ty, less than
2 seconds, Hugo less than 1
second.
So 11ty is about, I want to
say, two times Hugo. But you
get a lot for it, right?
You get a lot of extra access
to the JavaScript ecosystem.
A variety of template syntaxes,
as well
. And yeah, I think 11ty does
really stand out in terms of
our build performance.
But the number one thing, I
think, and
11ty is sort of known for and
has little, very little to do
with me. 11ty is known for our
community and people.
We have so many people that
have built things with 11ty on
our authors' page.
We have people that have braved
the leaderboards, which is
pretty incredible.
We have so many hundreds of
sites that are 400 on
lighthouse. We have so many
open collective supporters, and
I
really appreciate everyone that
has put money to 11ty. It's
such a vote of confidence.
We have our folks helpful on
discord, our community
moderators and people that have
answered questions
for folks that are coming in to
ask, I don't understand how
this works, please, help me.
Anyone that has answered a
question on Discord or social
media or anyone that has helped
anyone else
with -- helped someone else
with 11ty is such
an amazing, big help to the
project.
We have our 11ty meetup folks
that run the 11ty
Meetup, we have Bob that ran
the 11ty
Bundle site, which is sort of
an aggregate, ing a aggregation
of all of the 11ty resources,
which is such a huge task.
Thank you, Bob, that's so
amazing.
And just some amazing folks on
the issue tracker, as well,
Raphael and Peter just have
helped out for so much over the
years.
And then, we have the people
contributed on GitHub. So many,
so many people, thank you to
everyone that has
just even if you've just fixed
a typo on the docs , that's
hugely important.
And then, our conference
organizers, David, Olivia, and
Mike, just really appreciate
y'all.
Shout out to James, y'all
, maybe are aware of the 11ty
possum , this came from James.
It started as the cat on the
balloon. And it changed to the
possum.
And we've sort of iterating on
different mascots over the
years.
And yeah, that came from James.
And I do just want to recognize
CloudCannon because I think
they have played such a huge
role in the 11ty community.
Especially over the last year.
Without CloudCannon, this
conference would not exist.
That's very easy thing for me
to say.
And, yeah, without CloudCannon,
the 3.
0 release would not be shipping
on the timeline that we're
aiming for.
And importantly, with
CloudCannon, they're already
ready for the 3. 0 release.
We've put in the work at
CloudCannon to make CloudCannon
's configuration ESM
compatible, make it work with
our new async configs, and so,
that's ready to go .
From day one, which I think is
amazing.
And just from a personal level,
I really, really, really
appreciate d the folks at
CloudCannon. They're super
helpful. They're super nice.
They have been champions for
accessibility.
I think you've probably seen
some folks online talking about
how CloudCannon has really
iterating
on our accessibility and trying
to do some really great work in
that space.
And they've been super amazing
champions for static sites,
generally. You should go out to
the future of Jamstack. org and
look at the community that
we're building there.
I think that is a super
important thing.
To pick up the Jamstack
community and elevate it to
something new .
And so, just to wrap up,
there's -- it's just such an
interesting world right now.
We have nothing but algorithmic
timelines on social media, we
have for you pages just
shoveling content
at us, we have large
language models generating
content for us. I really think
that folks that are making and
hosting and having full control
of their own content on the web
is so powerful.
In a way, I think it's very
subversive, too.
So just ask yourself, what do
you want to build on the web
? What would you like to grow?
What would you like to see the
next generation of the web be?
And I think 11ty is
a great place to help you move
in that direction.
So let's get our hands dirty
and, I guess, keep building for
the web.
Thanks, everybody.
≫ MIKE: Zach, that was
incredible.
That just the 3. 0 release is
exciting.
There's so much packed into
there.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, and I didn't put
it all in there.
I honestly have no idea how
much time I used. I'm so sorry.
But yeah.
There's so much more to talk
about, too.
Yeah, no,
≫ MIKE: Yeah, I can't wait.
What sort of timeline for the
3. 0 release?
≫ ZACH: I really worked hard to
get the first beta out today,
but we didn't quite make it.
There's a couple of minor
things I'd like to clean up.
But I would like to have the
beta out within the month.
That's definitely doable.
Yeah, and that's what we're
working toward.
≫ MIKE: Very cool.
Nice, OK.
Let's keep rolling. We've got a
lot of speakers to get through.
Just before we do,
CloudCannon has teamed up with
11ty to give away prizes. You
can enter to win at CloudCannon
.com 11ty
Conf, up to the value of
$5,000, plus a 30% discount for
3 months.
For second prize, ten lucky
winners will receive a 30
% discount on three months on
any other CloudCannon plans.
You can head over to
CloudCannon.
com/11tyConf to enter that
draw. And yeah, more
information there.
≫ ZACH: Great.
≫ MIKE: We're going to get the
next speaker ready. And then
we'll keep this thing rolling.
So, just from Zach's talk, what
are people most excited about
in the 3. 0 release? I heard a
lot of images.
I think that's pretty mind
blowing
. Just how easy that's going to
be,
especially in dev, just
speeding up that process.
Yeah. Very, very cool.
So, let's move on to our next
speaker. Next, we have Miriam.
Miriam is an artist, developer,
and open source
web, she's a cofounder of
OddBird
and expert on the CSS working
group,
developing new web standards
like cascade layers, container
queries and scope. And member
of the SaaS core team.
Offline, she might be repairing
clocks, knitting socks,
or creating hybrid performances
with teacup.
I'm looking forward to finding
out more about CSS and how
it balances its constraints and
the task of collaborative
styling.
[ Applause ]
Hey, Miriam, welcome.
≫ MIRIAM: Thanks, how are you?
≫ MIKE: I'm doing well.
Really excited for your talk.
Interested to know more.
≫ MIRIAM: Great.
≫ MIKE: Over to you.
≫ MIRIAM: All right.
Yeah. We're going to be talking
about the origins of the
web, but especially design on
the web using
CHSS, cascading HTML style
sheets proposed
by Hokum Lee in 1994. This is
still archived online. You can
read it. I recommend it.
It's fascinating, the original
design of the language.
But this wasn't the only
proposal for design on the web.
And it wasn't the first
It was actually based on
several existing proposals like
the one built into the Viola
browser, or this easily
parsable format where I have
no idea what's going
on, equals 14, I don't know.
But CSS solved a major problem
for this new platform. Not a
technical problem exactly, but
a
philosophical problem,
political, like all of the
decisions
we make when we're designing a
new platform or interface.
The first web browser,
developed by CERN,
called the hyperbrowser www.
editor was developed for the
fancy machine for this graphic
interface , but you can't make
a worldwide web by saying
it works on my machine and
everyone else is a edge case.
They hired Nicola Pello to
design, it's text only, you
don't have to install it. Any
device with an internet
connection can log into the
CERN servers and browse the
web. This becomes the mission
statement.
Web for all, web on everything.
And everything is a lot of
things.
There's so many different
things that the web is on. And
that includes devices without
any screen or
visual display at all as well
as screen readers, which do
read the screen.
So are sort of a combination of
interfaces .
If we really want this to work,
web for all web on everything,
then we get some interesting
constraints.
And these are documented on the
first website, the HTML
documentation that was launched
around 1991.
And is also still online. You
can go read that, as well.
And it says browsers should
ignore tags, which they do not
understand and ignore
attributes which they do not
understand of tags which they
do.
So, oh ...  I'm afraid...
let's go to it here.
Edit that on Codepen, will it
let us? Yes.
Zoom in on that a bit.
≫ MIKE: We just have your
slides at the moment. You might
need to share another window.
Myrrh
≫ MIRIAM: OK. Share this tab
instead.
No, wait, how do I do that?
Present.
Share a whole window. That's
what I want.
Sorry about that.
≫ MIKE: Nice.
≫ MIRIAM: Great.
Yes.
So browsers should ignore tags
they don't understand, so you
can see here, hopefully, in
this
code I've inserted a lot of
tags that aren't real
. They're fake tags, I made
them up and the browser's
ignoring them and displays the
tags it understands and
displays the content inside of
those tags . Also ignoring
attributes I made up.
That's become very useful as we
start doing web components and
custom attributes. This was
planned from the beginning.
The goal is to protect content
over code. The code is
optional, the content is
essential.
Whatever else happens, browsers
should protect the content.
And that's why we can still see
this first website on modern
browsers.
And we can also load modern
browsers, modern websites on
the first browser. This is an
emulator you can go play with
of the www. Browser. You don't
see -- sorry, that's a lot of
noise. You don't see CSS in
images, but all the text is
there. You can see via
international symposium
website, and my cascading style
systems workshop website, they
load fine. And the content is
preserved.
This limitation becomes even
more dramatic for graphic
design. In order for HTML to be
a common language between all
platforms
, we can't have any
device-specific markup
or anything which requires
control over fonts and colors.
That's in the original
documentation web design
will never happen, at least in
the graphic sense.
And the problem isn't styling
documents online, that's easy
enough and all of the early
browsers provided internal
style sheets, even the text
-only browser, you can see it
has all caps headings and space
between paragraphs .
So there's styles happening
here, but the styles are
provided by the browser, so
there's this same across all
websites, they depend what
browser you're using.
And this is fundamentally
different from print design.
Right? Where we get to describe
everything about our page.
In fact, we describe the page
itself. How big is it?
And then, it stays that size
forever. It's static. So we can
export to a PDF or a JPEG or
send it to the printer and what
we get back is exactly what we
designed.
And you can click on it all you
want, nothing's going to
happen. It just sits there.
The same was true for other
digital formats at the time .
Postscript had been around for
almost a decade . That's the
basis of PDFs, which came
slight , I think around the
same time. It's a page
description language. So like
print, we describe a static
page, how big is it? Where does
each thing go? And we set the
fonts and colors, et cetera.
We get all of the control in
those systems, but that control
comes at a cost. The page,
print or PDF is a static medium
. It can't adapt a context or
preferences.
And that's a limitation of the
medium. Go read John Elsop
's style of web design from
2000, it's still relevant . I
won't wait.
Web styles have to be
different. They have to be
contextual. Even static sites
aren't static.
What we ship is not always what
our audience sees
. So styles must adapt to all
of the different situations
where they might show up
because the web is responsive
to context. And that's a
political vision from the
beginning.
Not just the width of the
viewport, but user needs
and preferences, device
interfaces, and changing
capabilities over time. In
other words, we're not alone.
We're part of an ecosystem here
and our decisions impact other
people. We don't get final say.
We're collaborating with the
browsers who are
instructed to ignore us when we
go off the rails.
And we're also collaborating
with the people who interact
with our sites
on their chosen devices with
varying capabilities , with a
browser that they choose, and
wearing
these handy little tool belts
that I think are very cute. And
we're probably also
collaborating with aliens,
maybe, who knows, if they're
around, we should collaborate
with them. They're just trying
to get home.
The CHSS proposal is
explicitly designed around this
collaboration. That's how the
document starts
. This proposal tries to soften
the tension between the author
and the reader.
It's specifically for that.
And, if conflicts arise, the
user should have the last word.
And that is built into the
cascade itself.
It's the first step of the
cascade is that the user styles
can override the author styles
when it's important from step
one, origins important, when
the user
marks sometime important, they
take priority over everything.
That's the purpose of
importance.
It's not for us to get into
petty
squabbles, but to maintain
balance in the universe and
give power back to the...  I
don't know...
rebel users, I don't know.
Analogies are hard.
A Jedi uses importance for
knowledge for defense, never
for attack. This also becomes a
core W3C principle.
If a tradeoff needs to be made
in the design of the platform
itself, always put user needs
above all.
So under these sort of absurd
constraints,
design seemed almost impossible
on the web
. If we want this political
vision, how are we going to
control fonts and colors, for
example, we can't
.
But nobody was happy with that
outcome.
When every site looks the same,
that's not just boring for
people who are trying to brand
their product, it's kind of
boring for everybody. People
like design.
The turning point came in 1993
when
Mosaic added the image tag to
HTML. This was before web
standards, web styles were
suddenly possible
through the image tag.
You could just throw everything
into an image.
And then, when it breaks,
there's no content to protect.
This fundamentally breaks
everything that was special
about the political
vision of HTML. If it doesn't
load, it's just lost. This was
a real risk to the platform.
The web could've become a giant
fax machine where pictures
of text would be passed along.
So there's a real race
between 1993 and 1994, a rush
of different proposals trying
to figure out how are we going
to get styles on the web is
that that don't
break what makes the web
special?
I recommend checking out a
bunch of these. They're really
fascinating. But all of them
talk about this problem.
Allow the authors, that's us,
building the web.
To attach style hints. Styles,
not rules, but hints and
suggestions.
This phrase shows up over and
over in many of the proposals.
Provide hints that the browser
may or may not use. Again,
we're drawing from HTML's rules
there.
A set of hints or suggestions
to the renderer, which might be
used .
In Hokum's proposal, authors
and publishers have stylistic
influence without resorting to
page description languages.
That's called out specifically.
We're not giving us full
control. Only the ability to
provide some
influence.
And this uses the same
resilient logic as HTML
. And we can see that, again,
did I leave that tab open?
I did not. Let's go back to it.
In CSS, I've done the same
thing. Calling colors that
don't exist.
Oh, my I must have -- that
became content.
I'm using colors that don't
exist.
I'm useing entire declarations
that don't exist.
Selectors that don't exist.
Everything can just
be ignored and it's fine.
That's how CSS is designed. We
can be ignored.
And this is the reason that the
default overflow is visible.
If we get cocky and make a box
too small for our text,
browsers will try to bail us
out. Not because it's the
best-looking solution, but
because the web will
try to protect content whenever
it can, browsers are helping us
out here.
This is another design
principle of the W3C.
Content should be viewable and
accessible by default. And the
browser ensures that's the case
unless
we go in and mess it up.
Indesign doesn't have to worry
about
this. Accidental overflow can
be found and fixed before we
hit publish or after
we get a proof and fix it.
And then, once it's fixed, it
stays the way we designed it.
It's not going to change.
It's not going to move. But
we're doing graphic design of
unknown
content with unknown
collaborators on an infinite
and unknowable canvas across
operating systems, interfaces,
languages, writing modes.
It's absurd what we're trying
to do here. What this language
is trying to accomplish.
I don't know any other tool
that is trying to do this in
design.
There are too many variables to
consider. The point of CSS is
to make it so we don't
have to worry about all of
them.
We have We hand some of that
over to the browser, that's why
CSS is a declarative language.
We literally write our hints as
declarations of property and
value.
And some of those can seem like
simple concepts, the width of a
box, 500
pixels, some are more abstract.
Wrapping text so it looks
pretty, whatever that means.
Even the concepts that
seem simple, hide a deeper
complexity. Should the box be
smaller on a higher resolution?
What do we mean by a pixel?
And how does the unit respond
to zooming in or out?
And are we talking about the
width of the content where the
padding and border are
additional to that width?
Or the width of the whole box
with the borders and padding?
There's not one universal
answer.
It depends on what we're doing.
And maybe we really don't want
the width at all, we're
thinking about the in line
size. The size available to a
line of text.
Or maybe we should be sizing
the box based
on its contents, the min size
or max size.
Or the size of a character in
the font we're using, or
based on context, parent
element, viewport, container,
some combination of those, the
minimum of two values.
Everything in CSS is based on
this constant back and forth,
context pushing in, defining
the
space variable, and content
pushing out, taking up space,
and
we're trying to make those two
always work together.
How do we ensure that our
content will fit
any container that we put it
in? We can't. We don't have all
of that information.
We don't know but the browser
does have that information.
So if we want this power, we
have to give up some control .
The most useful parts
of CSS express this kind of
abstract behavior, letting the
browser work out the details.
If we can avoid touching it, we
should.
The browser knows more than we
do. So, we're using an
expressive language, not
describing the page in step by
step de
tail, but expressing high-level
concepts. Our job is poetic,
providing subtext
for the browser, no the just
the resulting style, but the
purpose of a style choice. And
units are great for this.
And it's why CSS has so many
units because they help convey
this meaning and intent.
So, 1em and 16 pixels may in
some cases by default look the
same.
But they have very different
meanings.
They adapt differently in
different context.
So our job is not to make it
look good on my device.
But to make sure it adapts to
different contexts as needed.
Adapting to unexpected changes
in the
context. Similar with layout
methods.
Flex and grid can give us the
same result in a static
setting. But they move
differently. They behave
differently.
It's useful to learn both
because they're going to
act differently in different
contexts.
Even when we can get the same
result, they have different
meanings, and that's worth
paying attention to.
We're trying to express more
meaning with fewer constraints.
Expressing our intent clearly
using hints and suggestions for
the browser.
So, to me, this meme, the CSS
is awesome box breaking meme.
It actually perfectly captures
what is awesome about
CSS and how much can go wrong
when we try to control things
that
we shouldn't necessarily
control. When we add too many
constraints at once.
So how can we loosen our grip
on this?
There are several things we can
do.
We could change
the -- we could remove the
width and height constraints .
And oh, we could keep that font
size.
Let's see. Yeah, we could --
the height's not going to do
much in this case,
but the width there, that's
going to help.
We could even say the min width
is min content and otherwise,
we leave the max height and
width.
We could change this to
overflow, wrap break word. We
could play with hyphens, or we
could, yeah, if we're going to
break word there, we want to
get rid of the max height. We
could decide if we want the
height to move or the width to
move.
We can change overflow to clip
or scroll.
Get all sorts of different ways
that we can mess with this box.
I mean, I think the most fun is
just, there we go . CSS is rad.
That fits perfectly in our box.
Yeah, so I love that meme for
the wrong reasons.
To avoid harm, we don't want to
describe a static
page but express a design
vision through hints and
suggestions, help the browser
understand the constraints that
are important for our de sign.
So that when things change,
browsers can adapt
to -- can adapt our design to
those changes.
We're designing systems, in
facts I would say cascade
ing style sheet is a designing
system, it's a set of guides
for maintaining cohesive design
across a variety of contexts.
It's the kind of design system
that a browser can read and do
something with.
To avoid harm, we use a light
touch. We define the outer
boundaries, the constraints of
our design, rather than every
little detail.
We provide hints that help the
browser understand our goals
that let the browser take care
of the details.
This is our job as designers,
design engineers, whatever we
want to call ourselves.
Everything else in CSS is built
around this political vision to
protect the content, protect
the
user, and our first
responsibility is not to break
that .
Thanks.
≫ MIKE: That was incredible.
You just blew my mind.
I think that, like, just that
mind set of writing CSS
hinting at the browser, rather
than telling it what to do. It
makes doing websites so much
more enjoyable .
≫ MIRIAM: It does. Yeah, I feel
the same way.
I think for me, it's kind of a
fun -- I work in theater, too,
I think there's a fun sort of
like -- it's different in every
venue, different on every
night.
That sort of, yeah, the
performance, there's
the script and the performance
of the script.
≫ MIKE: And your point about it
being poetry.
That's a fantastic analogy, as
web designers, we're writing
poetry, we're not
designing pixel perfect layouts
on screens. Very cool.
And I think the other thing I'm
taking away from that talk is
just what a miracle CSS is with
its ambition that it actually
works and --
≫ Yeah
≫ MIRIAM: Yeah, and look
through that original document.
The ambition was so much
higher, even.
They were imagining wild media
queries right from the
beginning. So media queries
didn't actually land in
browsers for another
five or six years, but they
were part of the original
design of it .
And there was also -- there was
this whole thing about the
collaboration was even more
intense. So, you could say
instead of
a binary importance, importance
was a percentage , so you could
want something 60 % importance,
and somebody else could want
something 40% importance
, and then, the browser would
give you a weighted average of
the two results.
So you would get a font size
between the two weighted based
on their importance.
That became a little absurd if
you, like, you
request yellow, I request blue,
and were we're going to get a
weighted average of those.
I don't know if that's what
anybody wants, but yeah, a lot
of real cool ideas in there.
≫ MIKE: It's like hitting that
balance of giving
web developers enough control
but not too much , it's --
≫ MIRIAM: Right.
≫ MIKE: Such a delicate balance
.
Yeah, I'm going to rewatch that
talk, it was amazing. Thank you
so much for joining us today,
Miriam.
≫ MIRIAM: Thank you.
≫ MIKE: All right. What was
everyone's favorite part of
that talk?
Yeah, I'm seeing a lot of
claps.
Yeah, reach out to Miriam, I
think it was a Twitter link? X,
I should say.
If you want to find out and
talk about it more.
So we've got our next speaker
lined up. Paul Everett who is
going to be talking about 11ty
and large project tooling.
Paul is a Python web developer
advocate at Jet Brands
, desperately trying to put the
web back into the web.
Paul has bootstrap Python
Software Foundation, prior to
that, Paul was an officer in
the US Navy
.
[ Applause ]
Welcome, Paul, great to have
you on.
≫ PAUL: Thanks a lot, Mike.
What a talk that was by Miriam.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, mind blowing.
≫ PAUL: It's one of those
perfect combinations of the
first principles that we all
need to get back to.
And, unfortunately, a beautiful
slide deck, as well.
Mine shall not be quite as
attractive.
≫ MIKE: Looking forward to
this, Paul, over to you.
≫ PAUL: Yeah, sure. And I'll go
ahead and proceed. I'm Paul
Everett, developer advocate as
Mike mentioned.
We're going to talk about using
11ty on larger
projects, but first, I wanted
to give a big thank you to all
of you to you,
especially to Zach for this
conference. It's like you
crawled inside my brain and
found the
exact speakers and the exact
topics that I would be
interested in seeing.
And not only that, Zach created
this community
around 11ty, which is
fantastic.
I'm just such a supporter and
advocate for everything he's
doing.
And like was mentioned before,
trying to put the web back in
the web. So let's begin.
We have a website called the
JetBrains guide.
It has content, we've been
working on it for a while
while with a big friend of
11ty. And when I started this,
in 2018
, I used Gatsby. No, seriously,
please, stay.
We all make decisions, just
like getting beat up on the
playground as a kid, you can
learn from your mistakes, but
we also can learn some of the
things that can take us
forward.
I learned a lot about modern
web, good and the bad.
Learned a lot about I come from
a CMS background, I learned a
lot about modern CMSs.
And there was a point when
Collin came to me and said, you
know, really everyone hates you
about this Gatsby thing and so,
you really got to make a change
here.
Let's go to 11ty. But we wanted
to keep the developer
experience we had from the
tooling . We wanted to keep
some of the author experience
that we had.
So we went away and added some
of the
things to 11ty and
realistically, that's the talk
for today, what did we do with
11ty to support things that
you might want to do with a
Gatsby
. Things you might want to do
with a CMS. Things you might
want to do with a larger
system.
What do I mean?
We rolled out a codebase that
used typescript and used a
templating language, TSX.
JSX, TSX. As an 11ty template
ing language, not as a browser
rendered templating language.
We also added in, I like to do
tests
-first development, we added in
V test, and friends, the
friends we'll cover in a
moment.
And some other stuff I hope
we'll have time to get to about
improving the author experience
with automatically generating
JSON schema, and then, one of
the things I kind
of was intrigued about from
Gatsby was its GraphQL query
model.
One little point, if you're
ever doing GraphQL
and you -- and Gatsby, and you
think you want to do custom
GraphQL schema extensions,
don't.
All right.
The real philosophy P behind
this is, doing your web
development in small little
chunks so you can stay in the
flow. And you're not like doing
a whole build with console
logs and poking around hoping
to stumbling across the problem
that you're having.
Instead, it feels like
development with joy.
As I go through this, you don't
have to follow
along too closely, I'm going to
go pretty fast through the how
and try to get more to the
demos that show a little bit
more of the why .
And the reason you don't have
to is because we put up
an 8-part tutorial with text
and code and
videos walking through each one
of the steps that I'm going to
go through a little bit today.
I'll take a look over here and
see if there's anything I need
to catch up on in comments, as
well.
With that in mind, let's do a
quick tour of how we got to
tooling.
For 11ty. First in the package
.
json as Zach mentioned in the
opening remarks, we started
with ESM modules.
This was something in 3. 0 that
we got when we did this in 2.
0, we had to stick with
CommonJS.
The hero of the show is a
package called TS X, and it is
a layer on top of ES build
that gives you a bunch of
sensible defaults so that you
don't have to think about it so
much, which is good because I
don't really understand a lot
of these decisions.
And it winds up feeling like a
Node replacement.
The command node, obviously,
it's running node under the
hood,
but you run TSX instead and you
inherit all of this stuff.
Then, we needed something to
render a VDOM, I guess, is the
best way to put it
into a string, and this is the
package we used. It had a
number of things that we really
needed.
Versus a package we were using
before.
What this means, we're not
using React anywhere.
There's no React, Preact,
this package renders or JSX
into a string.
And then for the component
driven development workflow, we
like to sit in tests . So V
test is a wonderful package and
it's super speedy. Friends came
along for the ride with V test.
A browser called Happy DOM and
testing library that has a
philosophy of testing your site
the way people use it.
In an accessibility oriented
way with rules and stuff like
that.
And then, finally, in the
package. json, these are the
two build scripts. You notice
the TSX in front and the
config file is written in
typescript.
I won't go into TS config
because I frankly don't
understand it that way.
But typescript has support for
JSX, so we turn it on with the
misnamed value React JSX.
It doesn't actually have any
React.
And then, second, pointing it
at our package, the JSX async
runtime which then teaches the
compiler where everything is so
we don't have to manually
import.
Here is our 11ty config file.
11ty has support out of the box
for JavaScript templates.
And what we want to do is say,
these file extensions are
actually JavaScript.
Even though it says jsx,
THOECHB it says ts.
Because that tsx package is
going to transparentally
convert all of that into
JavaScript.
Finally, in the config, this
was the big breakthrough
eleventy.
config gives us a plug point to
do transforms, and in one
central location instead of
doing it throughout the code,
we were able to transform a jsx
node into a
string asynchronously, and
then, just for fun, we
centralized the placement of
a dot.
One last step, we wanted to do
testing and so in vtest, it has
support for the fake browsers,
out of the box, it supports
happy dom, this was the line
that we put in to get our good
testing. I'll take a look over.
And see, no, not a lot
of dependencies. We removed
dependencies, in fact, as we
went along.
OK. Over to some demos.
I'll go ahead and switch over
to...  the sample repository,
and then, I'll go back to our
repository to show some of this
in action.
I'm going to show you an
end-to-end of the smallest
possible thing without a lot of
extra concepts.
Here is the home page or my
site, and you see that it's got
layout, front matter,
everything we understand, but
because I've switched over to
this tooling
friendly approach, I don't have
to think too much about files
anymore, and I can think about
symbols.
And so every page on the site
has a main layout, and I can
navigate to this main layout.
This is what the file looks
like.
If you've done any of the ESM
stuff, this line will look
familiar to you.
You need to export a named
export called render.
I rename everything so that I
can have similar bombsymbols so
everything isn't
named render. I've got a
function called main layout.
This might look a little
React-y to you. And what it's
doing is saying, hey, I'm going
to
be passed these two things, I
know what I'm going to get
passed,
and any caller can get
auto-complete for this .
You can get auto-complete
because we
do props and prompts in a
typescript type.
And now, tooling can help me. I
can mouse over this and see
what is the
contract that needs to be
obeyed? And what I can
destructure from it?
I can get auto-complete,
obviously.
I can get a squiggle if I make
a mistake . I could even
decide, no, really, I want this
to be
called "heading. " And
everywhere in my project that
uses that will
now use heading, including
the prompts because there's
great tooling support for
typescript.
There's great tooling support
for jsx, and if I don't like
that, I undo it. And everything
in the universe goes back to
what I had
before I did the refactoring.
Again, this is stuff that
people are familiar
with in the frontend
world, and we're getting the
good parts of that while
leaving the whole agenda of
client-side rendering.
I'm returning jsx instead of a
template, I
get all of the stuff like
auto-complete in here. And
then, this is a fun one,
I'm showing -- writing my site
in
a reusable component-driven
fashion . So I do little units
of increment.
And I can get auto-complete of
my headings.
And when I do the
auto-complete, generates
the report for me, and I get
all of the things that you
would expect from good tooling.
I can then navigate to the
heading, see how it's
implemented, and then, I can do
the way I
do development, which is in a
test.
And so, I'm working over here,
I've got my test over here .
And if I
changed this word to "Zach "
and run this test, it's going
to fail, and I might be
confused why it failed
. Well, I can go into the
debugger, stop on this line,
that's the first time
through, and I see, oh, yeah,
duh, I passed in --
I didn't pass in tsx, I passed
in Zach, that's why I ran into
the problem.
So that's a little bit of a run
through of the test-driven
development approach on this.
I'll look over here. And see.
Some comments.
Hey, Collin, thank you for
helping me out here.
I do like the minimum layout in
my IDE in here.
And with all of that in mind,
here's the way I actually work.
I run vtest in watch mode.
Because it's so fast.
And I run it in watch mode
under the debugger.
And so, I've got my entire 11ty
development that is running at
all times
whenever I make a change. And
so, if I fix
this, that's my turn around
time. I didn't go to a browser
and hit reload. I didn't run an
11ty build.
In fact, if I wanted to, and
I'm like, I'm confused here, I
don't have a bug, I just don't
know what's going on here. Set
a break point, press space, and
you will stop there.
And sometimes, 11ty hands me a
lot of
data, a lot of surface area in
page, a lot of surface area in
data, and I get confused, I'm a
man of a certain age.
I just want to see what's
available. And this is what I
do to stop at a certain point
in rendering and see what is
available to me at that point.
All right. I will continue.
Obviously, we want to see does
this
thing actually render a
template that can be used in a
browser?
So after I've done all of my
development, that's when I
actually
go over to a browser and look
at it . And, yes, actually,
it is a very nice size. It did
render, it could use a little
bit of help from Miriam on the
styling, obviously.
That's an end-to-end
tour of the minima with about 5
minutes
left, I'll take a look at what
we're doing in our knowledge
base . Feel free to ask any
questions, Collin is show
runner with me on that project,
and he can answer anything over
there.
I'm going to switch over to our
actual project . This is our
knowledge base.
It's pretty big.
So this is all the content, or
all the programming languages
that JetBrain supports.
These are all of the components
that we have that are isolate
d and easy to test and stuff
like that we can use wherever.
And so, this is, again, test
driven development
. What I'm going to do this
time is I'm going to run all of
the tests in the entire site
under the debugger.
Vtest will fire it up the first
time, it'll take a few seconds
to fire up the first time vtest
has gotten faster. I could
speed this up.
Once it's running, all of my
tests pass, I have 131 tests.
And I make a mistake. Here is a
usage of a test. I'm calling
the heading.
Passing in the two values. I
make a mistake.
And then, my test no longer
passes, I get a little squiggle
here.
I can mouse over it and get
more information for exactly
what the problem is.
But that's a pretty fast turn
around time under the debugger
for working with your site.
And we never went to the
browser, and we never did
console log.
The part that I wanted to
finish with is the other stuff
besides just developer
experience. We also added some
stuff from an authoring
experience.
So if you were interested in
leaving Gatsby, these are some
of the kinds of things you
might also be interested in.
For example, I'm sitting in a
markdown file.
This is actually the tutorial
that we wrote for this
conference . And I have front
matter up here.
Well, my front matter actually
has a schema.
And so, if I were to write
author, I get auto-complete.
But I don't get autocomplete
just of the keys, I
get auto-complete of the
values, that is actually
i... y...
markdown file. PWE was the
thing, it's in content
space, it's not in software
space.
How are we doing that?
We have a bunch of resources
that we define in typescript,
and let me go to tip model.
Tip models, yeah. We define our
schemas in typescript.
Here's the schema for a tip.
And then, we use type box to
convert that to a JSON schema
we can enforce.
And then, every single time you
hit save, we rerun some
code that writes a JSON schema.
We dump all of the schemas to
disk. And here's what the
schema looks like.
And so the IDE sees this, it
sees that
these are all of the possible
values, and we give an
authoring experience where an
author.
This was the thinking that
killed us in Gatsby. You would
put in a wrong value, and you
would fail.
And you would fail obscurely,
and you would have no hope
other than coming to me and
getting me to look at your
branch.
We really wanted with the
embrace of 11ty, we really
wanted to give a better
authoring experience on this.
Some other things we would like
to talk about at a later
date, things such as the
content model that has plugable
resource types and the queries.
Zach is adding in 3. 0, more
hook points that are exactly
the hook points
we need for validation, for
custom collections , and things
like that.
And then, we also were
confronted with something for
client side rendering where we
wanted to keep the templating
that we had and had to do a
work around for that.
With that in mind, this has
been a wonderful experience for
us.
Any of you that are interested
in moving from a larger system
with all of this tooling, such
as Gatsby,
over to 11ty, please reach out,
let's see what we can do
working all of this stuff
together.
.
≫ MIKE: Thank you so much,
Paul, it's always interesting
seeing, like,
how these big use are cases --
how 11ty
can and does a very good job of
it, of adapting to handle
something like that.
It was really interesting
seeing that workflow.
Which like a site, the scale of
your knowledge base,
it makes a lot of sense that
you need all of that tooling.
What was the buildout time?
And how long did it take you to
transition from Gatsby to the
11ty setup?
≫ PAUL: Collin and I did a
first shot in 11ty 2 and got it
out the door. And then in the
second shot, we did a lot of
just
redesign the user design and
user experience and stuff.
And along the way, as we really
got into what 11ty
could do for us, it changed the
idea of the knowledge base
completely.
You know, we'll let authors
create their own channels, and
they can write templates
because this is simple enough
that it can be put in the hands
of mere
mortals.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
So the workflow and GitHub
pulling in those --
≫ PAUL: Indeed.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
≫ PAUL: Just -- to reinforce
the point you're
making, people might have this
idea that 11ty is for personal
blogs. Let's change that.
Let's tell people that you can
do big projects,
Zach continues to add what's
needed for that. And let's see
how far we can go before 11ty
runs out of steam.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, it's actually
ideal for doing something like
that. Like, what other kind of
benefits have you
seen from move inging from
Gatsby to 11ty? I imagine your
build time came down?
Yeah, did it come down?
≫ PAUL: It came down from
infinity. What happened was,
you couldn't trust the Gatsby
cache,
so you had to do a full build
all the time and in our CI, it
would never complete before the
CI canceled the job.
≫ MIKE: OK. That's a lot less.
[ Laughter ]
So you'd have to build locally
and push it up?
≫ PAUL: Yeah, right.
≫ MIKE: Wow. Incredible. Yeah,
that's a big win.
CI being able to build your
site.
≫ PAUL: Indeed, and from an
authoring experience
perspective, I know we're going
to be thinking -- actually, the
talks at this conference are
very author-focused. And that's
great.
It's not just machinery.
When you can build sites that
give you the feedback that
instantaneously
and provide the hook points for
people like me that are
interested in content
management systems, you can
have an authoring experience
that is really fantastic.
There's nothing worse than an
author that feels dumb, right?
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
And ultimately, like, most
websites are managed by
nontechnical people.
It's so important to think
about the workflows and empower
editors .
≫ PAUL: They're not developers,
they're humans.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, again, for
joining today, Paul. Fantastic.
≫ PAUL: Thanks for having me.
≫ MIKE: All right.
We're coming up, in 5 minutes,
we're going to have a 15-minute
silent break.
I'll explain that in a second.
But before I do, I want to ask
the chat two questions.
One, when did you start -- why
did you start using 11ty? What
was the feature that -- the
straw that broke the camel's
back that you were
like, OK, I have to try this
now? What pain were you feeling
that 11ty really resolved?
And then, two, what is
a technology that you
think should be bigger or have
more adoption than it does now?
Yeah. And why do you -- yeah.
It'd be interesting, what's
your take on why is it not
bigger? So the 15-minute break,
we're going to split into three
parts.
It's going to be silent, so
there won't be any captions
during that time.
So the first 5 minutes, Zach
and
I are going to do a live
drawing with a prompt.
And it'll be side by side and
chat will judge who did it
better .
And then we'll do a five- minute
quiz, 11ty quiz and 5 minutes
of slides and get back into it .
OK. Let's see.
What chat...
faster and simpler than Jekyll.
Yeah.
Adam, yeah, that's what I came
from, as well.
Like, I got into static sites,
Jekyll was my first site
generator. And it has -- it's
still an amazing tool
. It does its job really well .
But it just has some, like,
legacy structure
and notorious, like, speed
issues
that can really hamper and
certainly was a breath of fresh
air for me.
-- coming into 11ty.
Should have more adoption
static sites. Yes. Exactly.
I couldn't agree more. Like,
it's just crazy to me how much
complexity is added to websites
to
have dynamic functionality that
is basically
generating a static page when
you can avoid a lot of pain.
And have it a lot simpler,
better user experience, better
developer experience, better
for everyone, just embracing
static.
I think we need a lot more
innovation in the static space.
Bring your own templating
language.
Got stuck in dependency hell
trying to get to the latest
version of Gatsby. Yeah. I
mean, that's another -- amazing
thing about 11ty is I saw Zach
do a demo of a site built
on pre-1. 011ty, and bring it
into
11ty 2 or alpha of 11ty 3. It
still works.
And still everything works as
expected.
So, like, not being required to
upgrade and doing it because
you want new features is just
incredible.
Needed something like Jekyll
that didn't destroy my soul
with Ruby dependencies.
I'm a Ruby guy, but just
getting Ruby set
up on a new machine is always ,
always a problem.
It's always -- it's never
simple. OK.
Zach, let's bring you on, and
let's get this drawing set up.
≫ ZACH: Break time.
≫ MIKE: Put on a little
background. Here we go.
And yeah.
Just share the screen. I came
to it from Hugo when I got fed
up with how Hugo manages
things. And stuck around
because it's just
so easy. Yeah, I really like
Hugo, but you really have to
fit your site into the way that
Hugo wants to build it.
Whereas 11ty just gives you so
much more flexibility.
≫ ZACH: All right, Mike, no
more speaking.
≫ MIKE: All right.
I should say our prompt, our
prompt is a possum.
≫ MIKE: That was so cool. Just
seeing, like, the impact of
this project. Yeah. Incredible.
All right. We're back in
action.
Back on schedule. So we're
going to do a short segment
on a project that I've been
working
on called the Future of
Jamstack . Jamstack was coined
in 2016.
And really created a lot of
awareness and brought the
community together. Around
static websites. And recent
years, it's got a
little muddied about what
Jamstack means.
And the community is like a
shadow of what it once was.
So, what the future of Jamstack
is
, is a project that's trying to
figure out, how do we get back
to the good stuff that Jamstack
was? So here's a highlight
video of that project.
≫ Welcome to the future of
Jamstack, the community-led
project that's figuring out
what's next for Jamstack. Over
20 interviews, three panels,
and over
100 clips of Jamstack goodness.
Here are some of the highlights
of what the community has been
discussing.
≫ It's become a radical idea
somehow to build close to the
middle of the web.
≫ You build as many things as
statically as possible up
front, and then you pull in
data and new things as needed.
≫ At its base, there needs to
be pregenerated HTML.
≫ I like saying a folder full
of files.
≫ Just because it's simple,
doesn't
mean it's technically worse.
≫ It's built on the
fundamentals of the web.
HTML CSS JavaScript, it's
pretty fundamental. And so,
regardless of what happens
going forward, in many ways,
it's kind of future proof.
≫ The people who have been
enthusiastic about Jamstack,
typically, I've found, people
who care about the fundamentals
of the web and the behaviors of
the web that certainly I hope.
≫ Can I take my site and easily
deploy it on a different
provider?
≫ When we didn't put strong
enough guardrails on what is or
isn't Jamstack, then it gets
really easy to start to add
more things in it, and then,
all of a sudden, it kind of
loses some of the potency.
≫ We start out with a term and
setup tools and it's very ,
very narrow.
And then, we start to kind of
grow as
we try to meet the needs of
various people in the
community, what they're trying
to build . And it's naturally
going to kind of expand.
≫ Single page applications,
multi-
page applications, SSG, SSR,
progressive hydration, island
architecture, progressive
enhancement, incremental static
generation, streaming SSR,
resumability, hedge rendering.
Someone entering the field and
hearing Jamstack and being
presented that Tweet is going
to think like what is this ?
≫ We pulled in a whole lot of
things saying, yes, that counts
. Yes, that counts.
For the shareholders, because
if it counts, then that means
it can be hosted on this thing.
And if we end up saying, these
are the guarantees you have,
these are the rules
then, yes, it gets rid of
things, but it's better for the
community and learners and not
necessarily the companies that
host it.
≫ Because SSR capabilities have
been built into frameworks
nowadays, people are doing that
more and more because they can,
not because they need to.
But because it's available to
them.
≫ A lot of the frameworks
started to kind of sneaking in
things that weren't static
without being
really good about saying that
it wasn't static.
≫ The community, therefore, got
broader and bigger
, to a point where there was no
real semblance of any
relationships anymore.
≫ It was 11ty and Gatsby were
the two, like,
strong sides to it, right?
Everything HTML or everything
client rendered.
≫ Because the Jamstack seems to
be somewhat of an identity
crisis, this is actually the
time to create a community
around it. Because in many
ways, projects, they survive
and thrive based on community.
≫ It's the cross tooling
community sharing that
happened.
≫ I
do agree with the static first,
it does not necessarily mean it
can't be done any other way.
≫ Static rendering
, that's a great approach for
me and out allows me so many
other things we've said.
≫ Static first is about what we
are, it's not about what we've
done.
≫ For me, the static first is
something that really appeals
to me.
Because I think that it kind of
directs
the discussion and thinking
towards this kind of mindset
that you can start by building
things statically . And that
you can add on to it when you
need.
≫ The thing I think is really
important
for us is the education around
the word static, because static
is a virtual, but it doesn't
describe the experience
. And that's the kind
of misunderstanding, I think,
that was at the heart of this
way back when when people were
like, I'm not having a static
site.
≫ Join the movement and have
your say at the future
ofJamstack.
org.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, it's a project
I'm really passionate about.
And it's just -- it's been so
cool. Just getting to talk to a
bunch of people about static
websites and, you know, the
space that we're
all passionate about. So, yeah,
excited to see
where we take that in the
coming months.
All right.
We're ready to move on to our
next speaker, which is
Henry Desroches, creative
technologist based out of
Denver, Colorado.
He's been designing and coding
the front of the frontend for
the web on nearly a decade
. Specializing in CSS
necromanicy, and the dark magic
of design systems.
He's worked for some incredible
clients, including YouTube and
"New York Times", can kickflip,
citation needed, loves
keeping the web strange, and
beaten ELDen
Elden Ring without leveling up .
I imagine it's extremely hard.
Henry's --
[ Laughter ]
Digital frontiers, a place
online to call your own.
Hit it.
[ Applause ]
We got there. Henry, welcome.
Great to see you.
≫ HENRY: Hey, how's it going?
≫ MIKE: Excited to hear your
talk.
Let's get your slides going.
Yeah.
≫ HENRY: Sweet.
≫ MIKE: Over to you.
≫ HENRY: Thank you. Just off
the rip, I've also beaten Dark
Souls
without leveling up. I wanted
to put that out there.
Hella multitudes. Hey, my
name's Henry, the font's name
is
Manuka, I'm a creative
technologist.
I also spent time in New York
City, based in Denver. Super
into hand crafted web code,
poetic
computation, CSS, and most
importantly for today, also,
shit posting. So thanks for
coming to the talk.
Digital frontiers,
Indie web cowboys, owning your
post with posse.
I'm super excited to get
started with this one.
We were given this vast realm
of self-discovery , philosophy
and joy and community. But most
of us spend most of our time in
the bad lands of brain rot and
attention farming and
doom scrolling and general bad
vibes.
We break our backs, the foundry
of algorithmic content as
endeavoring of our
sharing our interests corrupted
into the hollow twin of content
creation, to trap attention
spans, list
the thread emoji digital dams
to harvest scroll inertia.
However, it's not all bad.
There's plenty of folks who
oppose this mundane and
uninspirational for profit
corporate web, folks who
instead believe in the strange
and surprising web, hand built,
cell phone web.
The battle for the soul of the
net is fought upon three
particular
stages, well, OK, it's many
stages, but I'd love to focus
on three of them in particular.
Holy smokes, I'm killing it.
One, do you own your content?
If the companies that own the
platform
disappeared tomorrow or
devoured by the board
millionaire, would your content
have somewhere to live or also
vanish ? Two, can your content
go anywhere it wants?
If I want to find your posts,
do I need to go to a specific
platform? Or can I find and
reply to and share and
be delayed by those posts or
that content wherever
it prefers to dwell, wherever I
prefer to dwell, rather ?
Three, are you in control?
Can you post anything you want
or does someone decide, for
instance, that you have a
limited number of characters or
you can only post images as a
certain resolution
? What good is a banger shit
post, Mr. Anderson if you can't
pair it with a gif?
Those are familiar with what
the heck I'm talking about will
recognize these as some of the
core tenets of the IND
Indie web movement.
You own your demand and can
verify and identify yourself
across the web, owning your
content, and the specific
subject of today's talk,
publishing on your own site
first.
So POSSE, or publish on your
own site syndicate elsewhere,
is the idea that for example,
if I've got a banger
shit post and I often do, I can
create that post on my website,
write some software to reformat
and propagate it to other
common places of conversation,
such as
Mastodon or Blue Sky, no other
places.
And use additional tools and
standards to make the post and
the inevitable content
surrounding it because I said
it was a banger, serialized and
read by anyone in any arena,
always
linking back to the home URL
post, which by the way, will
never change .
I'll get a little more in-depth
on this, but right off the rip,
this solves everything.
I own it, syndicating to RSS
and social media that make my
posts are good or worthwhile,
which is everyone, engage with
them in the preferred format
and back feeding
the conversation that's
happening in all of those
places to my website collects
all of the great conversation
and engagement in one place.
And there's more wins to be
had.
Storing bangers canonically
allows you to be a better
steward of the web because you
can prevent link rot, thanks,
Twitter, and then, search
engines will learn to prefer
your site and search results if
they continue following links
back to your site .
So, I can see by your
individual faces, which
I can see that everyone's on
board with the strategy for
posting online.
In the rest of this talk, I'll
briefly cover a light technical
implementation of POSSE.
If you're feeling stoked on a
content syndication strategy
but not ready to take the leap,
you do have options.
Such as COPE. So briefly some
alternative strategies are
COPE, create once, publish
everywhere. It's the default
strategy.
The problem with posting the
same content everywhere, at
best, you're growing X number
of audiences on disparate
folks' sites, fractured digital
identity, there's
pesos, publish elsewhere and
syndicate on your own site.
There's actually room for PESOS
as an are archival sense.
Publishers, the Tweetback
project allows you to collect
historical posts from the
fractured identities and give
them a nice forever home
somewhere with a nice lawn,
careful,
he's a rescue. Also publish
elsewhere syndicate everything
to a silo.
Not because it's a good
strategy but because the
Indie web folks love a fuckin
algorithm, and you've got to
love them for it. I'm going to
sprint through building an
application that creates and
reads content.
P
We're going to make an app that
syndicates, capturing
engagement on
sites and rendering the
conversation back on our site .
Before I get into this, many
extremely bright people have
gone here before, many of them
aren't speaking today.
I admire all of these people
massively. This would not be
possible without their talks
and blog posts and their work.
There's a bibliography for this
talk, it's coming, I'll make it
available after I shut the hell
up.
Oh, yeah, and the other thing,
I meant to use this talk as an
excuse to rework the publishing
strategy on my actual personal
site, but as
I'm sure many of you can relate
to, I'm still redesigning it.
That's showbiz, baby, instead ,
we're going to create a
distinct and memorable
domain and that's showbiz,
baby,
or showbiz. baby. Don't worry
about the specific code. It's
an 11-minute talk.
I'm going to make everything
available after I get off
stage.
We'll start by creating an 11ty
project with two templates. One
that lists all of the bangers
and one that
creates individual permalinks
for the bangers. You might be
able to see in the market, if
you can see that, that I'm
using a format called Hcard as
part of microformats 2, which
is
a system of classes that we add
to the HTML to make our
information structured and
easily parsed by like crawlers
that come to look.
This is useful because we can
indicate who wrote the bangers
and what the useful parts of
each banger are.
Yeah, microformats  2, I got
off sync with the tabs.
All of this stuff is like super
well documented online.
It's a little bit wild west.
On the topic of
aweuthentication. We use the
domain as identity and use it
to
verify other instances of our
identity. Since my website and
GitHub account are both me, I
can verify those two identities
by linking to my GitHub account
from my
site and linking back to my
site from my GitHub account
useing realm A links .
This is the basis for Indie web
authentication
. Since I'm the only person
that can edit my website and
GitHub account, it's reasonable
to assume that both of those
sources are me.
Once we've verified and back
linked ourselves different
places online, we
can use a service called
Indie auth that can handle
authentication and web mentions
and add a few lines of code to
the head of our
site to tell the services that
they can go to Indie auth to
verify us.
Also, oh, there's like -- this
is off script.
There are some serious power
houses of the Indieweb in the
chat right now.
If I'm getting anything wrong,
feel free to rip me apart.
I specifically used GitHub in
the realm example because they
have a sign-in example that
Indie will coopt so you can
sign in securely as GitHub and
verify that I am my GitHub
account and by extension, also
my website.
But great, so now we've got a
website that verifies our
identity using
Indieauth and capable of
telling other services how to
authenticationuthenticate us.
Through publishing, it's 11ty,
we could create markdown files
by hand, but it's still really
nice, turns out, to go to a
website and click post. There's
nothing that clears the ass
of sending the Tweet. In this
case, I'm using Erin
Pereki's micropublish er
er Quill. This will feel like
magic the first time you do it.
We're going to grab a token and
proceed with our micropub end
point that Quill will speak to.
So I'm basically, we need to
accept publish requests from
Quill and convert them into
files that 11ty can build. I'm
going to create, I'm using
Netlify functions for this
because it's what I know .
Create a file function/micropub
and add the
corresponding endpoint to the
head on our in dex.
HTML, go to this end point to
make publish requests.
Also, I'll be using GitHub's
octokit tool to converting into
flat files in the GitHub repo.
We can grab a quick token from
there, as well. And we can
throw all of the tokens into a
.
end file and make them
available, but not public in
your environment. And then, we
can use them in the micropub
function.
Here's the function.
This borrows heavily from
Robert's tutorial publishing VI
writer. Here's the general
vibe. One, listen for post
requests and check their
veritoken matches the one from
Quill,
publish the content and
template them in a way that
11ty can work with. I made
markdown files with a timestamp
in the front matter.
And then, commit both the newly
created file to
GitHub and then, also, like a
-- some way to let -- like
basically a JSON file that
contains the most recently
posted post. I'll use it later.
But once that function's
deployed, we can sign into
Quill with our website, feels
amazing, make a post, and then,
watch
it magically appear on our site
pending a build set. Publishing
sorted.
Next, we've got to talk about
web mentions. This is the
conversation aspects.
From the Indieweb Wiki, it's a
super powerful protocol.
It lets us like, you know,
lightweight way and
standardized way tell our
friends and colleagues that
we're referencing their blogs,
et cetera, and lets us know
when folks are referencing or
talking about our work.
There's another service called
Webmention.
io, lets us read web mentions
from all over the web . We'll
sign up using the same
Indieauth steps as Quill, add
the mention endpoint to the
head. If it's feeling
repetitive, we're establishing
patterns, baby, and throw the
API key on our . end for later.
We can get web mentions from
other blogs, et cetera, just
like right off the rip.
But because this talk is
particularly concerned with
posting bangers, we need to
work out some way to collect
and share conversations, likes
B,
and replies, et cetera, from
social media . A free service
that does exactly that.
Con VRTs engagement into web
mentions.
Collecting engagement on the
other sites, et cetera, and
then, also to indicate and
create posts we can track
web mentions on that was the
like publish on our own site,
bridgy does that.
So, OK, once a post is created
and published on our own site,
we need to do the syndicate
elsewhere part.
I'm going to use another
Netlify function, it's what I
know. If you're an API genius
and want to do this a different
way, you can . The world is
your oyster.
Here's the function.
Again, TLDR, 11-minute talk, by
the way. We're going to grab
the last published note.
I stored it in the JSON file
like I said.
Ping Bridgy with a request to
publish to Mastodon and this
most recent post .
And that's literally it.
It'll just like Bridgy will
automatically post our posts ,
I've got -- somebody should've
proofread
this script, bro, holy smokes,
to Mastodon and
it's like four lines of code
like blue sky, other
syndication targets, whatever
you want.
So our flow is now completely
automated from I thought of a
genius post and I posted it via
Quill to having it published
on our personal site and copy
out to Mastodon, to whatever,
with a link back to our
original site.
So, on to the final step here.
Oh, crap, I've gone a little
bit over. I'm sorry.
Really cool now, the
conversations from all of these
different sources are collected
as web mentions.
So we can show all of those
conversations from the
bluebird, the butterfly, the
elephant, in one place.
So folks don't have to miss out
on a reply because
they prefer Blue Sky, they can
click back and read everything .
It's pretty easy to use 11ty
data files, run me the check,
Zach, to collect
web mentions as JSON from the
web mention API that I
mentioned earlier . And then
render them into templates,
Maxbook has a fantastic
tutorial on this . This borrows
from that heavily, obviously.
And I've included
implementation of that in the
GitHub repo, again, available
after the talk.
But that's it. Like, after
maybe two hours of work, you're
owning all of your content,
you're divested from the whims
of social media silos and sicko
owners and made the web more
kind.
There's a million enhancements
that can be made to this. You
can follow Cy Sia
's amazing guide, you could add
media endpoint in case you want
to post gifs, use microformats
to let folks find
a post from your site back on
to the silo, if you want.
All the code for today will be
examinable, like, under the
microscope, whatever, online,
on my personal website, Henry.
codes in the next couple of
days. Oh, I didn't mean to
leave that in there.
Oh, yeah, no, sorry, first big
talk, bear with me. And then,
yeah, thanks for listening
today. Thank you for 11ty for
having me and all of these
other amazing speakers.
I'm literally so honored to be
sharing the estage to these
people.
I've been looking up to y'all
since I was a wee child.
Last minute plug, if you 11ty
sickos love personal websites,
visit us at
personalsite. es and share
yours.
You can filter by RSS feed, you
can do whatever you want . Find
me somewhere JAUP line, Free
Palestine, thanks so much.
≫ MIKE: Thank you so much. That
was amazing.
Those principles of the
Indieweb are so important
as we've seen in the past
decade play out.
We really are the ones that
need to push these ideas and
, as you showed, like 11ty's a
great tool to kind
of be at the core of that
publishing platform.
≫ HENRY: Yeah, and it's a
stronger and stronger strategy.
≫ MIKE: We're going to move on
to our next speaker, thanks,
again, Henry.
≫ HENRY: Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: All right.
Next speaker is Sia
KARM , she's currently working
on web performance at Shopify.
She also is an international
conference speaker, writer,
Google developer expert in web
technologies, and member of the
W3C web performance working
group.
She coorganizes the 11ty
Meetup,
which won the 2021
jammy award for outstanding
community meet yum up. She's
going to talk about probably
doing web performance wrong.
I'm really interested for this
one. I think it's going to be
fascinating. Hit it.
[ Applause ]
≫ SIA: All right.
Hello, everyone, I think I'm on
here now.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, welcome, Sia.
≫ SIA: Thank you.
I'm excited to talk to y'all
today about why you're probably
doing web performance wrong.
I will admit it's a little bit
click baity, you're not
actually doing it wrong, but
maybe you're making your job
harder and getting frustrated
on the way.
Let me make sure my slides are
working.
All right. If I were to ask
y'all, what's the number one
tool you use for making your
site faster?
I would guess that 90% of you
are going to say lighthouse,
right? It's a great tool.
I credit it with giving
the web developer community
more -- or maybe making web
performance more visible to
everyone. Which was great, but
what you need to understand is
it's an algorithm and it's
limited and it might point you
in directions that aren't very
helpful sometimes.
And we're going to talk about
lighthouse, but also, the tools
that you're probably more used
to using.
What do I mean by that? This is
a real case I was looking at
the other day.
And this was its Lighthouse
report. On the website, they
had a score of 33, and you can
see,
there's more than 20 different
audits here that are flagged.
You're probably thinking oh, my
god if this was your site, and
the next thing, oh, do I have
to do all of these things to
make my site faster?
And what I want you to do is
take a step back and think,
what are the primary reasons
this website is so -- is it
really minimize main thread
work? Let's take a step back.
Again, my name is Sia,
Karamalegos, but I help make
merchant sites
FAESer onshop faster on
Shopify. I have a lot of 11ty
posts on there, although, I
haven't done enough lately
because I've been working more
on our Shopify, it's a
performance. Shopify. com site,
in case you're interested about
web performance at Shopify.
And yeah, all the things. Let's
keep going.
Let's talk about speed metrics.
In this presentation, I'm
talking mostly about speed
because that's what we usually
think about in performance, but
those other things are really
great, too.
But if this, I'm going to focus
on loading speed. Because the
idea is to give you information
about what you could do, which
is applicable to other ones, as
well.
So when we think about loading
speed, there's three important
metrics. The one that's user
important
to real users is contentful
paint
. That's when the largest item
on the screen or the viewport
is rendered, which gives the
user the idea, oh, this page
has loaded.
And the threshold for it is 2.
5 experience. And this one is
more, it's about
human perceptions of
performance, but also
achievability and things like
that.
But we also have a few other
load
ing metrics, time to first
byte, when the first byte comes
back from the server, user
doesn't know or care what that
is . They don't care. But it
helps us understand what might
be going on.
First contentful paint is the
clue something 's happening.
That's when the first item is
rendered. These are the
thresholds for good.
If you've ever used pay speed.
dev, and you have a site that's
popular enough to have publicly
available data in this data
set, you might see something
like this. You can see at the
top it says discover what your
real users are experiencing.
So this is real world data
or, we call it run data for
short.
It's telling me my largest
contentful paint is 4.
8 seconds. Largest of 4. 8
seconds or faster.
And so, you can see we have our
core web vitals on the top row,
and on the bottom row, the
extra metrics, plus one that's
about to be deprecated
or semideprecated.
But we can see this data.
This is how my real users were
experiencing that same website.
And this, again, is the Chrome
user experience support, if you
don't know much about that.
So at the top, I have our same
little kind of waterfall
diagram.
And at the bottom, we have our
example with the real user data
map to it.
You can see that time to first
byte, I've extended that row
out to 2. 4 seconds, that was
the number on the previous
slide. SEP is 3. 8. And LCP is
4. 8.
So what's the primary
bottleneck here?
There is no world in which you
can achieve a 2. 5-second LCP
with a 2. 4 second time to
first byte. It's just not
possible.
To do your entire first render
and your largest
contentful paint within . 1
seconds, it's not possible.
So if I were to, instead, so
the first two on this screen
are what you've already seen,
and on the bottom, what I've
done is
I've presented like I made my
time to first byte good and
then I've met FCP and LCP so
that you can see, you know,
what would they look like if
the time to first byte was
faster? Because these are
sequential. You can't render
the page until you get the
bytes from the server.
And you can't render the
largest thing until you've
rendered the page. And
sometimes, those can happen at
the same time. But, we can see
now that FCP is, it's still a
little bit slow, it's only .
4 seconds slower and LCP is
about . 7 seconds slower.
They still have a little bit of
issues. But that biggest
contributor was actually time
to first byte. So looking back
at our
lighthouse report, where would
we have found that out in here?
Well, what's really
interesting, which it took me a
while to figure this out
because I was looking for it, I
ran
it twice because I was trying
to explain, essentially, a
similar point to someone else,
and it didn't even pop up in
this lighthouse run. It
actually in
this specific experience, we
actually had a good time to
first byte. So it didn't even
trigger what is usually
happening in the real world.
Additionally, are remember,
that was probably our biggest
issue.
But because I know there's a
little bit of issue with FCP
and LCP, my guess is the other
two are these other two audits,
that's what I think they call
these things.
But the largest contentful
paint might have been
lazy loaded, that happens a lot
on Shopify sites. But this is
not a liquid Shopify site.
And then, render blocking
resources is a common reason
why first contentful paint is
slow. All right.
Let's take a step back and
learn about these two different
types of testing. So what you
see on here is what we've just
seen.
On the left is that top part of
PHP web.
dev which is your real user
data. And on the right, we have
our Lighthouse report that
you've probably seen a lot,
right?
It's this Lighthouse report,
you can see in the gray area,
you can see that it was run on
an emulate
Let's take a step back and
learn about these two different
types of testing. So what you
see on here is what we've just
seen. On the left is that top
part of PHP web.dev which is
your real user data. And on the
right, we have our Lighthouse
report that you've probably
seen a lot, right?
It's this Lighthouse report,
you can see in the gray area,
you can see that it was run on
an emulated motoG powered phone
using a slow 4G connection. And
it's just a single run. It's
only a single point of data.
Whereas on the left, it's
aggregated across the user
experiences.
On this page, you can see an
internal report we used at
Shopify that is real user data,
so we collect data with our own
script. And we can run it
across our site.
So I like showing this because
it shows, oh, now I'm going to
break it down by page and
device type. So I can see that,
you know, the collection page
has a big problem with CLS,
which is right down here.
But the desktop page has less
of an issue with CLS.
You can see the differences by
page and by device, oh, you
know what, it's directional
clues.
And on the right, is a network
diagram from dev tools, which
if you've ever run, that would
be considered lab testing, a
single run.
Left is aggregation, right is
the single run or lab test.
Again, on the left, this is
another way to see Chrome user
experience report data, it's a
cool site called Trio.
The site speed report uses crux
API.
And I like how you can see
monthly data in there.
It's aggregated data from
Chrome specifically. On the
right is your performance panel
dev tools, which is another
lab testing tool.
So there's two different types
of testing.
There's real user monitoring,
also called field of data.
And then there's lab testing,
which is sometimes called
synthetic testing. Neither one
of these is better than the
other. They just have their own
uses.
So you wouldn't use a hammer
when you need a screwdriver,
and the reverse. So what are
those differences?
Example tools, again, Chrome
user experience report is for
real user data. But you can
also collect this
data yourself, a package I use
for collecting myself is the
web vitals
NPM package, which is
maintained by the Chrome team.
There's also Boomerang, which
is a pulse product.
And there's also, if you wanted
like a paid service, there's
impulse but also speed curve,
which I really like.
Lab testing, the tools like
Lighthouse you're used to,
just the bottom section, the
one with Lighthouse in it, web
page test, you know, your
network diagram, your
performance tab in dev tools,
those are all lab testing.
So RUM is great for when you
want to see how real users are
experiencing a site.
And reveal those real world
bottlenecks that might be
hidden in a lab test. Like we
just saw. What was actually
hidden was there was a time to
first bite issue.
Lab testing, though, is great
for detailed data. And you can
more quickly debug and retest.
So their cons are kind of the
mirror of each other.
RUM, there's going to be
limited metrics. You only have
a handful of metrics and it's
hard to debug. You can't go
make a change and quickly see
if that probably fixed the
issue.
Instead, you actually have to
use lab testing for that.
But, of course, on, that side,
it can hide the real world data
and not representative of real
user experiences.
We're using servers to emulate
and experience or we're using
our own powerful desktops and
whatnot to measure.
So what are some of those
example observations? With RUM,
I can say, oh, LCP is slow on,
you know, the product page, or
CLS is bad on
the home page on desktop but
not mobile.
On lab testing, though, what I
can do is use those what I call
directional clues to
figure out if, oh, I can see
now that LCP is lazy loaded or
that 5 files are render
blocking, maybe I should
figure, you know, dig in deeper
on that or that sales banner is
shifting content down.
So when I debug, what I do is,
I use real user data and those
gaps between time to
first bite, first contentful
paint and largest contentful
paint to narrow down the most
likely issues.
Very similar content...
a very similar concept is LCP
subparts , and
Estella Frankel had a great
talk at a conference.
I usually have these specific
metrics at hand. So this is the
method I used.
But it's a very similar
concept. So what do I mean by
that
? When we have the three
metrics, if you have a problem
with one of them, it's usually
specific to that issue.
If I have a problem with time
to first byte, you might ask
yourself, why might my server
be responding slowly?
If instead, you have an issue
with first contentful paint,
you might want to ask what's
preventing the render? Do I
have a lot of render blocking
resources?
Am I using an antiflick r
snippet because I have AV
testing turned on or something
like that?
If your LCP is slow, you might
ask yourself, why is that
LCP element showing up faster?
Is it because the image was
lazy loaded?
Or if it's text, am I blocking
the font until the web font
comes in?
So there are different issues
depending on which part of your
speed is broken.
All right. So now that you know
that generally, let's take a
look the a
A at some examples. This is
actually an example of a great
hook performance. There's a
fast time to first byte, first
contentful paint and largest
contentful paint.
This is crux data from the trio
tool.
And this second example, we can
see that this is somewhat
similar to the one I've shown
you is that time to first
byte is 1. 7 seconds, that's
pretty slow.
And so, it's actually impacting
the other two, even though
there's only a gap of what .
6 seconds to first contentful
paint ? And . 4 seconds to
largest contentful paint.
While all of these are yellow,
it's time to first byte that
has the bottleneck here. I'd
look at server issues.
In this next example, this is
an easier one because
the first two were actually
green, we know it's just the
largest contentful paint . I'd
look at that element to look at
what's going on.
This next one, you can see that
FCP or LCP is only . 3 seconds
after FCP. So FCP or first
contentful paint is the primary
bottleneck.
Finally, a lot of cases aren't
going to be so cut and dry. So
this one, time to first byte is
good, but FCP and LCP could be
worked on. All right. So those
are some examples.
Because this is probably the
stuff you've seen less of and
in the past, you maybe seen
more of like just the
lighthouse stuff.
So I use that information, and
then, finally bring up my lab
tool to dig in deeper.
So once I have those
directional clues, I will dig
in deeper. So for Shopify
sites, Shopify uses liquid, but
of course, there's a lot more.
We have a server side, it's not
static generated.
We do use liquid, and I've had
an article about how to
optimize Shopify sites.
A the lot of these issues are
going to be similar to the
general web if you're not using
a frontend framework.
Although, the issues for time
to first byte being slow on a
static
site might be more, for
example, around your provider.
So like, if you're using GitHub
pages, I don't think that's on
a CDN, but if you use Netlify
, there's a CDN for that and
also cloud front pages.
Depending on your service, that
could impact your time to first
byte.
But the FCP and LCP, especially
for eCommerce
sites might be common reasons
why a site might be slow
compared to the Shopify sites.
So, of course, this is a whole
other talk and we only have 22
minutes. I'm not going to go
into the different lab tools.
But what I'm trying to tell you
is, DOENTS start
don't start with just
Lighthouse or your lab tool,
you might go down
the rabbit hole with minimizing
your main thread work, which is
still important and a
valid issue, and especially
considering, because I think
this site has INP issues, as
well.
But instead, I want you to
start with the real user data.
Get your directional clues.
And then, dive deeper with lab,
only on the specific issues
, essentially, try to get your
heavy hitters first.
Don't worry what those
microoptimizations first.
And then, in the end,
hopefully, you'll have more
time to focus on that hobby
that you've been neglecting.
So thanks, again, you can find
out more about me on Sia. codes.
All right.
That's all I have, Mike. I have
no idea how we're doing on
time.
[ Laughter ]
≫ MIKE: We've got a few
minutes.
≫ SIA: All right. Go ahead.
≫ MIKE: That was great.
I think just that context on
like, I'm definitely guilty of
doing Lighthouse and then, I
love a good to do list. OK.
This is my work. I'm going to
--
≫ SIA: And it's not bad, it's
just like a computer looking
for common flags . But it can't
necessarily tell you, like, the
primary reason why your site
might be slow. So --
≫ MIKE: That's it.
So my question is you kind of
mentioned this in your talk
that it'll change per use case,
but what are the most -- where
do you typically see the most
problems? And what are -- is
there like a common thread
in those performance problems?
≫ SIA: Oh, well, yeah, I think
it really depends on what
you're looking at, so like I
said because I work
at Shopify and most of our
sites are on our Shopify
liquid, essentially, your
standard, standard system.
We also have Hydrogen, which is
a headless tool
. But there's common thread. We
actually used crux DATD data
with http archive. It might be
hard with your personal sites
to get in there.
But you can also use free tools
like the
web vitals NPM package to
collect your own information.
But what we saw using that
information was that on Shopify
sites, this is not like the
rest of the web. Like, 80%.
We hit a peak of 80% of Shopify
liquid sites were lazy loading
their contentful paint image .
The rest of the web was around
20%. We knew that was a
Shopify-specific systemic issue
and it was because in our
liquid API, we didn't have
the ability for the way
Shopify's rendered, we can have
sections repeat, so
essentially,
if you had a template in
11ty...
what do we call it?
A it's not template for the
whole page, but something
you're reusing, but you don't
know where it is.
So you know you don't want to
lazy load above the fold, but
you the do -- I'm probably
going way too in-depth here.
≫ MIKE: No.
≫ SIA: I added into the API the
ability to know where your
section on the page so you can
be smarter about how you load
that thing.
≫ MIKE: Interesting. That's so
cool.
Like that work is going to
influence millions of sites.
And really shift the
performance of the web because
of that.
That's -- such important and
powerful work.
≫ SIA: It's definitely exciting
when you can find something
like that and fix it and get
everyone back on track.
≫ MIKE: Very cool.
If anyone has anymore questions
or
wants to talk about what
performance for Sia, reach out
to her on Mastodon.
≫ SIA: Yeah, if you go to sia.
codes, I'm on Blue Sky, but
that's mostly for shit posts
like Henry was talking about.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, Sia.
≫ SIA: Thank you.
≫ MIKE: We're going to roll
straight into our next speaker.
Next up, I've got Dan
Sinker, a designer from
Chicago.
He's made a lot of things over
the years, the underground
culture magazine, Punk Planet,
Foul Mouth Twitter Account,
Mia Emmanuel, the long running
podcast, and the journal
ist tech Open News.
But nothing is quite like
Question mark, the internet
spanning multiple platform
novel he launched a year ago
with novelist Joe M eno.
Today, Dan's going to be
talking about building a town
that doesn't exist.
[ Applause ]
≫ DAN: Hey.
≫ MIKE: Great to have you here.
≫ DAN: Thank you so much.
I feel like I'm a dog in a pair
of pants at this conference
, but I'm very happy to be
here.
≫ MIKE: I like pants on dogs.
And I like, I like hearing from
lots of different points of
view about 11ty. So really
excited for this one.
≫ DAN: Awesome. I'm super
excited to be here. Let's do
it.
Let's go.
The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, is
located in the Southeast corner
of the state 12 miles north of
the Ohio River, nestled
to woods, next to a
breathtaking waterfall, a
monument of battalion of
British soldiers and the
remains of a French settlement
that disappeared a hundred
years before that.
The quaint downtown of question
mark features a beautiful town
hall
rebuilt three times after fires
destroyed the previous two, a
magnificent library, and a
clock tower that stopped
working in the 1960s .
These were all built from the
fortunes of the Wylie Family,
town founders and creators of
the Wiley Safety
Envelope now in the cemetery at
the northwest corner of town
. The drive-in theater, bowling
alley, convenience store, two
cults, four murders, and seven
mysterious voids that sit at
the spiralling center of a
series of mysteries that have
beset the town over the last
year.
The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, doesn't exist.
It's a creation of myself and
the novelist Joe Meno, launched
in April of last year and
has unfolded on a near daily
basis in the year since.
It wraps, actually, in the next
couple of weeks . The story of
Question Mark has been told
across the internet.
On Instagram, Twitter threads,
The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, doesn't exist. It's a
creation of myself and the
novelist Joe Meno, launched in
April of last year and has
unfolded on a near daily basis
in the year since.
It wraps, actually, in the next
couple of weeks. The story of
Question Mark has been told
across the internet. On
Instagram, Twitter threads,
over email, on the phone, and
most immersively, on the web,
where it's unfolded across a
sprawling collection of
websites, over 40 in all , that
have played out like chapters
in a novel, advancing the main
story while also telling their
own at the same time.
There's no template for what
we're doing. I mean that in
terms of the fact that nobody
has told the story like this
for this long in realtime
across so many different
spaces. But I also mean it
literally.
Each site is built from
scratch.
There's no cookie cutter
approach to any of it because
each site is unique, each plays
a singular role in the story
and each site also has to stand
alone as something real and
believable.
Something that's marked with
the
age and ewe till I
utility of a work a day
website. John colton who wrote
a song for the story said we
were
building things as much
artifact as they were art.
That's exactly right.
Everything we made in Question
Mark needed to feel lived in
and real.
In that way, each site is a
puzzle, a puzzle for the
audience to solve, but also, a
puzzle for Joe and I as the
creators. How to make it work,
how to tell the right story,
how to make
it happen across multiple
screen sizes, and how to do it
in a turnaround time measured
in days or sometimes even
hours.
The key was to keep things
simple.
Each site was static, either
straight HTML, manually
deployed on Netlify, or when a
site required a
more complicated structure like
the newspaper with over 150
stories that span 90 years of
the town's history, that's
where 11ty came in.
Beyond that, all of our styles,
we're using tail
wind CSS, most interactions
were built with Alpine jsx, I
needed everything in a single
index
file because keeping track of
anything else was near
impossible.
While keeping it simple was
crucial to the endeavor, the
reality is a lot of what we did
with Question Mark, we couldn't
have pulled off a year ago.
We ended up leaning on
generative AI tools for imagery
more than we thought. And some
of the writing and coding.
In pushing them to see what was
possible with the tools
, I actually learned pretty
clearly they're just like any
other. And skilled hands, you
can do pretty incredible
things.
Of course, they are not perfect
in many, many ways, but for two
people with no budget to
imagine a world in near
realtime, it was liberating.
We used all of this, old
school, HTML, new school large
language models in service of
story.
The story of Violet
Bookman, a 17-year-old trying
to find her neighbor's cat Mr.
Business.
As readers, that's where we
meet her and we follow her
adventures through town. We
help her to solve mysteries and
find allies, even as the story
grows bigger and darker than a
missing cat.
But the real story of Question
Mark is one of grief, of
wishing you could return to a
past that felt better, felt
more whole, but realize
ing that to grieve is really to
move forward in spite of
everything.
That pattern, this is what the
story's about, and this is what
it's really about
. How we approached every site
that we built.
There was the garbage dump, one
of the more complicated and
janky builds that let readers
dig through hundreds of items
of trash to uncover a long
buried container of
toxic sludge. But really, the
dump was the story the town's
long time
mayor finally coming to terms
with the scale of her dead
husband's corruption.
There was the experimental crop
stations
online course catalog, where
you could actually take an
entire course on experimental
biology if you wanted to, but
the real goal was to take and
fail the employee security exam
in order to free
the sentient bean made of light
known as queuey.
There was the Question Mark
motel, which isn't coming up in
my slides. There it is.
The Question Mark Motel, which
actually advanced four
different stories on a single
page. Giving readers back story
on a number of different
characters simply by clicking
on the room. But really, it was
the story of one room.
Room O, and the cult that had
taken up residence there. And
their plan to commit a murder
on the eclipse. And then, there
was Bookman's music.
The music store run by Violet
Bookman's father . We knew we
wanted to bring readers into
the store
the same way we brought readers
into the ice cream shop, the
chicken joint and the pet shop
and many other locations in
town.
We also wanted to reveal a fun
detail about
Todd Bookman, he was in a one
hit wonder band
called Matrix who charted with
their song called ticking away.
Jonathan Colton wrote and
recorded that song for us.
What was the site really about?
It was about a way to explore
the distance between
Violet and her father that
emerged in the shadow
of the death of her mother four
years ago.
We hid that story throughout
the site and encouraged people
to interact and explore. Fill
out the form for music lessons,
and you
get an entry from Violet's
journals. Start inquiring about
instruments, and you'd get
another
entry delivered line by line.
You learn how distant she and
her dad have become.
She writes, maybe I'm just
afraid to have a relationship
with him because that would
mean admitting my mom isn't
ever coming back. On the about
page, we
reversed that point of view and
hear from Violet's father.
Click on the images of his late
wife and Violet as a child, and
you learn how he's been dealing
with the death.
I know I've been distant, he
writes, but I know both of
us needed to find answers in
our own way. I know I've been
afraid to talk about the pain
both of us are dealing with and
I know in just a few months,
she's going to be leaving for
college.
The Bookmans' music site came
together in two days. We
started with the story and all
grew from there.
It launched and we were already
on to the next chapter.
There are dozens of examples
like this. Because nothing in
Question Mark is what it
appears.
Almost everything has a deeper
connection to the story or to
the characters or to the theme
of loss and grief.
I have made a lot of websites
in the last year, and I will be
honest with you, I code with a
cat caught in a paper
bag. I am not here to tell you
about web standards or creating
elegant, efficient code, lift
the hood on any of these sites
that I've made, and they are a
horror show, but that is OK.
Because every site worked for
what it needed to be. A small
part in a larger whole.
Sure, they were janky as hell,
but they were sites that
thousands of people wanted to
go to and engage
in. They definitely did not a
adhere to best
practices, but instead, they
offered a doorway into a world
that people wanted to live
inside.
I love this post from one of
the folks on
the Discord server dead dicated
to unraveling the mysteries.
I struggle to make my brain
understand that I can't get on
a plane, go over there and sort
it all out myself, it's so real
to me.
This should be the aim of
anything that you build .
Create something that feels so
real
that someone has to struggle to
remember that it isn't.
That is making a website or 40
of them real good.
It doesn't matter if you've got
the latest skills or if you
know the cutting edge approach
to building or the right
framework or whatever. I had
none hof that when I started,
and I still do not a year
later.
Instead, have something to say.
Figure out the best possible
way to say it. The rest will
follow.
Every day Joe and I got to sit
down and ask ourselves
what's the story we want to
tell? And how can we build
something amazing to tell it?
And then we'd ask, what's the
real story we're telling? And
how does this artifact we've
created service that?
There's that pattern, again,
right? What's the story? What's
the real story?
And that's true with this talk,
too
. Because, yes, this talk is
about the work and love and
care that went into building
ing Question Mark for the last
year. But what it's really
about is this.
The web is still magical.
It's still a place where you
can build everything you want,
even a whole town.
There's no permission to get,
no hoops to jump through, no
risk of a platform shutting you
down, you don't
need fancy tools or a big team,
you just need your imagination,
a text file, a doc type HTML
tag and the whole world is
there for you to make.
It doesn't matter if it's
imperfect,
doesn't matter if the edges are
rough. Rough edges are just our
humanity showing through.
When people wax nostalgic for
the web, for the hamster dance
or MySpace profiles, what
they're nostalgic for is the
web
before it got all sanded down.
They're nostalgic for a web
that could give you splinters,
for a web with rough edges. For
a web that was more human.
But the story of Question Mark,
the real story is that you
can't move backwards .
That the past is the past, and
attempting to return to it
never works. And that's OK.
Because we don't have to.
The tools to make a web that's
more human,
more magical, more amazing are
not the tools of the past but
the tools of right now.
There's never been a better
time to make something,
anything, on the web.
You can build a world, tell a
story, make things happen big
and small, the web is still
vital, it's still exciting, and
the rules are there for the
breaking.
Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: So cool.
I've never seen anything like
that. That was incredible.
≫ DAN: Neither have I, and I
made it.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
So -- how did this start? Why
did you decide this platform
?
≫ DAN: So, I have worked with
Joe
for many years on and off. He
worked with me on the magazine
Punk Planet, I put out a couple
of books of his. But we have
not collaborated in probably 15
years.
And we went on a walk on a warm
November, and he was like,
I have this idea for a novel,
but I don't want to make it as
a book.
Kind of want it to exist on the
internet. And I was like, just
stop, let's do it.
And then, we figured it out
from there. You know.
We did not know what we were
getting into when we got into
it . But it's been a ride.
≫ MIKE: Is it a sequential
story? How do I navigate
between the parts of the story?
≫ DAN: So there are sort of
three main channels that the
story's told in.
One is Violet Bookman's
Instagram
account @violet bookman, I
don't remember it right now.
And then, there's the town
website, which is questionmark.
town, and the town
announcements that are
published from there, there
have been about 170, 180 town
announcements at this point.
Those are almost always the way
you branch into different
websites.
There's also the kind of sad
dad cop in town Ron
Deblosky who you can follow on
threads now, he was on Twitter,
but why would he still be
there?
And then, there's a mailing
list you can subscribe to, but
the
best way to get into it,
actually, is questionmark Ohio.
com, where we are breaking it
down week by week as
episodes, there are 42 episodes
you can read summaries for with
all of the links there.
≫ MIKE: Very cool. Thanks for
joining, Dan, it's a
fascinating project .
≫ DAN: Thanks for having me.
See you on the web.
≫ MIKE: See ya.
All right, we're about to enter
our next silent break. Zach's
going to come on, we're going
to
draw -- what are we going to
draw? I'm going to draw a CSS
logo.
All right. So we'll be back
running in 15 minutes.
≫ MIKE: Got to unmute. We're
back in action. So we've got
our next speaker coming in 5
minutes.
So before then, I want to ask
the chat a question. And this
is -- this is a household
question. In the household
category.
So when I unload the dishwasher
each day and
I'm always amazed at how many
cups we use in a day.
We need a measurement of like
cups per person. CPP.
I think our CPP might be 4 or
5.
Which, yeah, that feels like a
lot.
I'm wondering what everyone's
CPP is.
While we're waiting for
answers, let's go over some of
the other comments.
So, thanks for everyone to
getting into the quiz. I put
that together last night.
It's really cool seeing people
getting into it .
Yeah, it's just been -- it's
been really cool just
watching all of these, these
fantastic talks.
Like Dan's, most of them have
blown my mind in some way or
another . Dan's talk just
fascinating, seeing how we can,
you know, we
often think of 11ty as a tool
for building some sort of
either corporate or personal
website, but being
-- telling a story through
websites is fascinating. OK.
We've got some cup CPP.
2, 20 to 5,
1, two, 2. 5, 1, 4.
5 with kids driving up the
average. Yeah. Like, I feel
you. Three espresso, one big
coffee, two glasses
, at least.
Man, we're at 15CPP, yeah. We
have a lot of CPPs.
One, I would love to be in the
one CPP category, I just can't
do it. I lose my cup somewhere.
I have a reuseable water bottle
I carry everywhere, but forgot
it today. Yeah, that's the
smart way.
One cup over multiple days.
Keep improving the flavor of
the coffee. That would be
interesting.
Three to four CPP, the real
measure of our home is BPP,
bowls per person.
We eat bowls of cereal around
here. Yeah, what's your BPP?
Zero for me, I use the same
coffee mug and water and
tea mug for at least a week at
a time.
Yeah, that's impressive. So,
yeah, I have
a friend who, I kind of like
this philosophy,
where they just had everyone in
the house just had one cup and
one plate and
one set of cutlery.
And you were responsible for
washing your own stuff.
And then you never have a dish
load of, sink full of dishes or
anything.
Just sorted. But I don't know
if I could do that.
Two per person, three.
Yeah BPP and PPP, plates per
person.
I think I'm good on plates.
It's the cups that get away on
me. OK.
Let's get into our next
speaker.
So it's Adrianna Tan.
So Adrianna's the director of
product management San
Francisco Digital Services.
In her free time, she likes to
build websites for friends and
family.
And causes close to her heart.
She's talking about 11ty sites
for people who don't think
they're web developers.
[ Applause ]
Let me get rid of -- welcome
, Adrianna.
≫ ADRIANNA: I'm excited to be
here.
≫ MIKE: I'm really looking
forward to this one.
≫ ADRIANNA: Great.
So as I was just introduced,
I'm the director of product
management, I've never been a
professional web developer but
always worked with developers.
I've always loved hacking web
stuff, and I think that --
for people like me, who have
always been sort of adjacent to
technology but not like always
like knee deep in it, this is
sort of like who it's for.
Some interesting stats.
Before I started learning 11ty
, I had maybe built one site
over five years . It was a
Gatsby site, and it made me
cry, and I just sort of like --
never went back to it. Never
wanted to do anything. Didn't
want to update it, I was
fearful  I would break stuff.
And for various reasons, I
started following Zach on
Twitter and
I was like, well, this seems
cool, I should give it a shot.
And I've actually built maybe 5
sites over 5 months. So that's
been really, really fun. And I
started thinking, why is that ?
Why is it I got so far with one
tool but not others?
I've tried tons of different
frameworks, site
generators, and I think for me,
it's that it was just -- it
feels so much
harder, not easier to build a
site in
2024 compared to 2000 when, I
guess, I built my very first
website, you know, hacking
around, changing HTML
and the CSS and stuff and being
like, this is really fun.
But then, at some point, it
stopped feeling
fun or it started to feel like
it was harder to find fun
things. And getting to build
sites with 11ty
brought back some of that joy.
So then I started thinking, why
is that? And how can we help
other people feel that way?
The same sense of, OK, this is
something cool I want to learn,
again.
And my theory is that there's
probably too much to learn,
people are not sure where to
pick up if you're not in
industry, there's so many
tools, so many frameworks, you
need to know a bit of JS to get
going to get anything done at
all.
There's also a lot of conflicts
advice on what you should do
and a lot of
this advice is about how to get
into the industry and how to be
a web developer ? How to make
money? And many of us got into
it because it was fun. So can
it be fun, again?
So I actually really think so.
I think that we can sort of
tweak maybe through
documentation and through the
way we like approach
tutorials to make 11ty
approachable to people who are
not web developers who don't
think they are . And, you know,
sometimes,
I don't like the word like
nontechnical because it feels
like it excludes people who
don't feel they're technical
enough and certainly, for me, I
think one of the reasons why I
didn't really
like go knee deep into web dev
because growing up, I was told,
you're a girl, you can't do
math, you don't know how to do
stuff, you shouldn't be a web
developer.
I do think having more
inclusive approach to things
will
help other people want to learn
this and this seems doable.
And when I announced I'm moving
off my
microblog, I was using a
microblog thing, which is good,
by the
way, I recommend that to people
who don't know how to build
sites from scratch.
For my photography website, and
someone emailed me and said, I
want to microblog because you
used it, it was really cool,
now 11ty, I also want to try
that. But I really don't know
where to start.
So how do we get people to
start here with 11ty?
So I think that this was the
right tool because a lot of
things are like you said, like
Zach said earlier, HTML first.
Many things work like expected.
It's not filtered through some
opinionated thing.
You can learn as much or as
little as you want. So could we
find a way to help people like
go, here's a bunch of starters,
here's where you deploy it and
if you want to know more,
figure it out later. And we
already have friendly
communities.
So how do we, then, sort of
take that and go maybe a
different set
of people who see themselves as
not web developers need
different sort of, like,
knowledge base or different
sort of documentation or
simplified versions of it.
Or they need to ask questions
at sort of happy hour thing
maybe on Discord,
maybe these are things we can
do. And I started thinking that
what would have helped me?
Even just how I got started in
January when I was learning
11ty, I found
that I was referencing
Stephanie
, I was referencing Bob, like
11ty from scratch.
So there's a lot of stuff that,
you know, I kind of have to put
together and figure out what
worked for me. But maybe we can
sort of help
curate them for someone that
feels like an absolute
beginner. Maybe we could have a
far more opinionated walk
through. Here's a bunch of
starters, click here, host
here, you know,
sometimes there's decision
paralysis if we could sort of
help to recuse that, maybe
people could get further with
the idea that they can, if they
can get early success, then
they might be inclined to want
to try to learn even more.
I also think it would be cool
to write more blog posts about
things that I learned when I
was
learning web dev as well as
11ty.
Really, just beginners, there's
a lot of content out there
obviously is very centered at
web developers.
But what if we could talk about
why we picked this thing, why
we used this tool, what you can
do, and really
simplify accessible ways. I
think that would be very
explanatory and
reach a far bigger audience.
Maybe there could be pairing or
like buddy system and we could
have a special channel just for
like newbies to get help
. Those were just ideas that
came to mind, and I'm
presenting this so we can
discuss what possible paths we
could pick up in the future, I
certainly volunteer myself for
a part of it.
And, you know, really, I'm
interested in doing this
because I think it's important
to spark joy, again, with the
web, that right now, if
the default option for someone
who doesn't perceive themselves
to be a developer is to put up
a squarespace site.
They don't have very much
control.
I think it's hard to go from
that squarespace pipeline to
I'm actually going to learn to
become a web developer
or build stuff for fun
pipeline.
And so, how can we sort of help
give people
the tools or at least
handlebars to get started,
again? On this sort of journey?
So I personally want to see a
world in which I
can build things that are fun,
maybe even pointless. I don't
want to just be productive, I
don't want to just build work
things. I also want to build
websites, too, for example,
I'm someone that documents a
lot of Asian Potato chips I
eat. And someone would love an
Asian potato chip website.
If I genuinely believe that
11ty empowers me
to do fun stuff like this, I
think it'll be the same for
other people.
So I'm putting myself out there
as someone who wants to sort of
help bridge this divide and to
maybe work on new stuff with
the team, either in like
writing more blogs or blog
posts to help other people get
started.
So that's all I have.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, thanks,
Adrianna, that was great. And I
think you highlighted that step
really well where going from
Squarespace where everything's
taking care of you to
understanding some of the
fundamentals and being able to
build your own site and through
that, having more control, it's
such an important
one that we need to figure out
how we can help people make
that jump.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah, exactly.
≫ MIKE: The web's for everyone,
it's an open platform. And if
you're confined to the CMS
platforms, you don't get to
experience that.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah and it's part
of taking back control aspect
of, you know,
building an open web that so
many of us are really big fans
of .
≫ MIKE: Yeah, and it's so cool
hearing about your journey, as
well,
like five sites in five months?
≫ ADRIANNA: Five months.
≫ MIKE: Really cool. I hope you
keep doing that and posting
them.
≫ ADRIANNA: Yeah, I definitely
will, thank you.
≫ MIKE: Thanks for joining us
today, Adrianna
. All right.
So we've got our next talk
coming up. In five minutes.
So, yeah, that was --
I feel like Adrianna really hit
it on the head there.
Like it's a big -- ask that
question to the chat . I think
she had good ideas
. But how do we make
technologies in
and the web as a platform more
accessible? Outside of like web
developers?
I think,
I think learning computer
science and web development at
high school should be
mandatory.
It's such an important part of
the world now that, like,
understanding these
technologies, at least to the
high level how they work is
really important. And it would
just give a lot more knowledge
and control to everyone .
As a nondeveloper, use GitHub
is
not an answer that speaks to
nondevelopers. Yeah, it's like
they can be a big -- it can be
a
big jump, for sure. A lot of
the, I think,
that's the other thing about
Git is
, like, where else do you have
a workflow
that -- that Git can do?
Google Docs, you can have some
of those elements
of a Git workflow, you have
some sort of versioning, yeah,
and like a history of changes.
You can collaborate with other
people.
Those are great.
And like a lot of those ideas
come from
collaboration sort of workflows
from a version control system.
But when you get into branching
and merge
ing and pull requests where you
don't necessarily have
permission on that document,
but you can still contribute to
it, like, Google Docs falls
down there immediately.
So, like for the web and
for Git, how do we enable these
technologies
for technical people
? Git is terrible for new
folks. Yeah, it can be.
It can be, like, it can be
scary
. You can
compare Git to DropBox, it's
easy to get your head around, a
magical folder, whereas Git,
I'm suddenly introduced to the
terminal or some sort
of application, is like these
branching lines everywhere,
there's like a lot of concepts
that you have to be introduced
to.
Getting comfortable with the
terminal interfaces is a hurdle
in my opinion. I'm fine with
it, but it can be a challenge
for newcomers.
Yeah, well said. Maybe we can
show nondevs how to run build
scripts
inside VSCode, yeah, that's
true, but still
need VSCode and, like, to use
the terminal and, I mean, it's
also not
an all or nothing approach.
Like, if we can make it...
every step we can make it a
little bit easier, then more
people can access this
technology.
So many don't (inaudible) with
Git.
I agree, it's hard to get
folks,
I love when all this Git stuff
involved, running commands and
CLI.
Git is awesome, but
intimidating, maybe 11ty
community can provide a real
simple introduction.
Yeah, it's like something we're
thinking about a lot is how can
we give the power of Git
abstract a lot of the
complexity and then introduce,
we've had a big debate whether
we introduce new terms or
educate on Git terminology.
So, like, think of a save
versus a commit.
I think it would be more ideal
if everyone used the same
language, which would be
commit, then there's
no ambiguity or confusion
between those.
Trust me, it would be better,
too many ideas where the
product is harder to understand
and use, we've got to speak to
direct impact. For sure.
Nice. Yeah, good ideas there.
DropBox is file storage first,
yeah, that's a good way to put
it. And different tradeoffs
because
of that.
I worked with
norm engineers at previous jobs
and they used Git GUI.
I mean, I use a Git GUI.
I just like seeing on the
screen exactly what's happening
and, like, I use the GitHub
desktop and
that gives me confidence I'm
not going to miss something.
Welcome to the terminal, it
doesn't say anything if you get
it right and screams at you if
you get it wrong. And also, you
completely break your computer.
Good luck.
[ Laughter ]
That's good. All right, we're
ready for our next speaker. We
have Mayank
. They're a designer, design
engineer who cares deeply about
accessibility and inclusivity.
They enjoy working with new
revolutionary web tech such as
HTML and CSS, hell yeah.
In their free time, they run
their mouth on their personal
blog.
So Mayank's talking about Don't
Fear the Cascade.
[ Applause ]
Mayank, welcome. Great to have
you here.
≫ MAYANK: Great to be here.
≫ MIKE: I sometimes fear the
cascade, so I'm interested to
hear this talk. Over to you.
≫ MAYANK: All right.
So this talk is titled don't
fear the cascade.
And I want to talk about not
the dish soap, I want to talk
about CSS, specifically , CSS.
The cascade is probably the
reason why CSS gets such a
bad on developers.
That's why I'm giving this
talk. The cascade doesn't have
to be this unknown, scary
thing.
If you haven't been keeping up,
CSS has legitimately become
awesome.
We have the half serial class
and
nesting built into CSS now and
scope styling, how awesome is
that?
And for the first time ever, we
have the tools to manage the
cascade in a way that feels
more hinged for lack of a
better word.
Yeah, this is a
topic with multiple layers of
rabbit holes. To keep things
digestible, I'll simplify my
explanations and provide
practical suggestions along the
way.
So to understand the cascade,
we're going to start with a
completely blank
slate with minimum amount of
HTML required to file a page or
create a page, rather, not even
style it.
And let's put a humble button
element in there. And
immediately, we can see that
this button element still has
default styling, even though
there's not CSS on the page.
Earlier Miriam explained this
in more detail.
But these styles come from the
user style sheet.
And yes, these default styles
do respect the light and dark
team . So my system, operating
system uses dark theme, this
button is styled in a dark
theme . I won't spoil the
surprise, because
I'm sure Sara's going to talk
about this later today.
But yeah, you can have dark
theme without writing CSS .
Yeah, the user style sheet is
literally CSS style but built
into the browser, this is where
the cascade starts.
On this slide, I have a screen
shot of style sheet.
I went to their source code and
found it there.
It's like hundred lines long.
Specifically, I'm showing a
small subsection
where this affects input, text
areas, and buttons . And this
rule sets up font property,
this
font property is probably the
reason why every CSS reset
that you see is something like
inherit, buttons
just so these elements will
match their
font size and font family of
their surroundings .
So, yeah, this is the first
step in the cascade.
And then, come author styles.
This is the more interesting
part. This is where the party
happens.
Before that, I want to talk
about shadow DOM really quick.
Shadow DOM allows you to attach
an internal
, and it can have hidden from
the main DOM.
And that unlocks cool things
like encapsulate styling.
Even if you don't like using
Shadow DOM directly, which is
totally
understandable, it's still good
to know because many built-in
elements use Shadow DO,
M underneath.
And I attached this blog post
if you want to learn more. I
explain how Shadow DOM works
here and this animation showing
how the light DOM and Shadow
DOM are interlinked together.
I explained, cool. I have a
screen shot of the detailed
element, which is
built into HTML itself, also
uses Shadow DOM.
Even if you don't use it
directly, you are using it
indirectly.
And yeah, the reason I bring
this up is Shadow DOM styles
cascade after the user spells,
if you have ha
my button component which is a
regular button and
style both from inside and
outside Shadow DOM, the outside
styles will win.
So the overall cascade order,
so far, goes something
like user agent styles, author
styles, Shadow DOM styles and
the rest of the page styles.
There's also the inline style
attribute which comes after
these. But that's not part of
cascade.
The browser doesn't need to
resolve the cascade in order to
get the style attribute.
It's literally attached to the
element itself.
But yeah, now that
we understand Shadow DOM, we
can talk about the rest of the
page. The most simple concept
is order of appearance.
So for example, you can style a
button using
an element selector and you can
make it pretty straight
forward. But what happens when
there's two of the rules?
The last one wins, this makes
sense. CSS written, top to
bottom and the last one
overrides anything before it.
But these element selectors
aren't super useful on their
own. What if you only want to
style this one particular
button?
This is where I would use a
class instead of an element
selector . But when we do this,
we find that
the order of appearance seems
to not matter anymore.
The class selector wins over
the element selector even if it
comes before.
So what's going on here?
And thens a to that is
specificity.
Hopefully, I said that right.
Specificity. I'm not going to
go into too much detail here
because it's a complex, but
pretty easily understood topic.
Just Specificity is a score
made of three parts.
Starting from the right side,
elements and pseudo element
selectors contribute to the
least significant part,
classes, and attribute
selectors and pseudo classes go
in the middle and IDs go in the
most significant part.
So the browser will take the
score and use it to determine
which selector wins.
Chrome dev tools even shows you
the specificity when you hover
selector.
If I go and inspect this,
and I hover over selector, you
can see it says, 201, that's
the specificity score.
Yeah, you don't have to
calculate it by hand,
essentially.
So in the previous example,
specificity of the button
selector, the button class was
0 10, but the specificity of
the element was 001, so it's
more specific, it's by order of
appearance.
As you can imagine, with really
large selectors, the
specificity would become a bit
cumbersome
to manage and that's why the
general advice given to us is
keep specificity low.
And this is good advice.
We should almost certainly
avoid ID selectors, for
example. And we can still use
them.
We can still use them instead
of #ID, we can use a natural
selector
. Or we can make a class
specifically for the thing
you're selecting.
So it's easy to understand the
problem with high specificity,
but keeping specificity low can
sometimes be challenging,
especially when you want to
share styles between different
elements
, so you might, like, you might
be tempted to make
a single class or every bend of
the button.
But each shares the base cloud
of the button and that gets
complicated.
Sometimes, we tend to go too
far with this advice . Where we
want to keep specificity, not
just low, but
totally flat, by only using
single class selectors.
This usually is done through a
convention or tooling like CSS
Modules.
And yeah, I've always just
found this kind
of advice restrictive. It feels
like using CSS without the
cascade.
So, yeah, for the rest of the
presentation, I want to show
you how much better things can
be with modern CSS .
The two topics that I would
broadly cover are
controlling specificity and
controlling the cascade itself.
Let's start with the easy one.
You might already know you can
increase the specificity of a
class selector by chaining it
to itself.
You can even use CSS nesting to
chain ampersands, this can
be pretty useful when you need
it, but only increases the
middle portion of the
specificity.
Now, this next part might kind
of blow your mind, but you can
use the is
pseudo class to make a huge
jump in specificity.
This is pseudo class, it's
interesting, lets you group
multiple selectors into a
select
single selector, but changes
the specificity of the whole
thing so only the strongest
selector in the group counts.
What this means is, you can
have a class selector act
like it has the specificity of
the ID selector.
And this ID selector doesn't
need to exist. It can just be
there hanging by itself.
You can do the same thing even
easier using the not pseudo
class. So this one requires you
to use
the impossible selector where
you can use
two IDs because, remember, an
element can only have one ID.
So this selector would never
match, and we're saying,
never not match this selector.
So this will match the thing
you chain it to. I love this
because you can chain it to
anything to scope it down, just
how much you want while
retaining the super high
specificity .
And if you chain it to the
universal selector, it'll match
everything by having the high
specificity that we want. You
shouldn't need this very often.
But it's so handy when you just
want to have certain styles,
have the highest priority.
So with that out of the way,
let's talk about decreasing
specificity.
We know how to increase it, how
do we decrease it? Because
that's kind of the goal, right?
We want to keep specificity
low, at least that's what
everybody tells us . So that's
where the rare pseudo class
comes in .
There is except it doesn't add
to the specificity.
We can put an ID selector in
there, and it'll have zero
specificity.
And just like is, you can chain
it to other selectors
. So you can have some parts
inside that don't count towards
the specificity, but the things
outside
do count.
There's one restriction
here you can't put a pseudo
element selector inside, but
that's just a thing that you'll
get used to. But yeah, in other
words, we now have a CSS
native way of writing any kind
of selector you want with just
the right amount of
specificity. That's awesome.
CSS is awesome.
The most obvious way to use
where is when you want to
create select this for CSS
preset. This kind of makes
sense.
You want the reset to have the
lowest cascade priority. You
put everything in where.
And I built my own reset that
uses this technique . And you
can find it on NPM under
the end cap name space.
With where, you can make zero
specificity, but many don't do
that.
I would actually suggest coming
up with a desire specificity
for all of your other styles.
So you might want your global
style to be no higher than
0,0,1. And you can still use
longer selectors there,
like restricting the
specificity . And yeah, you can
--
the point here is you can kind
of
just control the specificity
while not having restrictions
on how you're writing your CSS.
One thing I like to do is,
like, put everything that is
nested inside the main rule .
Put where so that the whole
block has a flat specificity,
and everything inside it has
zero specificity.
So you're like going top to
down, everything is like using
source order or order of
appearance and, like,
everything inside is flat.
So you have some specificity,
but just not too much
. So yeah, if you haven't use
d where, give it a shot, it'll
solve your headaches and it's
back all the way back to Safari
14 . Ask And that brings us to
my favorite topic, controlling
the cascade using layers.
If you have a CSS rule, you can
wrap it in a layer, an
anonymous layer, and you can
give it a name, and you can put
other styles in it, too.
So far, so good. But the
interesting part is when you
use multiple layer statements
and
put different -- or multiple
layer blocks and put different
styles in them.
So here, the second layer will
always be the first layer.
It's kind of like order of
appearance, but without
specificity part.
So here in the second layer,
we're using
where pseudo class, but the
first one still wins. Or
actually, I misspoke.
So in the second one, we're
using the
pseudo class with a lower
specificity but still wins
because it's in a layer that
comes later.
So the layer order is kind of
resolved in the way in the
order that is defined.
And then, there's on layer
styles which always have the
highest priority. It'll win
over all layer styles.
This might not feel intuitive,
but it kind of makes sense.
You'll get used to it.
The way I think about it, you
want to start with you lower
priority
layer so you can put your CSS
reset in a layer and leave
everything else unlayered.
This kind of allows you to
slowly add layers to your
codebase . Yeah, that's
kind of my introduction to
layer. I still have some time
so I'm going to dive a little
bit deeper. I mentioned layer
order.
It's the layers are prioritized
in the order that they first
appear . So if you have layer A
and layer B and
write layer A, again, the rules
inside the second appearance of
layer A will still lose to
layer B . The layer A was
already defined all the way up
there. To make this more
predictable, you can separate
layer statements from layer
blocks.
The layer statement will define
the order and the layer blocks
will contain the actual rules.
And you probably want to define
the layer order up front
because all of your other
styles or before all of your
other styles.
You can put the layer
statements in the
beginning of your first style
sheet, but what I like to do is
put it in style tag, and put
the style tag all the way up in
the head.
Because I don't trust
bundlers to put my first style
sheet in the correct place. So
I just like doing it myself
before any
other style sheets are linked.
So, yeah. Let's go even deeper.
So we can nest layers, this
functionality is built into
layers. So it's separate from
CSS nesting. You can nest
layers without using CSS
nesting.
And if you only want to
reference a nested
sublayer, you can use the dot
syntax.
But it gets even more
interesting when you do use CSS
nesting, because you can put a
layer block inside another
CSS rule, like a class
selector. You want to style
different parts of the same
component using different
layers.
I want to point out that this
is a CSS nesting is a
relatively new feature, so you
might want to use preprocessors
, SaaS to trans
get this part out for you. I
find this useful especially
when different part of the
components need to have
different priorities. For
example, I might have overrides
as a sublayer where I put
my scaler styles and print
styles.
These should always be all of
the other styles of the
component.
Moving on to layer strengths
and the idea of style sheets.
You can reference the same
layer name in multiple CSS
files and they'll work just
like you expect regardless of
how they're imported.
So you might have a giant
components layer that is
referenced in every single one
of your components and within
single file components,
in Vue or Astro, you can import
into a layer.
The external CSS pod doesn't
need to contain any layers. And
I want to give a shout out to
CSS
import here, it can transform
the import statements to
layer block statements and
inline all of the contents of
the style sheet and even works
for remote URLs.
This is great for performance,
mainly.
And I want to talk about SAUTSZ
SaaS real quick.
Layers were just like you
expect in SaaS, but when you
want to combine multiple SaaS
files into a single layer, you
need
to use metaupload CSS, you
can't use the use statement.
This was a recent update made
to SaaS to ensure that meta.
load CSS is a canonical way to
use layers in SaaS.
And finally, the most important
slide, you might have used
the important keyword to win
specificity battles in the
past. But we all know it's a
shameful hack and the general
advice is to
avoid important. And earlier, I
already showed various ways
to increase specificity. So if
you want to just win a
specificity battle, then
use one of those techniques
instead of important.
But the reason why important is
interesting here is emerges
kind of differently in layers.
The important keyword is more
important when used in lower
priority layers.
This feels strange, but I think
Miriam was explaining earlier
that
user agents and preferences
might declare some styles that
are legitimately important.
So even though all of the other
user styles are less important,
they want to say this
particular thing should be more
important . So works similarly
in layers.
So CSS reset, you might have a
rule that says,
may not be important if the
dialog is not open.
This helps ensure that
subsequent layers can't
accidentally override the
display when it's always meant
to be hidden
. I've done that accidentally
so many times where I set a
display grid
on the dialog and it shows when
it's not supposed to be
showing. So now I handle that
in my reset.
If you take everything we've
seen about layers so far, our
cascade
overlooks something like the
user styles and the page styles
and the Shadow DOM styles ask
and and unlayered styles and
the important styles come after
all of that.
And since I'm running out of
time, I won't go into too much
detail here, but important
style also have their own
quirks. In that, the user agent
important
styles are more important than
inline style attributes, for
example.
But yeah, I'm going to talk
about browser support real
quick. Browser, I think, 2022,
February, is when all browsers
shipped cascade layers. It was
a coordinated rollout and very
impressive to watch.
But if that still makes you
uneasy, there's post cascade
layers, which polyfills
everything
we've talked about so far.
And then, there's revert layer,
I haven't talked about it so
far because it's such
a broad topic. You might not
want to use it yet.
I have a blog post on this
topic.
And the only part I want to
mention just right now is that
if you're trying to use revert,
consider
revert layer instead. It works
even when you don't use cascade
layers.
Then, there's some best
practices. I think I'll skip
that.
Slides are stuck.
Oh, no, OK, sure.
There was an iframe here where
I was going to show that layers
and scope are different.
This is a CSS tricks article
written by Miriam Suzanne.
And yeah, I really want to
emphasize this point is that
layers and scopes are different
things.
You don't want to create a
layer for every single
component. They can overlap so
you can have layers within the
same
component or don't use it scope
your CSS.
And I think we can wrap it up
here since I ran out of time.
I just want to mention one last
thing, that I think Peter
Griffin would really enjoy
using cascade layers.
Yeah, that's all, if you want
to learn more, subscribe to my
RSS feed, and that's all for
me.
≫ MIKE: I just learned so much
there.
It's like a pain I didn't know
I had where I feel like in a
lot of situations I add a
lot of specificity to kind of
wrangle the browser to do what
I want
when, actually, what I want is
layers, which
not aware of at all.
Yeah. It's going to take me a
while to get my head around
that.
≫ MAYANK: Yeah.
≫ MIKE: It's a completely
different paradigm.
≫ MAYANK: The thing I tell
people is, start with just the
reset . Put that in your, in a
layer, and if you have some
third party styles, put
that in a layer, you don't have
to migrate your whole codebase
to layers right away.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
And so the advantage of doing
that is -- let's take a
really basic reset of, I'm
setting the margin of HTML
element to zero.
So that's in my reset in a lay
er.
But now, I decide I actually
want some padding on my HTML
, so then, I can have HTML and
what's a nonlayer called?
Called the root?
Or?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah. HTML and root
are going to be the same thing
to each other.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, now I can set my
padding on the HTML and
it'll just work without any
more specificity?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah, and if you wrap
it in rare to make the zero
specificity, it'll still work.
Because unlayer styles over
layer styles.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome. Very
cool.
Mayank, thanks for sharing that
today, I learned a lot. I'm
glad you're here.
≫ MAYANK: Thanks for having me.
≫ MIKE: All right.
We're going to keep this
conference going
next we have David
, he's based in New Zealand
where he covers static site
generators and related open
source tools for CloudCannon.
When he isn't wrangling
templates, he helps to organize
Hugo Conf, builds
arcade game cabinets and carves
wooden spoons
to slow static site generators.
Liam PZ
Bigalo creates tooling for open
source sites including static
site tool search page
fund and static API generateor
that we'll be learning more
about today.
He co-created the
game Trunket and still spends
hours playing it for quality
control purposes and to learn
fun effects about
etymology.
Today, they're talking about
managing content management .
Git CMS and static
generation
.
[ Applause ]
Welcome, David.
≫ DAVID: Thank you. I wanted to
introduce, we're in the same
room.
We'll be passing this back and
forth as we talk.
CloudCannon, we focus on two
things, we want to make it
easier
for everyone to manage the
content, and the visual
interface, and on creating and
supporting open source
, agnostic tooling
. It's important for us that
there's absolutely no vendor
locking in CloudCannon, we
think your site, your source,
and your content should be
yours and stored in your Git
repo. You can take it when you
want to, it's fully portable.
Today, we're joining forces to
talk about how CloudCannon
has a feature called site
mounting that can combine with
a new open source tool that
creates esthetic API.
And that's aimed at allowing
large organizations to receive
the same benefits of static
sites and CMS as smaller single
site orgs.
So site mounting. Site mounting
allows multiple sites to sync
to one build image
on CloudCannon. You might have
seen this in action on 11ty
already
. Zach made a video about it
when the feature first launched
last year.
But today, in addition to
shearing components and layup
files on sites, we're going to
demonstrate a data link and
group of connected sites 11ty
sites , enabling content
syndication and
aggregation, new tool
flatlink.
≫ LIAM: Flatlake is tool we're
developing similar to the way
the static site generator spits
out static HTML files that can
be used as a website, Flat
lake spits out JSON files that
can be query . We'll show how
to aggregate and share content
between stand alone 11ty sites.
≫ DAVID: Let's imagine we're
tasked with building several
real good websites for quite a
large organization.
We're going to demo four
smaller sites connected to one
larger parent site, but there's
no technical limit. We'll call
out the larger site real big
company. You can check it out
if you like Real Big.
company, look at the GitHub,
it's all connected.
We love static sites, we love
flat files, we love 11ty.
And our smaller sites static
laboratories, 11ty
incorporated, and
liminal interfaces. It's very
unbrand.
You can imagine a large
corporation or university,
perhaps, needing a setup like
this.
They may or may not be
technical, they'll be managing
several hundred sites. So, I
can jump into this right now,
I'm editing on CloudCannon,
this is an 11ty
site I'm editing, I'm marking
down live in the visual.
It's great, right?
Really good for a single site.
I can edit everything quickly.
I can add page components that
our developer has built. But
what about a smaller site?
Had What about our smaller
sites?
If we want to jump to what the
big corporation needs, what if
they want to spin up a new
site?
They have quite a large wish
list here. How do they get
exactly the same page building
components in each site ?
What about brand recognition
for the real big corporate
family. And perhaps, more
importantly, if we update a
layout or a component, how can
it be reflected on all of our
sites?
That's a pretty decent sized
wish list. And of course, we
want this on 11ty for all of
the performance benefits of a
static site and on CloudCannon
for the benefits of visual edit
or without content stored in
Git. We can do all of this.
We can see this in action here,
this is Xity, a subsidiary of
real big company. You can see
here, our
site is retrieving the source
files from the component
library, that's the shear ed
common re
shared common repo and from the
common repo into the sites
includes layouts.
This is pretty straightforward
setup. Just an option within
CloudCannon to set up.
Here's a simplified version
where our site folder and our
conflict
tent files are sourced from the
content repo and layouts
sourced from the central repo.
And the important aspect is
that from here the 11ty
build proceeds as if all files
were arranged in one folder
originally and thus built as
one unified stacked site.
And once any files in the
common repo are changed, layout
is tweaked, perhaps, or a new
page building component is
added, any downstream link
sites have immediate access to
the new components and any
layout changes will
automatically rebuild every
affected site.
≫ LIAM: Where are we?
Now that we can share codes
between the sites in our
company, it'll be great if we
could share content, too.
So, bringing up their next wish
list, we have the content
wishlist.
So, on the main corporate
website, we want to rehost some
of the
featured news articles from
each division, plus for every
division's website, we want to
list the news articles
from every other division.
With this level of
interconnection between sites,
a typical approach would force
us to move the source of truth
for our content
out of our sites and into some
central data link.
But we don't want our team to
have to edit a data lake
directly, we want them to edit
their site in context.
To achieve that, we're going to
show how Flatlake and
site mounting work together to
create a static Git base data
lake, without change in
workflow for
the company. You can picture
building this with something
like site mounting on its own.
The burden of understanding all
of the source files means this
approach doesn't scale beyond a
few sites.
We're going to use Flatlake
to aggregate into a static API
and give every website access
to the data at build time.
We're going to keep the content
experience grounded in their
website, not in some giant
database.
Flatlake is driven by a single
configuration file and runs as
a stand alone command.
Our data lake repo
with just a Flatlake build
file. Looking down the file, we
see the extent of Flatlake
setup.
We define a news collection,
give it a set of inputs, one
for each division's news
folder.
We merge in some data to each
input to filter by division.
And I accidentally clicked on
the wrong thing .
[ Laughter ]
Here we are.
And -- there we go.
And -- we tell Flatlake we want
the
front data and the frontend
content to be part of the same
API . You'll notice this repo
doesn't contain the content
it's referencing. How you
achieve that depends on the
environment.
Locally, tends to use symbolic
links or Git submodules can be
good.
But for this talk, we're going
back to our good friend site
mounting. In CloudCannon, we
mount from each of the division
sites into the data lake and
hit build.
Behind the scenes, Flatlake
pulls the
markdown content files and
metadata and builds them up
into what I've been calling a
static API
. If we look at Flatlake's
output
directory, we can see a bunch
of folders containing JSON
files, files that list every
item in a given collection or
globally.
And there are files that
aggregate content on certain
data.
For example, highlighted as a
file that lists every news post
that was written by David.
Within it, we see the JSON
RENGS representation of the
content that Flatlake ingested.
The content allows you to host
them as a live API
with pagenation. And since this
is a flat folder full
of files, we can load it as
data, which we'll do for our
real big company.
So far, we've been site
mounting source files from one
site to another, which anyone
can do on CloudCannon.
To use our content as site
data, we want to output the
files . We can mount the data
files that generated into all
of
Real Big's 11ty sites. And it's
a feature of our higher tier
plans and unlocks
options for larger teams.
With the static JSON files on
disc, it's trivial to pull and
use this data.
On the main website, we're
pulling Flatlake's files adds
computer data ready to be used.
Since this glues together with
siting, you don't need to
trigger any builds.
One one of our we write a new
article,
it triggers Flatlake and
triggers every site that
consumes it to build with the
aggregated
content automatically. And a
great feature of the
syndication is it works
seamlessly
with the Git workflows. Content
only syndicates when
it lands on a main branch, and
each site can have as many
environments as they need
without leaking content.
No need to fork one giant data
lake or maintain version
content within it.
With all O that in place, plus
more liquid content
behind the scenes, we have
content syndicated and shown
across of Real Big's web
properties.
On the main corporate website,
you can list and read all
featured news articles from the
divisions.
And we made the related
articles section of each
division's website list the
latest news from all of
divisions, as well.
≫ DAVID: All of this dev work
only happens once behind the
scenes . For a team of editors,
website users and perhaps, the
nontechnical content folk, all
they need to do is
never get to the site they're
working on, choose the content
type that they're creating or
editing, and just get to work.
They have the layout and the
components already. And once
published, the content will be
syndicated to the parent site
as well as to any other sites
that mount the data lake.
It's also important to remember
that editors don't
need to wade through just to
get the content, they get it in
situ in the environment just
for them.
And that kind of sums up how a
real big company can build
real good static websites with
a great tool like 11ty. Can
share layouts across any number
of sites,
aggregate, syndicate the
content, and can keep
everything portable
with Git-based CMS, and that
means as I've said before, no
vendor locking, you always
control your
content as we think you should.
If you'd like to try any of
this out for yourself, please
have a look at CloudCannon.
com, and Zach and Mike
mentioned earlier, we have
a draw for a free migration to
CloudCannon and a bunch of
discounted plans over at
CloudCannon.
com/11tyConf. This is only open
during the conference. So you
have a couple of hours to
enter, still.
If you do miss out on those,
you can
still try out with a free trial
in one of the included
starters.
We have a new team plan we've
added for universities and
colleges who, I think, are
quite likely to find site
mounting and Flatlake a really
handy solution to manage that
standard several hundred sites.
You can also check out Flatlake
at flatlake.
app. And finally, do feel free
to take a look at Real
Big. company.
Read the content that was so
much fun to write . And check
out the files for Real
Big company if you'd like to
dig through the source there.
We're happy to answer questions
in chat after the talk or on
Mastodon, if you prefer. Thanks
very much.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, team. What a
duo.
≫ DAVID: That's great.
We're going to move on quickly,
but I want to quickly ask, what
kind of use cases do
you -- you mentioned,
universities with a lot of
different websites.
What other use cases do you
think this would be valuable
for?
≫ DAVID: I think anyone who
wants to share content to be
able to syndicate
content between sites, anyone
who wants sites to be
consistent.
It's for the users, people who
see the website, you could do
either approach
. You could have very different
websites with exactly the same
components.
I don't think there's a limit
to where this could go, really.
≫ MIKE: Very cool. Again, just
like page fun, it's
dispelling the myth of the
limitations of static.
Now, you can have a full API of
your content to access it.
≫ DAVID: That's right, I used
to work for a university, we
had 300 sites and it was a pain
to do the content and
everything had to be manually
synced and kept perfect
separately, and
a tool like this would've saved
-- would've changed my life .
[ Laughter ]
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
Very cool. Thanks, team.
All right, we're going to move
on to our next muted break.
Going to kick off now.
A prompt for our drawing is
going to be Lighthouse.
≫ MIKE: All right, we're back
in action.
So, we've got 5 minutes before
our next speaker.
So, let's take a quick
question/answer with
the chat. So, I want to ask two
questions.
One, which video game would you
love to see
turn into a movie? I just
finish
ed Fallout, I thought it was
fantastic
they captured the world so
well.
And brought a lot from that
game into the series.
And it was cool just getting to
experience
that world with my wife who is
not a gamer. So that was cool.
What other game do you think
would -- well, what game do you
think would -- needs
an adapt?
That's one, and then, two,
what's the most
unconventional place you've
worked from ? I'll go first.
Probably the one that M co
comes
to mind for me, there was one
afternoon where I couldn't be
in my house, and
I needed to take a meeting. So
I went to our garage and
took the meeting with my laptop
on top of our trash can.
It was like the perfect height
for standing disk.
And I blurred the background so
they couldn't -- you couldn't
really tell, honestly.
My wife came home, she was in
the car and she opened the
garage door and, so, you just
see -- you hear this big
mechanical noise,
and have the garage door open
as I'm in the middle of this
meeting .
That's my most unconventional.
What do we got?
Not a gamer but can't wait for
Fallout season 2.
Yeah, it's going to be really
cool. We've got a lot here.
I just started that, that would
be fascinating. Zelda, maybe
like seems like Nintendo's
figured out how to make content
out of their property . That'll
be interesting one to watch.
Seems pretty natural for them
to tackle next.
Untitled Goose Game. I wonder
how that would work.
Gears of War, Fantasy 6 is a
hell of a story, I haven't
played it, but I should. I've
done 7, 8, 9
gears -- spirit era ? All that
and Last
of Us has been killer. The next
Last of Us, I can't wait for
that.
Mine Forever Voyaging. I
haven't heard of that. Half
Life.
Yeah, there was just a game
someone
can fill me in the chat, it was
released by New Zealand game
development company that is
kind
of -- it's like inspired by
Half
Life 1, and kind of is loose ly
following on from that story.
It looks awesome.
I haven't played it yet.
It's just being released in
it's like
a -- what's it called? A
prerelease. Aspire. That would
be cool.
Horizon Dawn, oh Netflix is
making a show, also, Monkey
Island.
Lots of Horizon Dawns.
(Inaudible) yeah.
Maybe that's coming up. Portal?
Yeah, that would be
interesting.
Dredge.
Shout out to New Zealand game
companies.
Here we go. Yeah, check it out.
It is perfect.
All right, we're ready to move
on to our next speaker, who is
Chris Ferdinanderdinandi.
His developer tips newsletter
is read by thousands each
weekday. Find it at
gomakethings. com.
Chris is talking about come to
the light side. HTML with
components.
≫ CHRIS: Mike, always a
pleasure to chat.
≫ MIKE: It is, and I know this
is a topic close to your heart.
I'm really excited to see what
you have to say today.
≫ CHRIS: Thanks. Yeah, glad to
be here. Thanks for having me.
Actually share. Cool.
My screen is now fully
obscured, is that OK ?
≫ MIKE: Yep, you're good.
≫ CHRIS: Perfect. Awesome.
We're going to talk about web
components today.
Full disclosure, I have ADHD, I
might bounce off screen as I
move around a little bit today.
Web components sit in this
uncanny valley.
Not quite react React
components, not with the grain
of the web either.
I think a lot of that is really
because we've been thinking
about and using them wrong.
Today, I want to show you what
I think is a better way to use
web components, or at least one
that works with the grain of if
web rather than against it.
Mike, thanks for that great
introduction, I'm
Chris Ferdinandi, you can find
me on gomakethings. com.
I teach how to make things in
the web through courses,
workshops , and daily developer
tips newsletter, and
I consult with amazing
companies. These days, that
means building custom web
components, like
I recently did for a project
with NASA.
The thing with web components,
they've been around for a
really long time. They were
first announced in 2011, which
is over a decade
ago, and they've been
supporting major browsers for
years.
Now, when they first came out,
a lot of folks thought they
were going to be the thing that
finally killed React.
And if you're watching in 2024
or beyond, you
know that they weren't. React
started to swallow up
everything.
And people often use them like
you would a React component.
So a lot of tutorials that you
see start with an empty custom
HTML element and then, they use
JavaScript to inject the HTML.
And don't forget about the
shadow DOM, there was a lot of
hype around using the shadow
DOM
to keep the HTML isolated from
the rest of the UI. This was
promoted as a key feature of
web components.
Of course, once you do that,
your HTML doesn't have
access to your global styles
sheets, so you need to inject
your CSS with JavaScript, too.
This approach feels a lot like
React but native
. But if you want React-like
components or React-like
experience, React and smaller
libraries
like Preact, honestly in my
opinion, they do it better.
That sounds weird coming from
someone who spends their whole
career
evangelizing vanilla
JavaScript, but the reality
that web components don't have
data reactivity, although you
can hack that in with
proxies, they don't have DOM
diffing. And they don't have
support for single- file
components.
Although, if you use a plugin
like Zach's web C,
you can kind of sort of make
that work. If you're a
developer who likes React, web
components often aren't React-y
enough.
But because this approach often
starts with an empty element
that relies on JavaScript to
render its content, web
standards and progressive
enhancement evangelists like
myself also dislike this
approach.
I think this is why it feels
like it's taken so long for web
components to catch on. For the
rest of this talk, I want to
show you a better way.
It's the approach that I use
with NASA and various other
clients to build web components
that are simple, reliable, and
that work more with the grain
of the web.
Here's the agenda for the rest
of this talk.
We're going to start by talking
about a new way to build web
components
or a different way to build web
components that's more with the
grain of the web. We're going
to dig into tips and tricks
that make working with web
components easier and we're
going to round things out by
looking at specific
examples, including building a
web component this way from
scratch .
Let's start by talking about a
new way about thinking about
web components that honestly
kind of old school. November of
last year, Jeremy Keith wrote
an article about this approach
. And he wrote, try not to
bring React mindset with you.
Do you really need to invent a
new component from
scratch or can you use HTML up
to the limit
and unHans enhance the markup?
It's a name that started to
stick and I'm seeing it pop
up more and more around the
web.
HTML web component is about
progressive enhancement.
So rather than an empty
element, you start with
perfectly functional HTML
. Here, we have a collection of
headings and some content that
goes with them.
Let's imagine we eventually
want this to be an accordion
component where clicking or
tapping on the heading causes
the content that goes with it
to get expanded or hidden.
We can use a web component for
that. As a convenient way to
enhance what's already there
into something more powerful
and interactive. And we start
that process by wrapping our
content in a custom element.
In this case, we'll call it
accordion group because that's
a very easy and obvious
description of what this thing
is going to be.
When the web component runs and
does its thing, the HTML and
the DOM ends up looking
different.
You end up with button elements
around the heading texts so you
have a focusable interactive
element, you get
some ARIA
attributes so that screen
readers understand the
interactions on the page . And
the content gets hidden by
default using the hidden
attribute.
But if this never actually ran,
you would still
have perfectly functional
markup. And that's really the
big difference between HTML
web components and the way they
were historically presented in
a lot of older tutorials talk
about them.
Now, this probably looks a lot
like old school DOM
manipulation. If you've been
around for a while, this is how
we used to build things.
And honestly, it really is, but
web components bring a lot of
benefits that make building
interactive UI a lot easier.
For starters, they're, in my
opinion, easier to write.
You get to write your HTML as
HTML rather than HTML in JS,
yuck.
And rather THARN
than unique selectors, yo you
combine your components once
and wrap your HTML in your
custom element.
You can even have multiple
versions on a page.
Each one automatically
instantiates as its own unique
instance.
Because functional HTML is
there, people get a usable
experience immediately.
And if your web component fails
to load for some reason, users
still have a perfectly
functional experience instead
of one that doesn't work.
Web components also let you
provide options and settings
declaratively in the markup.
This makes it a lot more
obvious what's happening just
by looking at the HTML.
The behavior isn't hidden away
in a JavaScript file somewhere.
And you can include multiple
instances, each with their own
settings , through the HTML
alone.
No more instantiating with
different selectors and
settings , often some
JavaScript file you have to
hunt down every time you want
to make an update.
Let's look at tips and tricks
that make working with web
components even easier.
Now, if you've never created a
web component before, I think
it's worthwhile to start by
kind of building
one, and we're going to start
with a custom element.
Here, I'm going to use the most
cliche of examples, a
countercomponent. So you get a
button, you click it, and the
text updates
to indicate how many times it's
been clicked or tapped or
activated.
This is honestly kind of a
terrible example for an HTML
web component, you're not
progressively
enhancing anything, the button
is absolutely useless without
the JavaScript. But it's a
really simple tutorial to
explain. So if you've never
worked with web components
before, it's a great way to
kind of wrap your head around
some of the concepts.
We're going to roll with it. We
start by wrapping some existing
HTML with a custom element. In
this case, count up.
And then, in our JavaScript
file, we use the custom
elements define method to
define a custom
element and associate behavior
with it.
You pass in the name of the
custom element as a string.
And just as a quick aside, web
component
, custom elements have to have
a dash in them, single word
elements are reserved for
browser native elements
. When you make your own, it
has to have one dash. We pass
the name in, here it's count
up.
And we pass in a class that
extends the HTML element class.
Your class needs to have a
constructer method in it. And
that runs automatically on each
element and creates
unique instance of your
component. And then, inside the
constructer, you always run the
super method first. This gives
you access to the properties
and methods of the HTML
element class that this class
is extending. And then, after
that, you can run any of your
custom code .
Now, web components provide
some useful ways
to handle that, and in
particular, they make
encapsulation really easy.
It's built in, even without the
shadow DOM. So while light DOM
elements, so things not in the
shadow DOM
will still be accessible,
they're scoped to your custom
element . And that provides
some unique benefits.
For example, in your web
component, this keyword refers
to the current
instantiation of the component
and the custom element wrapped
around it. You can define
properties on it. In this case,
we're setting a count property
of zero and we're going to
increase that every time the
button is clicked.
And, you can search for
elements inside
your custom element by scoping
them to the this keyword.
If I use the query selector
method on this, I'm looking for
the button inside my custom
element rather than everywhere
in the DOM. So it makes finding
elements in your component and
manipulating them way easier.
You don't have to use any
weird, special tricks.
You also get built in CSS
scoping, if you want it.
By using the light DOM instead
of the shadow DOM, your web
component will automatically
inherit your style sheet
styles, and in my opinion, one
of the biggest wins of this
approach because
shadow DOM styling, is a
painful experience. This gets
around this. But if you want to
scope styles in your web
component, you can use the
custom HTML
element as part of your
selector string.
Here, our button is going to
inherit all of the button
global styles and we can
override or modify
by prefixing with the count up
element.
You can even use CSS to detect
when the JavaScript is ready
with the defined pseudo class.
And if you define it with the
not pseudo class,
you can detect when the
JavaScript for the component is
not ready. If you've ever
written a DOM manipulation
library before and done
something like add a class to
the document or the body
element, that way you can
modify your styling depending
on whether the library has
loaded, or not, you don't have
to do that anymore.
Web components provide a
built-in way to detect that.
Using the defined pseudo class.
Web components also have some
built-in methods that make
handling events easier. With
the add event listener method,
you can pass in an object
instead of a callback function
as that second argument .
If the object has a handle
event method, that method will
automatically run response to
the event and receive the event
object as an argument.
Now, why would you do that
instead of a callback function?
A lot of it has to do with this
keyword we talked about
earlier. In a normal callback
function, the "
this" keyword doesn't refer to
the instance, it refers to
either the element
or the window object depending
on the context in which it's
used.
But in the handle event method,
this is the instance, which
means we can access those
properties like count that we
need to manipulate some things,
as well as if we had other
methods in our class, we could
run those, too, without having
to do things like use the bind
method
or some weird hacks with arrow
functions and timing around WHN
when we create callback
functions .
And in this particular
instance, we are increasing our
count by one. And then, we're
updating the text inside our
button to show how many times
it's been clicked.
If you need to listen to more
than one type of event, you can
create "on" methods in your
class with each of your
different event types and use
the handle event method to
automatically route them
. Here, I have an on click
event. And whenever that event
type fires, my
handle event method is going to
automatically
run that for me so you don't
have to use a bunch of if else
statements.
Set handle event to do the work
for you .
With web components, you use
custom attributes in
your HTML to define your
options
and settings . Say you wanteded
to define,
42, you could add a start
attribute and give it a value.
In your constructer, you can
use the
get attribute method to get
that attribute and the parse
float to convert it from a
string into a number, and
if that attribute exists and a
valid number, you use it for
this count instead of the
default of zero.
If not, you fall back. Users
don't have to use it but they
have the option.
What had makes this approach
particularly nice is you can
now have
multiple instances of your Web
Component on a page, each one
can have their own options,
settings, and properties
, you never have to write any
additional JavaScript.
And you can tell by looking at
the element what its specific
settings are and how you expect
it to behavior.
And while Web Components don't
have reactive data like React
or Vue does, they do have a
built
-in mechanism for detecting
attribute changes.
For example, let's say you
wanted to stop the count up
component from counting when
the pause attribute is added to
it.
First, you define an
array of attributes you want to
observe and assign them to the
static observed attributes
property. And you do this for
performance reasons. So if you
were watching every single
attribute that
could or could not be added or
changed on an element, it could
start to bog down the memory
and create performance issues.
You say, just pay attention to
these.
Whenever one of those
attributes is changed in some
way, the attribute changed
callback method runs. And this
will be triggered whenever an
observed method is added,
removed, or changes in value.
And it receives three arguments
automatically.
The name of the attribute, its
old value, and its new value.
If you want to detect whether
the attribute has been added,
removed, or changed, you can
check the old and new
value properties when an
attribute was just added, the
old value will be null because
there was nothing there before.
When it's been removed, the new
value will be null
. In all other situations,
where the value's just
changing, it will be a string.
It could be an empty string,
could have some sort of value
with it, but it'll be a string.
In this particular case, if the
attribute was removed, so if
the -- I'm sorry, if it was
added, rather , if the old
value was null, we're going to
remove our click event
listeners. We stop detecting
clicks.
When the attribute gets
removed, we are going to add
our click event listener back
on.
Let's look at some examples of
things HTML web components are
particularly great at.
Let's say you have a button and
you want to show or hide some
content when it's pressed.
This is a classic show/hide
disclosure component.
First, we'd start by wrapping a
custom element around it . The
obviously named show/hide.
Now, you have an easy way to
associate a button and content
that goes with it. But if
there's no JavaScript, users
still get the content. In our
JavaScript, we'll start by
defining our custom
element, we'll pass in
show/hide and our class that
extends the HTML element.
And then, inside the
constructer for that class,
we'll run the super method and
we'll define our properties.
Maybe we'll get the button
using the query selector method
on this . And then, we will get
the
content, the next element
sibling, and assign that to a
property, as well. That way, we
can access them later. Next,
the initial UI.
We'll add an ARIA expanded
value with the value of false.
This is an accessibility
requirement. So it conveys to
people who use screen
readers what type of
interaction they could expect
from that button and what the
current state of it and its
content are.
And then, we'll hide the
content using the hidden
attribute.
Now, the HTML UI looks like
this after a Web Component
instantiates and runs.
Next, we will add a click event
listener to our button.
And we'll do that by passing
the instance, this, into the
add event listener. That way,
we can take advantage of the
handle event method.
Under the ARIA show/hide
pattern,
it should have an expanded
value of true when it's visible
and false when it's hidden.
Inside our handle event method,
we can check the current value
of that attribute on our button
and show or hide the content
accordingly. If it has a value
of true, content is currently
visible,
we'll change it to false, and
we'll set the hidden attribute
to hide that content.
Otherwise, we'll set it to true
to show the content and
remove the hidden attribute so
you can see it.
Now, that we have a functional
component, we might try adding
some styling to make it look a
little bit nicer.
We might, for example, change
the button color based on
whether the content is hidden
or visible.
We'll give it maybe a blue
color as the default, and we'll
make it darker when ARIA
expanded equals true, which we
can do by using an attribute
selector in the CSS.
Because we only want this to
apply to our show hide
component, we will scope our
CSS to
that element. And maybe we want
to hide the button element
until our web component
JavaScript
loads since it requires
JavaScript to work.
It's functionless until the Web
Component starts. We can use
the not and defined pseudo
classes for that
. And display none on our
button to hide it.
Another example, we talked
about little bit earlier, Web
Components are great for
transform LG ing headings and
content.
No worries, users still have
access to all of the headings
and all of the content.
I'm not going to walk through
the code for the rest of these
because we would be here all
day. Just some more examples to
kind of get your brain going on
what
you can do with this approach
to web components.
You might also take a list of
anchor elements and their so
associated content and turn
them into toggle tabs. No
JavaScript? Users get a
perfectly functional collection
of anchor links and content.
One of my favorite uses,
though, is forms.
The project I did for NASA
involved building out an entire
app and it was done almost
exclusively
through Form Interactions. I
like to create forms that work
with old school server submits
and full page reloads by
default. So you provide an
action that points to
some sort of server pass, the
form sends its data
to that path and the server
does some stuff . And then, I
use Web Components to turn them
into
a A
JAX forms and show a status
message or update the UI
instead of reloading the entire
page.
Without JavaScript, you still
get a perfectly usable form or
in the case with the NASA
project, a perfectly usable
app. But with it, you get
something even better, faster,
snappier . If you
forget everything else about
this talk, and I really hope
you remember more than just
this, but if you only remember
one thing, I hope your key
takeaway is to start
with functional HTML and then
enhance with Web Components. If
you found this interesting, I
put together a bunch of
additional resources for
building HTML
Web Components on gomake things.
com, you can find boilerplates
and more. Thank you all so
much. This was a lot of fun.
≫ MIKE: Chris, that was
incredible. I'm going to agree
with a lot of the chat.
That's probably the best
introduction to Web Components
that I've heard.
≫ CHRIS: Thank you.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
I feel like just seeing that
and a lot of things click into
place.
Particularly, like the defined,
not defined, I haven't -- I
wasn't aware of that.
But it's such an elegant
solution to that problem .
I've just been adding classes
to things recently to -- JS on
or something like that.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, thank you.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome.
So yeah, what do you think the
-- what should we be excited
about in the web component
space
? Clearly we need more adoption
and awareness around this.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, so I'm
particularly pessimistic about
shadow DOM, in general, it has
valid uses.
But if you're someone who
enjoys that or wish you could
do more with
Shadow DOM but also you wish
you could do the HTML first
approach I described today,
it's now possible to use
declarative Shadow
DOM, so you can write the stuff
that's going to end up in the
Shadow DOM in your HTML rather
than having to historically
they would all have to be
generated through JavaScript.
So, you know, there's now a way
to do that without it. I think
that's pretty exciting.
Not specific to Web Components
itself, but one thing I really,
I think the biggest thing that
we're
missing from the web platform
as a whole is some sort of
method that allows diffing the
DOM and
selecting the API without
clobbering everything, right?
Where you say, here's an
element, what it should look
like, change just what needs to
get changed. We need that.
That, in my opinion, would be
the thing that really kills
React
. You know, until then.
≫ MIKE: Where do you think that
comes from?
The browser specification and
...
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, I don't think
I've even seen a specification
for that . I know there are --
I heard rumors there's maybe
some specs specific to Web
Components for doing something
like that.
Maybe, as a proposal, not like
anything that's on a track to
get built. But I would love
that just as a general, like,
thing for the
web, not just Web
Component-specific .
≫ MIKE: Yeah, that would be
incredible.
Zach was telling me recently
that React, latest version of
React has custom component
support, so maybe React --
≫ CHRIS: Finally.
≫ MIKE: Kind of meets in the
middle of Web Components and
brings a lot of the ideas to a
broad
er audience of web developers.
≫ CHRIS: Yeah, that would be
wonderful. I think the toughest
thing with Web Components in
general is
really just if you're used to
thinking about things in a
React-y way, wrapping
your brain around the whole
this is
more...  React components are
everything in one place and Web
Components are separation of
concerns and each thing does
what it does best .
And it's a mental shift.
So, yeah, I would like to see
more of that.
I think one of the -- we're
starting to see more big
companies use Web Components,
maybe bigger open source
projects around it, I'm hoping
the tide is starting to shift.
And you have projects like
Enhance that use Web
Components as the foundation
for an entire static site
generator. That's pretty cool,
too.
≫ MIKE: Well, appreciate
everything you're doing to
evangelize
Web Components, that was an
incredible introduction to Web
Components.
≫ CHRIS: Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: Thank you. We're going
to move straight on to our next
speaker. Ivan
Zhao.
Interested in nonlinear
narratives, forms, and
mechanics
that reckon with digital -- I
don't even know how to say
that (inaudible) and queer
identity, as
work interrogates individual
and viewer agency. Research
involves around interests tools
and play when he's not
making weird things on the
internet, he's making weird
bread in the kitchen. Love
that.
So today, Ivan east going to be
talking about Chinese type
systems.
[ Applause ]
Ivan, welcome.
≫ IVAN: Yeah, thanks so much
for that intro.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, came to hear more
about Chinese type systems.
≫ IVAN: Yeah, super excited.
I'm Ivan. This will probably
lean on the more like
history/theory
of the talks today, but super
excited to chat about this.
So my kind of fascination and
love for Chinese type recently
came about when I was traveling
in Taiwan.
And if you're a fan of this
creature, there's
a 7-eleven in Taiwan that sells
it.
I was enamored by this juxta
position of the Chinese type
VER
because it reflects the
personality. And I've been
fascinated in thinking how do
we balance these kind of
systems together today?
And so, yeah, a little bit
about me, I'm Ivan, I make
websites, animations, comics,
but I'm
fascinated in this whole world
of how do we make weird things
on the internet ? And how do we
communicate and create tools
and infrastructure to do so?
If you've ever taken a history
of graphic design or anyone
's talked to you about type
design, there's a very a famous
book in the mid 15th Century
called the
Gutenberg bible that everyone
likes to look and pontificate
upon. Look at the scripture,
think about the black
lettering. I'm here to tell you
that, you should completely get
rid of
the Gutenberg bible, and in the
famous book Patricia Lockwood's
nobody's talking about Chinese
writing system. The history of
printing ascends back into 11th
century China with this worker,
commoner
named Bichon Hu who created one
of the first examples of print
making .
So in Chinese history, there
are four notable kind of
inventions and print making is
one of them made in the 11th
century. This is an old bank
statement.
Made at the time using one
immovable type . And one of the
things interesting about this,
if you look at kind of the
entirety of the Chinese history
and sort
of Chinese writing system, it
compared d, is pictograph
ictal,.
But here you can see the top
that all of these sort of
representations started as the
original image.
You can kind of see on the
left-hand side, there's this
progression of what a horse
looks like starts very much the
image of the horse and we get
down to the simplified script,
that's what's being used today.
What's super fascinating about
this, as well, is that
the -- when you look at it, the
current standard for Chinese
language in China 2300
is used in 5% of websites.
But during the time when this
was happening, the
simplification, one of the
things about the Chinese
languages, there's an old
traditional script, which
you see is like the standard
script versus the simplified
and that happened during the
1950s where the CCP and
Communist Party wanted to
improve the literacy rates of
the Chinese people.
The literacy rates were super
abysmal.
I think more than 90% of people
at the time were unable to read
. It's really complicated.
If you've ever tried to learn
east Asian
language/character-based
language, there's so many
things to learn. How do we make
this easier? How do we
incorporate this into a
modernized world? How do we
think about this?
And so, coming here, this is an
example of what an immovable
type kind of emphasizing if
you've ever worked with print
making or letter
press, you would know that you
have in Latin script, you have
GLIFs
you have gl
yphs, you have to have all of
the individual characters.
This is an example of how much
stuff you would need which is
really terrifying. Even in the
modernization of it, it's
like, what would this even look
like? So this was just like a
speculative sketch of a
typewriter.
And so, it's like, you have all
of these characters mapped out
on to it.
The average Chinese dictionary
has 60,000 to 80,000 words.
A body font for a Chinese font
would require
you to have about 8,000 words,
but that doesn't take into
case differences in simplified
and traditional. There's a lot
you have to deal with and a lot
of history associated with
this.
There's also a lot of political
structures,
one thing, specifically, is
that in this example, the
Chinese language is comprised
of individual radicals.
So radicals and also characters
composed of traditional and
simplified.
And so, here, this radical
means speech.
So one of the things in the
basis for the Chinese language,
it's composed of
the various radicals that add
up to sort of give meaning to
the character. And you can kind
of see all of the characters
above have this speech rad KAG
and they all have words that
are -- meanings that are
related
to speech creation, word
creation, or sort of like
communication.
This is not like ubiquitously
true across the language, but
it is one thing really
interesting to consider when
you think about comprising and
creating the Chinese language
as a whole especially from a
type design perspective where
you want to sort of
componentize all of these
characters. But one thing
you'll also notice in this kind
of creation is that you can't
-- you have to make different
components for each specific
one.
For example, even in the
character on the right for
talking fast,
ha, there's two of these sort
of smaller radicals on the
bottom and one on the top.
And within the components have
to make different
subcomponents. And so, I think
this is a really interesting
and theoretical approach when
you consider to like how you
make UI abstractions or the
ways components exist in the
UI.
Is there a way this can exist
for font software and making it
easier for Chinese ?
This is aS Ais an example of
the traditional versus
simplified dichotomy looks to.
One of the main things to
consider in traditional versus
simplified,
there's political ramifications
around two where traditional is
more present in places like
Taiwan and Hong Kong and other
locations while simplified is
in the mainland. That's for
another conversation, but
something to keep in mind if
you ever have to do
localization .
Just to dig into what
specifically where you're
thinking about creating those
languages for.
And so, now a little bit into
classifications of Chinese
writing systems. So the way
that we have type systems kind
of as
like san
serif and italicized and all of
that stuff, Chinese also has
this in the font,
as well, this is called sunti,
which is based off historical
precedence in
the Song dynasty after the name
sonti.
It alludes to this more call
calligraphy nature. There are
large flat stones, flourish at
the end that is indicative of
old style.
This is what we would consider
kind of a serif in the Chinese
world. Next up, we have this
thing called hati which
translates to black lettering
or black body, and so,
this more represents kind of
the
san serif world and this rose
to prominence, mainly in the
late 2000s as a result of
increased digitalization where
it was like, how
do we make these characters
like easier to read online?
We also have this thing called
k iti, less engrained in
older historical periods, be
but some of the same
flourishes. And the fourth one,
a mix of this kind of old
songti. You can see here as the
one in the past, we have these
little flourishes
and like more sort of softer
notes.
And so, this kind of gives more
of a different writing style/ I
think in terms of the bamboo
pendant you would potentially
be using.
And one of these things, also,
is kind of
a classification, which is
translates to kind of artistic
display or artistic font. And
typically, it describes this
world of display fonts
, and like display lettering
that's super fun, very bouncy,
sort of like hard to define.
And I think I'm personally like
really interested in
this because it's like all of
those things can be done really
well, but where are the things
with a lot of personality and
depth to them?
And so, how do you use this?
Default set for English
language contains 230 gyphs.
In Chinese, you have to make a
lot of gyphs.
What happens with this, the
size of your font file becomes
really, really large and
becomes really kind of almost
terrible to use.
And the fact that in China,
there's different character
encoding
methods that are primarily
used, as well. But luckily,
thanks to the
unicode consortium, you can
ignore that and use
the unicode UTF-8, which will
always work for you given the
sort of
as long as your font file is
dwell defined within the font
file specifications. P
And you can always use that,
UTF primarily supports all of
the Chinese characters that
exist out in the world. But
luckily, when you use this, you
can actually just define the
font family inside your CSS
like this.
One thing to consider, you want
to put the Romanization and the
Chinese characters' names.
Just in case you don't know
which one it's going to map to.
You want to put it as a
fallback and also always define
your Latin language CSS font
family first.
There's some interesting stuff
being done in the
Taiwanese world. This is a site
which translates to, there
exists a font library. We have
a font library, which I think
is really funny.
And they have this kind of
experimental API that allows
you to fetch for a web P file
that provides
all of these gy
lyphs for you and checks which
are needed and will only
send you the corresponding
glyphs, thus decreasing the
size of it, as well.
This is sort of a reference for
if you ever want free fonts,
free Chinese fonts, because
they're really hard to get to
and really hard to find and
make, this is a great GitHub
for it call Words Hub free
font.
And one of the things I've also
noticed, when you look at these
fonts, all of them in the
beginning have the denotation
of what foundry made them. This
is Fongjun, kind of like
founder is the name of it.
These are foundries of the
various different types of
files. There's the san serifs
and the calligraphy
. You can use this writing mode
that allows
you to write right to left,
. You also have this great
thing called font variant East
Asian. Which is specifically
for East Asian languages and
scripts. You can move between
normal and traditional.
And then, one of the other
things to obviously mention as
a side note, is that no sans,
which is a project by Google
and Adobe exist to kind of
provide language scripts across
the world. And so how do we
feel about, we feel
that it BLOJ belongs in the
trash and look for other
things.
Really quickly, just some
examples of kind of like fonts
and use of what can you
actually do this? Or how do you
pair it with Latin scripts?
This is a comparison of what
hati and songti look together.
There was a project doing the
Chinese rebranding of the "New
York Times" and he uses this
beautiful black letter kind of
alluding to the same
"New York Times" motif and uses
the same stem/notion for this,
as well.
One of the funniest things if
you've been following along in
the three body problem
discourse, is the type
serif used in the banner for
the communist party. Everyone
in China was pissed because
it needed to be a heavier
weight. And you can see in the
bottom corner what it should
look like
. And you can also argue about
the issues in the three body
problem.
Here's a really great example
from the Taiwan design expo. I
love the sort of
constrained/put together
use of the Latin type that has
these weird
end traps/contrast together
with the more traditional
notions of the characters.
Here's a piece, who did the
Chinese brand identity
for Alice in Wonderland, and
you can see them piecing
together with the original
characters.
Here's another poster by a
graphic
designer who takes the original
character and uses the lines
and glyphs as individual
shapes.
Just a couple more examples.
One thing I wanted to mention
in the sort of vein of fun
Indie programming, you can make
your own Chinese esoteric
language.
This is written in the script
of sort of old Chinese
languages and programs and
compiles to both JavaScript,
Ruby . You can write programs
in Chinese if you wanted to.
And the great about it.
Since it's defined on the grid
structure, you can always --
they're all monospace by
default. So that whole problem
is solved for you.
Lastly, I wanted to sort of end
with this talk
. This is a characters that
means to add oil.
But encourage everyone sort of
to, you know, if there's
any interest, dig into these
things, look at Chinese
characters, think about
different scripts in the world
and how you can use them to
benefit your
own designs and your own sites.
So thank you.
≫ MIKE: That was really cool.
Just a whole world you brought
us into.
Yeah, it's fascinating thinking
about that
difference between the number
of characters and Latin versus
Chinese
and the
necessity to strip it out of
the font sizes. It really is
like a performance difference,
pretty major performance
difference that you need the
extra level of optimization on.
What sort of tooling do you use
to do that?
≫ IVAN: Yeah, so there's a lot
of kind of like one things I
mentioned, there's some
experimental stuff.
There's two font foundries, one
of them called just font, which
is based in Taiwan. And the
other one is also based in
Taiwan.
You'll find the interesting
type foundries are based not in
mainland China because of
various political reasons.
But they're providing like
experimental APIs that allow
you to do that . But honestly,
if you're doing it on kind of
like a one -off site or
project, you can just download
an OTF or raw file and use it
regularly as a font file.
≫ MIKE: Got it. Ivan, thanks
again for joining. That was
fantastic.
≫ IVAN: Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: We're going to roll
into our final speaker for 11ty
Conf. Lucky last and lucky
number 11, too.
We've got Sara Joy joining us.
Sara's been online since 1998,
making
her personal websites since
1999. In 2021, Sara switched
her career from
electronic engineering to web
development. She loves the web
platform and wants
it to be accessible to
everyone.
Today, she's going to be
talking about light mode versus
dark mode.
[ Applause ]
Welcome.
≫ SARA: Hi, I'm really enjoying
that.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, let's try to
simulate some real life
audience. Sara, I've BP been
doing
a lot of light mode/dark mode
recently. I'm interested to
hear this talk.
≫ SARA: You might already know
it. But yeah, I will roll
straight in.
Light mode versus dark mode, I
have changed the title to
Why Not Both? Or why building
both dark and light schemes
together is easy, actually.
I hope I'm not overselling
that. Hi, I'm Sara. I have am
both an old hand,
like Mike said, I've been
building websites as a teenager
since 1999, only my own stuff.
It was only ever really a hobby
thing.
I had a long hiatus. And now
I'm a newbie, again, I
switched my career from doing
general electronic and other
stuff in small companies and a
couple of big companies.
And I jumped into web
development,
not last year, two years ago
now. I still feel like a
newbie. I guess I'm not, but I
feel like one.
Just a little warning that
there's already been some
movement, there'll be some more
movement, a tiny bit of
animation and abrupt changes
between dark and light modes in
this presentation. Because it's
difficult not to.
If you suffer from migraines,
epilepsy, strong
astigmiatism,
I'm really sorry, but I hope
with this information I'm about
to present to you, browsing the
web will get more comfortable
for you and everyone else.
So with that aside, I'll try
and warn whenever I'm about to
flash the screen from dark to
light. Let's get started. Dark
mode versus light mode.
And we all love a good
polarizing argument. And what
could be more polarizing in
dark versus light? But there
are physical reasons to prefer
one over the other.
And just allowed to prefer dark
or light mode. That's OK.
You don't have to have a
logical reason for it because
your eye is your choice.
So that said, why dark mode?
Your pupils constrict when they
come across a bright page or
bright anything. I think you
can quite often notice.
You feel the muscles pulling
your pupil, pulling your iris
inwards to make your pupils
smaller.
And if you're in a dark
surroundings, like I am right
now, yeah, it's quarter past
10:00 here. If you suddenly
jump into a bright website,
that's uncomfortable.
And then, other people have
floaters that appear or block
their vision.
A lot of you may, I mean, I'm
40 now, so sometimes, when I'm
looking up at a bright sky, I
see these things.
The second example on the right
is a bit more
what I see, sort of translucent
something or other drifting
across.
That some people with really
severe floaters might struggle
to read, text on a light
background
because the light background
just sort of is distorted
through the floaters.
Why light mode?
Pupils constrict when coming
across a bright page . But that
can be a good thing, actually,
because it's easier to
focus when your pupil is
smaller.
Like with a camera (inaudible)
you might close your aperture
in order to get a whole
landscape in focus.
Whereas if the aperture is
large, you have to very
carefully focus on separate
items. You have your foreground
and background and they're
different and you have to
focus and it's the same with
your eyes, they have to work to
focus more when your pupil is
large because everything's
darker.
And then, people have
astigmiatism
STIG
stigmatism. Light text on dark
backgrounds can become hard to
read.
They might be clear like they
are now, but with a little bit
of extra fuzz and your brain
and eyes work together to
try to sharpen out that fuzz to
try to focus better.
But when you can't, get away
from that.
When you can't get...  when you
start to get headaches.
Interestingly, I found a lot
more examples about this and
people struggling with dark
mode, because clearly there's a
lot of people annoyed about
websites only available in dark
mode.
So there's really loads of
examples people have made
of slightly fuzzed out or
distorted text, light text on a
dark background. And even, I'm
looking at these, and you know,
I'm trying to focus them.
I can feel my eyes and my brain
trying to focus these bits of
text and I can't, of course.
And if you're staring at this
all the time, it's going to
hurt.
And I love this one, I am the
douche
bag that makes people read
white text on a black
background.
So that would be why you might
prefer light mode.
Why not both?
Both. Both. Both is good.
I'm sure everyone gets that
reference.
[ Laughter ]
Anyway. So in this talk scope,
is just having
your site react to preferred
color scheme.
So I'm not going to talk about
manual toggling. It can be
done. I will show you it.
Shortly because with a bit hof
of JavaScript, it's easy and
you can find advice on the
internet including
me trying to give advice on it.
I've got a little toggle here.
Be warned, it's going to go
white.
And back, again.
I'm back to auto. So the
toggling is absolutely
possible.
But I'm not going to go into
how to do that in this talk.
And I must remember to click
right. So this is what I get
for rolling my own
presentation.
So starting from scratch. If
you have no styles, this is no
problem.
However, if you have already
really big
mature site or design system or
massive project , this may be
tricky to bring into your
projects.
If everything already has
specific colors , branding,
everything's set, it's going to
be hard to put this back in.
It's possible. I'm sure it's
possible.
But it's going to be difficult.
But I want you to keep this
light mode/ dark mode bothness
in mind next time you have --
you start a new project.
So we know this, we all have
seen default HTML themes, not
that we look at it anymore
because you probably set your
CSS reset before you even look
at the page.
I often set everything to just
san serif at least before I
start anything.
It's standard HTML here.
There's nothing unusual.
But you may not know that
there's also default dark
theme.
And everything's done for you,
the buttons, the inputs, the
link.
Link colors here have all been
adjusted already to look better
in dark mode. You don't have to
do it.
The browser's done it for you.
How do we get to that? You
don't even need CSS.
And Mayank did hint to this
earlier that you can put a
metatag in your HTML.
The meta  name is color-scheme.
And the content is light/dark.
You can put dark/light.
It might make a difference if a
user's OS isn't broadcasting
I'm in
light mode or I'm in dark mode.
I'm not sure many of them do
that now.
I think almost all of them are
in light mode or dark mode,
there might be some that don't
care.
If there's some that don't
care, if you put dark/light, it
may be that your website shows
in dark mode first.
As a preference. I haven't been
able to test it.
You can also put it in your
CSS.
So, under the root or HTML
selector, you have color
-scheme, color light/dark.
This website can show up in
light or dark, no problem.
And then, the browser will
follow the operating system's
preference and show you your
preferred version of this
website.
So just as an example, in
CodePen, tech
nically, it has a separate
place for the he, head.
You're not supposed to put the
head here within the HTML, but
you can do it and it seems to
work. This is what I'm using as
a display.
And because my laptop, my
Windows is
in dark mode because I prefer
the dark mode, it's going to
dark.
I could just -- drop dark, go
back to light.
In fact, I can put some sort of
gibberish
in there and it'll still be
light because light remains the
default default.
Or I can say all of this is
going to be dark.
And just to prove this is the
case, I'll pop open dev tools
here.
We've got color scheme
light/dark, prefers from dev
tools. Oh, everything is light.
I'll put it back to automatic,
which is what my laptop wants
to be. For some reason, this
gets home in a very
strange position, I suspect
it's this head getting annoyed
with real head, I'm not sure
entirely what's going on there.
We also have system colors and
the most reliable of these is
canvas text.
And canvas. And they're kind of
what you expect them to be.
Don't confuse them with canvas,
the element canvas.
Con vas text is the color of
the text. Canvas is the color
of your background.
Here, you can see I've just
done
a div with what you've expected
and I've reversed them. And
just reversed in here.
If I call this dark, it's dark.
I'll put it back to light.
Or I can do light/dark and
it'll turn dark, again,
because my laptop is in dark
mode. So you can apply color
scheme to elements, but you do
need to put the canvas text and
the canvas in there first.
If I just remove them
here, it doesn't quite work
because your element is sort of
transparent by default.
You need to have given them a
color before you can put a
color on an element otherwise
it's got nothing to work on.
I found that by trial and
error.
There are other system colors
and I have a role, because
they're patchy and I wanted to
tell you it's patchy and it's a
bit sad.
I can get rid of dev tools now,
too, apologies.
Here, you'd expect that link
text, which is being applied to
this one should look like the
text of the actual link.
And visited text should look
like the color of the text of
an actual visited thing. And
active text should look like,
let's have a dash go to this
link.
It should look like that.
Unfortunately, it does not.
This is Edge I'm using, so
Chrome yum
Chromium. Who does do it well
is Firefox
. Beautiful, link text looks
like link text.
(Audio cutting out) visited
text.
So,
Firefox for that one. I believe
they're going to trickle
through, but I have not seen
any improvement in a couple of
years. Maybe we can push on
that. Contrast too high.
So you're there, you've got
your con
canvas and your canvas text and
you're thinking like, great,
but I don't just want to use
those.
Maybe contrast is a bit too
high. And like is written
there, those implementing
WCAG for accessibility may find
it unlikely that contrast could
be too high. But for some, for
example, migrainers, they do
have trouble with this.
It can kick off micro
migraines, especially on
websites where things are
moving and scrolling if the
contrast is too high, it can
start to kick things off.
But there's also preferred
contrast.
This is a bit tricky because
I'm not sure where you can set
preferred contrast in your
operating systems. But it's
there.
And I'm fairly sure prefers
color scheme came before all
OSs allowed you to
toggle dark or light.
So, hoping that prefers
contrast starts allowing OSs to
allow you to toggle contrast.
The simplest way to bring
contrast down across the board
is filter contrast.
So, for example, that's just an
extra thing I've added there .
I've added a filter,
prefers less. And filtering the
whole thing by half, which is
possibly a bit extreme.
But let's bring dev tools back
in.
And under rendering, under here
so with the -- I'm trying to
remember how I opened this
somewhere, you can
find this rendering
options. And there's all sorts
of different options, including
prefers color scheme.
But here is prefers contrast.
Nothing for custom, nothing for
more, but you can, you can
totally do something different
for prefers contrast more.
Or prefers contrast less. And
then, my media query is kicking
in. I have done a lot of CSS
nesting because it's fun, not
just because it's best
practice, yet.
I think it's great.
Let's bring down the contrast
change a tic.
And even for me, with normalish
eyesight apart from age-related
trouble,
it's already
for me, you might prefer lower
contrast. But might not want to
filter all the time.
We can start using other
colors, of course. I really
like color mix.
Because we can use canvas text
and canvas, we can use them as
mixes with other colors.
So they look good
both in dark mode and light
mode while only having to
declare them once. So, for
example, here, if you
knock out the percentage, which
you can, it just goes to 50/50.
40 looks good here, so I'll
stick 40 back in.
I'll switch it into light mode.
And the backgrounds also
lighten up because they're
mixed with canvas and the
text has darkened, which has
flipped along with my color
scheme .
Another way to do it is having
a bit of lower opacity.
So here, I've got magenta. It's
all red, zero green, all blue
plus O
opacity of 4, I'm going to flip
it, again .
Flip.
So that's one way.
We can, as we used to, use
prefers color scheme.
We're totally used to it, we
can do it.
However, if you're flipping
color scheme, just color scheme
light/dark with your JS like I
am here, it doesn't change.
Now, here I've set it so that
when it's prefers color scheme
light, top one should have a
background of a Teal color. And
this bottom one should have a
background of
a green with 25% opacity.
And they do not.
Because prefers color scheme is
only asking the OS, it's
not flipping with color scheme.
Again, we'll go to dev tools.
Just to prove that it does
work.
So color scheme light coming
on, again.
We're in a halfway house
because I've got dark mode
here. These all interact with
each other, and it's so
interesting.
So, light and back to dark.
And light, again, the purpley
colors are going to green
colors. And make it clear that
it's automatic. Light, dark.
So it's
prefers color scheme and the
color scheme property are a
little bit away from each other
once you start to introduce
toggling.
But -- what's coming is
light/dark and it's not quite
an all browsers.
It's coming in version 17. 5 of
Safari and there might be one
or
two straggler browsers after
that. But it's really nearly
with us.
And just to show the
difference, here we have a
whole media query. Here is
nested within the first
declaration.
So it's not too big, but still
is a whole media query
where it's just saying, when
it's
light, I want this color, when
it's dark, I want this color.
And the same here, when it's
light, I want this color, when
it's dark, I want this color.
And that will work with the OS
flipping to being
dark or light mode and also,
just with it's going to go
light now. With color scheme.
And back to light.
And back to dark. Soer, this is
really satisfying for me.
But this is happily working on
Microsoft
Edge and Chrome and I think
Fire
fox and just Safari left to go.
It's so close.
To summarize, once it lets me
go to the next slide.
In summary, have a go at using
color scheme light/dark or the
metatag. Either way, it really
doesn't matter.
If you use the metatag, it's
easier to flip with JavaScript.
Try using color mix when you're
adding colors
. Mixing it with canvas or
canvas text.
Have a go at supporting user
contrast preferences.
And look forward to light/dark
like I am. And then, just
encourage you to experiment.
Because it's just changing
these things
are quite easy things to
change. You need to experiment
to see what works with what and
how you can adjust things
and what looks good in dark and
light at the same time .
I find it immensely fun to play
with.
So I'm glad to share it with
you. And I hope you fine it fun
to play with.
The takeaway, is to offer
choice. Just with the dark
mode/light mode and the more
contrast/
less contrast you have four
different themes already
. And if you decide to do
something for, well, that would
be normal contrast, I suppose,
and less contrast,
if you decide to do something
extra for more contrast, then
you've got 6. Yeah.
I mean, and you've got 6 themes
all at once.
On my home page, I added a
border to everything
in canvas or canvas text
depending on whether it's dark
or light mode.
And it's brilliant. It shows
everything extremely contrasty.
That's it.
I hope you have some fun
playing with it.
There's -- I'll share these
slides. I obviously stand on
the shoulders of giants.
There's so many people whose
stuff I've read and digested.
And some people have digested
my previous stuff and come,
again, with better, written it
better than I did
. So please follow a few links
and thank you, I'm
really honored to have taken
part in the 11ty Conference
, huge thank to the crew, Mike,
David, and I can see here in
the studio,
captioner Diane, because that's
work, and thank you very much.
And hope to see you, any of
you, again. Thank you.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, Sara. Amazing.
Yeah. I learned a lot.
I've just been doing the --
I've been doing the basics of
light/dark mode.
It's just fascinating how far
you can take that.
I didn't know about light/dark,
a lot of those things .
≫ SARA: Oddly, I find this to
be more basic, just these
couple of properties have made
so much of it way easier, now
you've got a bigger play room
to jump into.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, and being able to
do it without any CSS at all,
I didn't realize that was
possible. Yeah.
≫ SARA: Right?
It was a surprise to me, too,
just like, oh, I didn't have to
style all that dark stuff
myself.
It already had it.
[ Laughter ]
≫ MIKE: Awesome. I've got to
play around with it.
Yeah, it's going to be a lot of
fun. Thanks, again, for
joining, Sara. It was awesome.
≫ SARA: Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: All right. That was our
last speaker.
And what a good one to finish
on. Yeah. I'm going to go away
and play around with that.
So, we're going to do a bit of
a wrap up. Let's get Zach on
the stream.
There he is. Right on time.
So, just a reminder, we're
doing the -- we're doing the
CloudCannon
giveaway for a free website
migration up to the value of
$5,000 plus some discounts on
our plans.
So you can head over to, where
is the banner ? Cloudcannon.
com/11tyConf. We're going to be
drawing that and emailing the
winners after the conference.
So, if you're going to enter
that, do it in the
next ten, twenty minutes. Yeah.
Get in there.
So, let's do a wrap up of the
conference . Man, what a day of
11ty.
Zach, you're muted.
≫ ZACH: No. Yeah, just saying
my brain is melted right now.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, what a day, what
a variety of talks, too.
Just an incredible
breadth of topics and people
and perspectives. Yeah, I
really enjoyed it.
I felt like every talk was
unique in a very special way.
Couple of talks made me
emotional.
Maybe I'm just like running low
on sleep, but yeah. It was
great.
≫ MIKE: I agree. It's
well-rounded, such interesting
topics.
So let's recap in reverse order
. So we've got Sara Joy, we
just heard from light mode
versus dark mode.
Yeah, as I said, a lot of that
I was not aware of that was
possible and aware it was so
easy
.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I think maybe
another talk today that touched
on the for free stuff that you
get from web browsers, and
I would love to see more of
that, to be honest. I think,
the web browsers itself need to
expose a user-facing preference
that folks can hit a button in
their browser to toggle these
things.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, and I think that
would be a great addition.
I feel like every site is serve
is implementing their own
widgets. And there's a way to
get a lot for free.
But yeah, it would be nice to
have that elevated
to the -- Chrome of the UI of
the browser.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, agreed.
Then working back, we had Ivan
Zhou
, Chinese Type Systems. That
was really interesting.
Like, I haven't had to deal
with Chinese characters, but it
just -- just yeah
. A lot of complexity.
Interesting kind of workflows
that introduced there.
I love the perspective on sans.
I feel like that font tried to
be everything to
everyone and we had a lot of
discussion about how that
approach
can fail to live up to the
expectations of all of the
different parties that are
involved there.
I mean that 4,000 character
typewriter
was, yeah. That was, yeah,
amazing. I loved it.
≫ MIKE: Then we've got Chris
Ferdinandi
, come to the light Web
Components. Again, just I feel
like that's such a good
introduction
for someone wanting to get into
Web Components
of how and why you would use
them.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I loved Chris's
mindset, I feel
like that's the number one
limiting factor to Web
Components right now, people
aren't thinking about them in
the right way, which is hard
when you have a tool that is
maybe so different but has just
completely different goals from
React as a library or Svelt as
a library, et cetera.
I mean, putting something in
the web platform is a huge deal
. And I think there's a ton of
benefit in using as much of
that as possible
.
≫ MIKE: 100%. It's going to be
an interesting one.
It's hard to know what the
timeline of if and when Web
Components get mass adoption.
But hopefully, we see it soon.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I think it's
going to be piecemeal until the
end. I mean, until forever.
It'll never be
a -- this one wins and this one
loses . Web Components will
keep incrementally adopting
things
that these component frameworks
are sort of
developing and they'll be sort
of ahead of the game . But
again, there's just an
incredible power in
using as much of the web
platform as you can and
I would love to see frameworks
adopt more of the web platform
in that way, too .
≫ MIKE: Big time.
And we've got David and
Liam in static API together at
last.
≫ ZACH: Site mounting is an
incredibly powerful feature and
I don't think it gets enough
credit. I mean, I've built a
couple of things with site
mounting.
And all of the demos for
CloudCannon have used site
mounting now.
And in one place, I can manage
all of the themes and styles in
my 11ty projects and when I
push a change
to that one upstream repo, it
updates all of my 6
or 7 demo projects I've made
and rebuilds them
automatically. I had to set up,
these are the relationships
that I want.
And it basically did everything
for me.
So, yeah. I love that feature.
I think it's amazing.
And I'm going to keep using it.
It's incredibly beneficial to
my -- to my development
velocity for sure.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, and I think Flatt
Flatlake is a tool, as well,
what you would assume a static
website is capable of.
And I think that's just, we
need more
innovation for static websites
and really pushing those
boundaries.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I do kind of
think that using a static API
is a very powerful thing
. Because a lot of APIs now are
being locked down and you have
to use a key and go through all
of this security whatever to
get it set up.
And I think if you have a
static API you could expose it
to the world to use and it can
make things
more open if you don't have to
spend the run time resources.
I'm a huge fan of static APIs.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, most static APIs
you can only do 100 requests.
But if it's essentially the
same as an HTML file except
it's a JSON file, like, you can
hit that --
≫ ZACH: Yeah, why is it
different than your website?
And it is kind of reminds
everyone of the Twitter
API changes that they sort of
locked down their
APIs to a lot of companies like
really suffered from that
because they were light on the
APIs.
And yeah, I think -- I'm not
necessarily saying
that Twitter could've done the
static API for all of their
things, but certainly, some of
them could have been.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, for sure.
Don't fear the cascade with
Mayank. And I thought I knew
the cascade, and now, I
realized
I'm a beginner. So much, yeah,
just completely new way, like
different approach to thinking
about specify
specificity and approaching the
cascade in general .
≫ ZACH: Yeah, Mayank has an
incredible talent for giving
you a very succinct example, a
little like a couple lines of
code and I'll -- there were a
couple
of times in the talk I was
like, oh, wait, what? I didn't
think of that or realize that
you could do that approach.
So even that double ID
selector,
I don't -- the not double ID
selector. I had never seen that
before.
I've written a lot of CSS, and
I try to stay up
-to-date on CSS things, that
was new to me. There were a
couple of different instances
where I absolutely learned
things. So yeah, that was
great, really enjoyed it.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, Adrianna Tan,
11ty sites for people who don't
think they're web developers.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I think we've had
a lot of overlap with this
topic in discussing this just
you and me in private.
How do we improve the developer
experience for just brand new
folks and nontechnical folks
and technical
folks
. And 11ty, we've thought about
that a lot in terms of the
developer experience of using
the console.
But I think there's still just
a ton more work to do.
Like we've talked about today,
Git can be a huge hurdle to
leap over and the command
line itself can be a huge
hurdle to leap over. And yeah.
I think that there's still some
more stuff to do for sure.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, building a town
that doesn't exist,
Dan Sinker .
≫ ZACH: Yeah, Dan was poetic
almost
. I think the end of that talk
was one where I was starting to
get in my feelings a little
bit. Sort of talking about how
it doesn't
need to be a good -- the code
doesn't need to be good to be a
good website.
And I think that is 100% true.
You need to figure out what you
want to say and then, post it
online.
And have it in your own space.
Have control of it.
I think there's just an
incredible power in that.
And I think the mainstream
method now is to sort of use
these social
media channels to elevate your
content and I think that's
great.
And Henry kind of talked about
that, as well.
We'll get to his talk, too.
≫ MIKE: Yeah,
Sia with you're probably doing
web performance wrong. Another
one where I thought a newer
topic and then going deep into
it. Yeah, I learned a lot from
that one.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I think that just
being aware of like time
to first byte is a huge step in
your web performance journey
. And there are different hosts
are better at this and some are
not as good.
And it isn't -- I think the
thing that's really
challenged me personally is
that it isn't necessarily
like, I think for a wider
audience and a global developer
community, it's -- static is
easiest, safest way to go.
But if you look at some hosting
metrics like is it fast yet?
There's like a -- a site that
looks at aggregate data of
folks visiting the web and
looking at
time to first byte aggregate
metrics. Shopify's one of the
top ones.
And I don't think they use a
ton
of static sites, but they have
a huge vested interest in
making money
online and getting as fast of
servers as possible and
I think for the rest of us,
static is probably a safer
default.
But, yeah, I think that's a
fascinating project.
≫ MIKE: Ultimately, for
performance, you want to get to
as close as static as possible,
and so, I
imagine Shopify's doing a lot
of caching
or -- yeah, things --
≫ ZACH: Yeah, we commerce,ith
e-commerce specifically, the
economics of the thing are a
little different. And they're
willing to put in a ton more
money into
server infrastructure because
they immediately see the
benefits of that money on the
frontend.
≫ MIKE: That's it.
≫ ZACH: Yep. Exactly.
≫ MIKE: And then, we had Henry
Desroches
, Indieweb cowboys and a place
online to call your own.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, I really enjoyed
Henry's talk. The slides were
incredible.
The design of the slides were
incredible. The speed at which
he conveys information, or they
convey information was
incredible
. Yeah, I didn't get to see the
live captioned version of that.
But I imagine that the
captioner -- was having a good
time trying to keep up with the
speed of thought that was
happening in that talk.
≫ MIKE: That is good --
≫ ZACH: Sorry, Diane.
≫ MIKE: This is a good time to
shout out Diane and White Coat.
≫ ZACH: For sure. They've been
amazing.
≫ MIKE: Those fingers have been
working hard typing everything
we've been saying today. So
thank you so much for that.
And bringing this content to a
wider audience.
≫ ZACH: Absolutely.
≫ MIKE: Then we've got Miriam
Suzanne
, hints and suggestions first
do no harm.
≫ ZACH: I did not get to watch
as much of this as I wanted
because I was sort of coming
down from the talk I gave. But
Miriam is always an amazing
speaker.
And yeah, I'm sorry, I didn't
see this one. As much as I
should have.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
This was one of my favorites
. It's just like interesting
hearing about. It's always
interesting hearing about the
history of the web.
Because there's so many things
that had to
go right to get the web that we
have today. Could easily have
been commercialized in the
beginning.
It could have easily be
constrained to particular
devices and things. Like the
fact that we have
open web with these -- this
open consortium that's setting
standards and the browsers
all kind of work together to
implement those standards and
agree on them.
It's a miracle. And yeah, she
did a really good job of
telling that story and laying
out how to think about
CSS, where you're hinting at
the browser rather than telling
it what to do.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, that's great.
≫ MIKE: I missed one, Paul
Everett, 11ty and
large target pooling.
≫ ZACH: I thought Miriam's were
right after mine.
≫ MIKE: No, I missed one.
≫ ZACH: OK.
I thought you almost blew my
excuse out of the water.
Yeah, Paul's was great. I think
that, yeah, 11ty has sort of
been
doing a lot of work to satisfy
the sort of data schema use
case and trying to sort of
validate
data and your data cascade
. And give you good error
messaging and we'll have some
of that in the 3. 0 release, as
well.
And yeah, I mean, I think JSX
is such an interesting
technology to maybe put it
nicely.
There's so much, I feel like
there's a certain amount of, I
don't want to get too spicy,
but a certain amount
of human being
human being that went into it,
because you have to have all of
the tooling for basically
this decision
you don't want to use template
originals.
So yeah, the tooling complexity
tradeoff doesn't really make
sense today. It maybe made
sense in 2013 or 2012
when it first came out, but --
I don't want to get too
distracted here. But yeah, I do
think that there is
still a place for these things,
but I would kind of wish that
we could just move to use
standard space
template literals so we don't
have to add the tooling
complexity to the different
runtimes coming up:
Now we have node, we have Deno,
we have
Bun, and we have browser
JavaScript and two of those
support JSX.
And two of them don't.
So -- like, basically, locks
you into using a bundler for
that at that point.
But, yeah, I don't know.
There's some, I think, maybe
Paul's real essence of Paul's
talk is that he should, that
you can
do some of that without a
bundler in 11ty, which I think
is super powerful.
≫ MIKE: And then, the final and
first talk Mr.
Zach Leatherman, the future of
11ty. That was, that was
awesome just to see it
laid out what's coming in 3. 0
and what you've been working
on.
≫ ZACH: Yeah. And there's more
to come.
I think that there was sort of
a huge sprint to get a lot of
things done before the
conference, and
now there'll be another sprint
to get a
few more things snuck in before
we do the final 3. 0 beta.
So, yeah, I think there's --
definitely feels like an 11ty
renaissance happening right
now, which is super exciting.
Because I don't know if I felt
that 6 months ago.
And the conference has
different solidified it for
me that just the community is
amazing.
And it's really about just
bringing everybody together.
And yeah, I am very humbled by
today.
I think it's been a very, very
cool day.
≫ MIKE: It has. Yeah.
And it is the community that
makes this project so special.
So, let's do some thank you s.
Thank you to everyone for
showing up today.
Like, you're the reason that
this all happened and we put it
together . You've been awesome
in chat.
So supportive.
And just active and a lot --
it's been a lot of fun. Just --
≫ ZACH: Yeah.
≫ MIKE: Interacting with you
all today.
≫ ZACH: Yeah, amazing. Just
another shout out to Diane.
Maybe the hardest working
person today. Doing those
captions all day.
I know that's a huge amount of
work. So, yeah. Shout out to
White Coat Captioning.
≫ MIKE: Shout out to
Liv and David and Liam and
everyone else
at CloudCannon who has been
involved with us, the
conference started, I think up
at 2:00 or 2:30am.
≫ ZACH: New Zealand time is
wild.
≫ MIKE: I think it's 9:00 am
there now, so busy behind the
scenes making this all happen,
thank you so much.
≫ ZACH: Yeah.
And I think, just, again, I'll
say this conference would not
have existed at all without
CloudCannon's support
. And yeah, I think in the
beginning, I was maybe
reluctant to do the conference .
And it was not my idea.
And, yeah, just seeing the way
it's come together and
the amount of support that
CloudCannon has given to the
conference and the project
cannot be understated.
So, yeah. I am just so
thankful.
≫ MIKE: Nice. All right, I
think we're done.
It's been, I'm seeing the live
stream where it's
6 hours, 16 minutes of 11ty
goodness content.
It's been a lot of fun. We're
going to do it, again. Thanks,
everyone. Thanks, Zach.
≫ ZACH: Yeah.
Thanks, y'all. See ya online.