I'm just kind of blown away
at what's happening right now.
I never would've thought I
would have -- I would be
attending a conference about
11ty .
It's just amazing to think
about.
We've sort of been around for 7
years now.
It's a long project, and we've
got more to come.
So as Mike said, I'm Zach. This
is my visual resume.
I started 11ty back in 2017.
And in some respects, it was to
facilitate my personal website
. And,
yeah, it was originally on
WordPress back in 2007. I
switched to Jekyll
around 2012, 2013, and yeah,
migrated to 11ty shortly after
launching. I do have some more
background in the JavaScript
world.
I ran a JavaScript meetup for
many years.
And we did a conference,
Nebraska JavaScript conference.
So yeah, sort of been in the
JavaScript ecosystem for a long
time. I think a lot of folks
might be aware of my work
with web fonts and web
performance.
And yeah, hopefully, we can
bring that to 11ty in the
future . And so, maybe
some folks are also familiar
with this meme from XKCD.
It's sort of this teetering
structure
. And the caption is a project
some random person in
Nebraska's been
maintaining and, yeah,
I think that in some respects
represents 11ty.
But I also think that 11ty's a
little bit more stable than
that little, tiny block may
represent. We've been around
for 7 years.
We've had so many, so many
releases.
And folks have really
identified with how stable it
is and how few breaking changes
that we
ship. Because I don't like
breaking changes myself.
I use 11ty for so many projects
and I don't want to have to go
back and update those either.
So, hopefully, you also feel
that. And there are kind of
many frameworks and tools and
site generation things that
exist on the web right now.
And there's kind of something
for everyone, right?
You can pick your flavor of
tool that you identify with
most, that you get the most
benefit out of.
That you get the most value
from. And I think that's a
great thing.
There are frameworks that maybe
represent someone that might
want to send a billionaire to
the moon.
Not for me, there's a framework
that might represent someone
that thinks this social network
is still cool.
Not necessarily for me.
A framework that maybe it wants
to live in a world in which
this is a normal thing. Not
necessarily for me.
And then, there are other
frameworks that really see the
value in Google Reader and
Indie web and having
information accessible for
everyone, and RSS and sharing
those things online and a root
in HTML and not necessarily
trying to funnel everything
through JavaScript first.
In my mind, there's kind of
this two dimensional graph
here.
And you can place all of
different tools in different
spaces on this graph.
On the left, you can see
dynamic servers
. This sort of moving away from
static site generation. On the
right, we have static sites
. Folder full of files, as I've
said.
And then, the top represents
HTML first, multi-page
applications that we've
seen the marketing pivot to and
then, on the bottom, we see
JavaScript first tools
. BUND
Bundler based tools, that
everything flows through
JavaScript code you write and a
lot of those are
application-based.
On the bottom left, we have the
most popular
site generation tool right now,
NextJS. It lives in that
JavaScript-first world. And you
can use Next. js in kind of
different ways.
They've added what they call
server side rendering mode,
which allows you
to serve HTML first in your DRK
-- and
code downloaded by sites that
you build. But it still has its
roots in single page
applications.
Next also has a static export,
which kind of goes more to the
right as a static site.
You can use Next to import a
static site.
Importantly, I've learned that
does not include Next image and
we'll go into that a little bit
later. I thought that was very
interesting that you can do
HTML, you can do JavaScript,
you
can do CSS, but you can't do
images. And that doesn't come
out of the box.
And 11ty wants to exist in this
top right quadrant, right. We
want to be HTML first.
We want to create websites that
are multipage applications,
above all, we want to be a
static site generation tool
. That's what our roots is.
That's what I really believe is
the place that 11ty does the
best work.
And, at the end of the day, I
think, static sites
really have this amazing
benefit of being the most
secure, the fastest to serve,
and they have a lot of these
very
great benefits that, yeah, I
think we are really doubling
down on right now
. Now, 11ty has kind of dipped
its toes into more dynamic use
cases.
We had an Edge plugin and
Serverless plugin.
But we're sort of regrounding
ourselves into the static
world.
And trying to be the best that
we can be. And so, there's all
of these
different site generation tools
that exist. And some of them
have sort of created
different modes of use. Most of
developing sites to where
they can serve more than one of
these
quadrants simultaneously, or at
least with the same or similar
codebases.
But importantly, 11ty really
wants to be the best that we
can in the top right.
We want to be the best static
site generation tool that we
can be.
And it's been so amazing to see
the response to 11ty over the
years.
We have over 72,000 open source
repositories on GitHub.
People that are using 11ty.
Over 16,000 GitHub stars ,
which is amazing. We have over
21,000 friends online across
all of our social media
accounts.
And we're now up to 8. 7
million downloads on NPM, which
I think is
incredible.
And a lot of sort of larger
enterprise customers have
started to use 11ty, too.
Some big names,
like CERN has a web site use ing
11ty, NASA,
their website is built with
11ty.
And it's, yeah, again, so
incredible to see.
To see the logo cloud that you
can find on 11ty. dev that has
all of these
. And I think one of the core
features of 11ty are
the secret sauce to 11ty is
that we don't have a moat by
design. A lot of times, when
you have frameworks
that have investors or some
monetization behind it, some
more aggressive monetization
behind it, they want you to
have a moat.
And a moat is something that
exists in this framework to
keep you using the framework.
Whether that be a --
a language format that only
runs in your tool and doesn't
run independent of your tool.
Or that be some more runtime on
request pieces , like image
optimization.
Maybe, the vendor that creates
the framework also sells you on
request image optimization. And
they charge you by the image.
And, again, we'll go into that
a little bit later.
And, the thing we've been
working
on for so long, I want to say
almost a year now is our next
major release, 11ty 3. 0.
It runs in Node 18 or newer.
And yeah, I'm super excited to
tell you all about it.
Just the number one thing, and
I'll maybe have a very
interesting number of points to
make in this talk. But the
number one thing is that it's
written in ESM. ESM is sort of
the more standard way to write
JavaScript that works in a
variety of different contexts
and runtimes.
So this is sort of a way for us
to prepare for the future.
To allow 11ty to run in a bunch
of different ways. And a bunch
of different tools.
And yeah, I think it's an
important thing. Although, the
subtleties of it may not be as
convince ing as we might want,
as
developers. Practically, it
just kind of means that you're
converting module
.exports in your code and
JavaScript code
to be export default or named
exports at the bottom.
You just can change it to
export.
So it's -- there isn't too much
change that happens when you're
migrating your code to ESM. But
I think it is important for the
future. And if you look at the
NPM ecosystem
right now, there's this graph
from Titus,
sort of maintain statistics on
how many projects are using
what mode. There's only 11. 7%
on NPM are using ESM first.
There are some people that are
dual publishing as the other
alternative in the thing that
most folks use is common JS .
So some folks are publishing
both
ESM and common JS
simultaneously. Not going to do
that.
And, some folks are using a
bundler to precompile their
common JS to ESM for usage.
And so, if you look at this
graph, you might be a little
worried that 11ty is using ESM,
right, because it doesn't
seem to be all that common in
packages that are published to
NPM.
And if you look the a some of
the existing frameworks out
there right now, you can see
11ty and Astro are kind of on
the left.
We're doing ESM first . Next,
Gatsby
, sort of use a bundle r
approach . And Next. js is
still using common JS. And so
there's sort of a wide variety
of things here.
So what does this mean for your
project?
You can still keep using your
existing configuration file.
project as is, you can still
keep using CommonJS with 11ty.
So you don't need to worry
about that.
So if you look inside of your
11ty configuration file right
now, you can keep using this.
It isn't a problem, you don't
have to migrate your code over
to use ESM, just because 11ty
is using ESM, doesn't mean that
you need to.
And yeah, just practically
speaking, you can import 11ty.
So one of the main problems
that people see when they're
using ESM and
CommonJS, you can't require an
ESM package.
So if you use any of the
bundled 11ty plugins that are
already included.
You will need to change your
configuration file to look
like this if you are going to
be using Node 18 . Now, Node is
actually adding support
for importing
, requiring ESM packages to
Node. It's an amazing thing.
It's come out in the last month
or two. And you can use this
today with NOED 22
with this command line flag
experimental requirement module
.
So if you want to not change
any of your code at all, you
can use this approach.
It really doesn't take much to
upgrade your project to use
11ty 3. 0.
Here's my personal website
. It is, I think, three files
were changed. I changed my node
minimum.
I changed the import to be a
dynamic import inside of my
configuration file.
And then, my package JSON, I
pointed to the new version. And
again, your existing
CommonJS code should work
pretty much as is.
Especially, if you're not using
the bundled plugins.
So you can use ESM if you want
to convert your
configuration file to ESM, you
can do that, and this is what
the new syntax will look like,
export default.
And, this might be the most
straightforward way to do it
because
there isn't any special dynamic
import that you need to do, you
just import your plugins
directly from the 11ty package.
And yeah, this is great. This
is maybe the most
straightforward way to do it.
But importantly, you can
incrementally migrate to ESM,
too . You don't have to -- it's
not an all or nothing thing
. On the left side, we see your
existing project might be using
CommonJS
. You can use ESM with a . an
extension.
If you want to start with ESM
first, you can add type module
to the package JSON, and then
use, then the default .
js will be interpreted as ESM
and you can use .
CJS to fall back to the common
JS format in Node.
So you can really sort of use
either of these approaches .
And it really, I think, gives
you an incredible amount
of flexibility when you're
dealing either with legacy
projects or new projects from
scratch.
So one of the things I'm most
excited to tell you all about
today is the new features that
we're shipping that we've
already shipped to 11ty image.
And I think this is just super
exciting . I'm very excited
about it.
We have this new image
transform plugin.
So with just a couple of lines
like config,
we'll automatically transform
your HTML and do image
optimization and image
processing for you.
And it's all sort of handled
for you out of the box.
Which I think is incredible.
And I'm using it everywhere.
So this means, no more worrying
about short codes, no image
short codes, no worrying about
asynchronous context versus
synchronous context.
A lot of people that used
handlebars, that's
a synchronous language, it
couldn't do asynchronous short
codes. We had this complex way
to do it. We don't need to
worry about that anymore. Use
the transform method and it
handles with all of your
templating languages .
So you never have to manually
add a width or height attribute
to an image, again, not even
for mode images.
This is a super unique feature
that isn't available in a lot
of alternative frameworks. A
lot of them require you to do
static imports or for
remote images, you have to add
your width and height manually.
Not at 11ty images, we do it
all for you, you don't
have to worry about it.
And the super really cool,
exciting thing that we shipped
just very recently is this new
transform On
Request feature. This is given
to you, it's automatically
enabled for you.
When you use 11ty in serve
mode,
we have a dynamic on request
piece that will transform your
images for you when they're
requested in the
browser, not as part of the
build.
So when you do dash dash serve,
we only optimize images that
are visited in the web browser.
And then, on the right, we have
the same when
you run a normal 11ty build,
not in server or local
development mode, when you run
a normal 11ty build,
you get this full standard
build output that you'd expect.
So the right side is sort of
the way it work ed before, the
left side is new for Serve
mode.
And you can set your own widths
here, if you want to do is that
that. And we sort of handle all
of that for you, right ?
It works the same. If you want
to set specific widths
for an individual image, you
can do that with the 11ty
: Widths attribute .
And you don't have to worry
about image versus picture,
either. We automatically swap
that for you based on how many
formats you're using, how many
sizes you're using, you don't
have to worry about that.
So as an example, if you only
want to output a
web P by default, 11ty does
JPEG.
But if you want one format, you
get the image tag, if you want
multiple, we switch to the
picture tag.
And what this gives us is near
zero build cost for local
development , which I am super
excited about.
Here's what it looks like. If
you have a thousand images
running through the 11ty
image pipeline right now, it
would take about 6 seconds to
build on my personal machine.
These are just benchmarks. I
ran on my machine.
And then in serve mode, it
takes less than a second to
start this the server.
Even with 1,000 images going
through that image optimization
pipeline. Which I think is
incredible.
We have another great feature
called sv
gShort Circuit.
A great new feature where it'll
actually compare the size of
that svg
versus the counterparts, the
web P, your JPEG or whatever.
And will throw out the ones
that are bigger than the svg.
So we do a file size comparison
and say, hey, is this svg? So
we have this complex Mexico
flag here.
Is the version of that flag
smaller in a vector format? We
prefer one over the other.
You can upload as many, or you
can get a small svg, and we'll
keep that for you.
So here's the classic tiger,
only about 20
kilobyte, we keep just the svg
in an image tank for you, which
I think is great.
We have some cool configuration
options coming in 11ty 3.
0, asynchronous work in your
callback function, which I
think is great.
We have this new config export
that you can do. So a lot of
times folks will
return an object inside of
their configuration callback.
And now, you can export that
and save your configuration
file.
And that is just an easier way
to organize your code and
allows us to access that a
little bit earlier and keep it
consistent in your config.
We have new set import
directories, set
output directory methods. We
have, also, those for includes
and layouts and
every directory you might want
to set, we have a method for
that.
We have a new virtual templates
feature, which allows you in
configuration
to create a virtualized
template. And this is a super
exciting feature.
Now, it allows you to create,
and will allow plugins to
create content in your 11ty
sites,
as well, which I think is
great. There was sort of an
example of how to block all of
the
AI spiders that come to your
site, and now, we can have a
plugin that does
that for you and generates your
robot txd for you.
I think that will be great for
the RSS plugin, as well.
There's a bundler, plain
text bundler, and you can add
plain text to
that bundle and we'll create
page-specific bundles for that
code.
To add a page to CSS bundle.
And web CSS is using this, but
it's coming to Core, as well.
This is how you output those
bundles.
Yeah, gets all of the CSS
that's added to that bundle for
the page, and then, you can add
it to a style block.
Or you can create your own
bundle file, if you want to
bundle that into an external
file, as well.
We have a great new plugin that
allows you to link to input
files . So files on your file
system, which I think is
amazing
. You can link to your markdown
file and it'll translate that
to the URL for you, allows your
project to be a little bit
more stable and less brittle
with your URLs as you change
them.
We have great new things coming
to data. We have sort of Node
front matter syntax.
Importantly, you can do
JavaScript data using the 11ty.
js template syntax type.
But now, you can do this in any
template syntax language.
You can use arbitrary
JavaScript. Which I think is
super powerful.
I first noticed this in the
Astro project, and I really
like it. So now, we have it.
You can also get act says to
the raw input of a
access to the raw input of your
file.
11ty works in Deno, which I
think is really great . Here's
an example of that.
And because it works in
Deno, now have actcess to JSX.
And here's an example of adding
a custom template
syntax that uses the render to
string
API to render JSX in your 11ty
project .
Bundlers. 11ty is still bundler
compatible, but we're also
bundler decoupled. We don't,
sort of, buy into
first party bundler at 11ty's
core. And I think that's
important to keep 11ty
independent moving forward.
But you can use bundlers in
11ty,
if you go out to our docs right
now, there's a great section on
using custom templates to do
that.
And just some stats on the 11ty
3. 0 version.
Again, dropped our node
dependency on additional 13.
3 megabyte, at about 22
megabyte for node modules right
now, which I think is great.
And this is far smaller than a
lot of the alternatives out
there right now. We've reduced
our dependencies to 176
, and I think that's not
necessarily the
most important metric, but I
think it is a great way to have
stability on the project.
We are pretty fast to install,
as well.
So just some benchmarks, it's
about 4. 3 seconds to install
11ty 3. 0.
And almost a minute to install
Gatsby, which
adds up, for sure.
I did run -- update the
performance benchmark. So we
had some interesting numbers
there.
How long's it take each one of
these tools to generate 4 ,000
markdown files? 11ty, less than
2 seconds, Hugo less than 1
second.
So 11ty is about, I want to
say, two times Hugo. But you
get a lot for it, right?
You get a lot of extra access
to the JavaScript ecosystem.
A variety of template syntaxes,
as well
. And yeah, I think 11ty does
really stand out in terms of
our build performance.
But the number one thing, I
think, and
11ty is sort of known for and
has little, very little to do
with me. 11ty is known for our
community and people.
We have so many people that
have built things with 11ty on
our authors' page.
We have people that have braved
the leaderboards, which is
pretty incredible.
We have so many hundreds of
sites that are 400 on
lighthouse. We have so many
open collective supporters, and
I
really appreciate everyone that
has put money to 11ty. It's
such a vote of confidence.
We have our folks helpful on
discord, our community
moderators and people that have
answered questions
for folks that are coming in to
ask, I don't understand how
this works, please, help me.
Anyone that has answered a
question on Discord or social
media or anyone that has helped
anyone else
with -- helped someone else
with 11ty is such
an amazing, big help to the
project.
We have our 11ty meetup folks
that run the 11ty
Meetup, we have Bob that ran
the 11ty
Bundle site, which is sort of
an aggregate, ing a aggregation
of all of the 11ty resources,
which is such a huge task.
Thank you, Bob, that's so
amazing.
And just some amazing folks on
the issue tracker, as well,
Raphael and Peter just have
helped out for so much over the
years.
And then, we have the people
contributed on GitHub. So many,
so many people, thank you to
everyone that has
just even if you've just fixed
a typo on the docs , that's
hugely important.
And then, our conference
organizers, David, Olivia, and
Mike, just really appreciate
y'all.
Shout out to James, y'all
, maybe are aware of the 11ty
possum , this came from James.
It started as the cat on the
balloon. And it changed to the
possum.
And we've sort of iterating on
different mascots over the
years.
And yeah, that came from James.
And I do just want to recognize
CloudCannon because I think
they have played such a huge
role in the 11ty community.
Especially over the last year.
Without CloudCannon, this
conference would not exist.
That's very easy thing for me
to say.
And, yeah, without CloudCannon,
the 3.
0 release would not be shipping
on the timeline that we're
aiming for.
And importantly, with
CloudCannon, they're already
ready for the 3. 0 release.
We've put in the work at
CloudCannon to make CloudCannon
's configuration ESM
compatible, make it work with
our new async configs, and so,
that's ready to go .
From day one, which I think is
amazing.
And just from a personal level,
I really, really, really
appreciate d the folks at
CloudCannon. They're super
helpful. They're super nice.
They have been champions for
accessibility.
I think you've probably seen
some folks online talking about
how CloudCannon has really
iterating
on our accessibility and trying
to do some really great work in
that space.
And they've been super amazing
champions for static sites,
generally. You should go out to
the future of Jamstack. org and
look at the community that
we're building there.
I think that is a super
important thing.
To pick up the Jamstack
community and elevate it to
something new .
And so, just to wrap up,
there's -- it's just such an
interesting world right now.
We have nothing but algorithmic
timelines on social media, we
have for you pages just
shoveling content
at us, we have large
language models generating
content for us. I really think
that folks that are making and
hosting and having full control
of their own content on the web
is so powerful.
In a way, I think it's very
subversive, too.
So just ask yourself, what do
you want to build on the web
? What would you like to grow?
What would you like to see the
next generation of the web be?
And I think 11ty is
a great place to help you move
in that direction.
So let's get our hands dirty
and, I guess, keep building for
the web.
Thanks, everybody.