Thank you.
I'm excited to talk to y'all
today about why you're probably
doing web performance wrong.
I will admit it's a little bit
click baity, you're not
actually doing it wrong, but
maybe you're making your job
harder and getting frustrated
on the way.
Let me make sure my slides are
working.
All right. If I were to ask
y'all, what's the number one
tool you use for making your
site faster?
I would guess that 90% of you
are going to say lighthouse,
right? It's a great tool.
I credit it with giving
the web developer community
more -- or maybe making web
performance more visible to
everyone. Which was great, but
what you need to understand is
it's an algorithm and it's
limited and it might point you
in directions that aren't very
helpful sometimes.
And we're going to talk about
lighthouse, but also, the tools
that you're probably more used
to using.
What do I mean by that? This is
a real case I was looking at
the other day.
And this was its Lighthouse
report. On the website, they
had a score of 33, and you can
see,
there's more than 20 different
audits here that are flagged.
You're probably thinking oh, my
god if this was your site, and
the next thing, oh, do I have
to do all of these things to
make my site faster?
And what I want you to do is
take a step back and think,
what are the primary reasons
this website is so -- is it
really minimize main thread
work? Let's take a step back.
Again, my name is Sia,
Karamalegos, but I help make
merchant sites
FAESer onshop faster on
Shopify. I have a lot of 11ty
posts on there, although, I
haven't done enough lately
because I've been working more
on our Shopify, it's a
performance. Shopify. com site,
in case you're interested about
web performance at Shopify.
And yeah, all the things. Let's
keep going.
Let's talk about speed metrics.
In this presentation, I'm
talking mostly about speed
because that's what we usually
think about in performance, but
those other things are really
great, too.
But if this, I'm going to focus
on loading speed. Because the
idea is to give you information
about what you could do, which
is applicable to other ones, as
well.
So when we think about loading
speed, there's three important
metrics. The one that's user
important
to real users is contentful
paint
. That's when the largest item
on the screen or the viewport
is rendered, which gives the
user the idea, oh, this page
has loaded.
And the threshold for it is 2.
5 experience. And this one is
more, it's about
human perceptions of
performance, but also
achievability and things like
that.
But we also have a few other
load
ing metrics, time to first
byte, when the first byte comes
back from the server, user
doesn't know or care what that
is . They don't care. But it
helps us understand what might
be going on.
First contentful paint is the
clue something 's happening.
That's when the first item is
rendered. These are the
thresholds for good.
If you've ever used pay speed.
dev, and you have a site that's
popular enough to have publicly
available data in this data
set, you might see something
like this. You can see at the
top it says discover what your
real users are experiencing.
So this is real world data
or, we call it run data for
short.
It's telling me my largest
contentful paint is 4.
8 seconds. Largest of 4. 8
seconds or faster.
And so, you can see we have our
core web vitals on the top row,
and on the bottom row, the
extra metrics, plus one that's
about to be deprecated
or semideprecated.
But we can see this data.
This is how my real users were
experiencing that same website.
And this, again, is the Chrome
user experience support, if you
don't know much about that.
So at the top, I have our same
little kind of waterfall
diagram.
And at the bottom, we have our
example with the real user data
map to it.
You can see that time to first
byte, I've extended that row
out to 2. 4 seconds, that was
the number on the previous
slide. SEP is 3. 8. And LCP is
4. 8.
So what's the primary
bottleneck here?
There is no world in which you
can achieve a 2. 5-second LCP
with a 2. 4 second time to
first byte. It's just not
possible.
To do your entire first render
and your largest
contentful paint within . 1
seconds, it's not possible.
So if I were to, instead, so
the first two on this screen
are what you've already seen,
and on the bottom, what I've
done is
I've presented like I made my
time to first byte good and
then I've met FCP and LCP so
that you can see, you know,
what would they look like if
the time to first byte was
faster? Because these are
sequential. You can't render
the page until you get the
bytes from the server.
And you can't render the
largest thing until you've
rendered the page. And
sometimes, those can happen at
the same time. But, we can see
now that FCP is, it's still a
little bit slow, it's only .
4 seconds slower and LCP is
about . 7 seconds slower.
They still have a little bit of
issues. But that biggest
contributor was actually time
to first byte. So looking back
at our
lighthouse report, where would
we have found that out in here?
Well, what's really
interesting, which it took me a
while to figure this out
because I was looking for it, I
ran
it twice because I was trying
to explain, essentially, a
similar point to someone else,
and it didn't even pop up in
this lighthouse run. It
actually in
this specific experience, we
actually had a good time to
first byte. So it didn't even
trigger what is usually
happening in the real world.
Additionally, are remember,
that was probably our biggest
issue.
But because I know there's a
little bit of issue with FCP
and LCP, my guess is the other
two are these other two audits,
that's what I think they call
these things.
But the largest contentful
paint might have been
lazy loaded, that happens a lot
on Shopify sites. But this is
not a liquid Shopify site.
And then, render blocking
resources is a common reason
why first contentful paint is
slow. All right.
Let's take a step back and
learn about these two different
types of testing. So what you
see on here is what we've just
seen.
On the left is that top part of
PHP web.
dev which is your real user
data. And on the right, we have
our Lighthouse report that
you've probably seen a lot,
right?
It's this Lighthouse report,
you can see in the gray area,
you can see that it was run on
an emulate
Let's take a step back and
learn about these two different
types of testing. So what you
see on here is what we've just
seen. On the left is that top
part of PHP web.dev which is
your real user data. And on the
right, we have our Lighthouse
report that you've probably
seen a lot, right?
It's this Lighthouse report,
you can see in the gray area,
you can see that it was run on
an emulated motoG powered phone
using a slow 4G connection. And
it's just a single run. It's
only a single point of data.
Whereas on the left, it's
aggregated across the user
experiences.
On this page, you can see an
internal report we used at
Shopify that is real user data,
so we collect data with our own
script. And we can run it
across our site.
So I like showing this because
it shows, oh, now I'm going to
break it down by page and
device type. So I can see that,
you know, the collection page
has a big problem with CLS,
which is right down here.
But the desktop page has less
of an issue with CLS.
You can see the differences by
page and by device, oh, you
know what, it's directional
clues.
And on the right, is a network
diagram from dev tools, which
if you've ever run, that would
be considered lab testing, a
single run.
Left is aggregation, right is
the single run or lab test.
Again, on the left, this is
another way to see Chrome user
experience report data, it's a
cool site called Trio.
The site speed report uses crux
API.
And I like how you can see
monthly data in there.
It's aggregated data from
Chrome specifically. On the
right is your performance panel
dev tools, which is another
lab testing tool.
So there's two different types
of testing.
There's real user monitoring,
also called field of data.
And then there's lab testing,
which is sometimes called
synthetic testing. Neither one
of these is better than the
other. They just have their own
uses.
So you wouldn't use a hammer
when you need a screwdriver,
and the reverse. So what are
those differences?
Example tools, again, Chrome
user experience report is for
real user data. But you can
also collect this
data yourself, a package I use
for collecting myself is the
web vitals
NPM package, which is
maintained by the Chrome team.
There's also Boomerang, which
is a pulse product.
And there's also, if you wanted
like a paid service, there's
impulse but also speed curve,
which I really like.
Lab testing, the tools like
Lighthouse you're used to,
just the bottom section, the
one with Lighthouse in it, web
page test, you know, your
network diagram, your
performance tab in dev tools,
those are all lab testing.
So RUM is great for when you
want to see how real users are
experiencing a site.
And reveal those real world
bottlenecks that might be
hidden in a lab test. Like we
just saw. What was actually
hidden was there was a time to
first bite issue.
Lab testing, though, is great
for detailed data. And you can
more quickly debug and retest.
So their cons are kind of the
mirror of each other.
RUM, there's going to be
limited metrics. You only have
a handful of metrics and it's
hard to debug. You can't go
make a change and quickly see
if that probably fixed the
issue.
Instead, you actually have to
use lab testing for that.
But, of course, on, that side,
it can hide the real world data
and not representative of real
user experiences.
We're using servers to emulate
and experience or we're using
our own powerful desktops and
whatnot to measure.
So what are some of those
example observations? With RUM,
I can say, oh, LCP is slow on,
you know, the product page, or
CLS is bad on
the home page on desktop but
not mobile.
On lab testing, though, what I
can do is use those what I call
directional clues to
figure out if, oh, I can see
now that LCP is lazy loaded or
that 5 files are render
blocking, maybe I should
figure, you know, dig in deeper
on that or that sales banner is
shifting content down.
So when I debug, what I do is,
I use real user data and those
gaps between time to
first bite, first contentful
paint and largest contentful
paint to narrow down the most
likely issues.
Very similar content...
a very similar concept is LCP
subparts , and
Estella Frankel had a great
talk at a conference.
I usually have these specific
metrics at hand. So this is the
method I used.
But it's a very similar
concept. So what do I mean by
that
? When we have the three
metrics, if you have a problem
with one of them, it's usually
specific to that issue.
If I have a problem with time
to first byte, you might ask
yourself, why might my server
be responding slowly?
If instead, you have an issue
with first contentful paint,
you might want to ask what's
preventing the render? Do I
have a lot of render blocking
resources?
Am I using an antiflick r
snippet because I have AV
testing turned on or something
like that?
If your LCP is slow, you might
ask yourself, why is that
LCP element showing up faster?
Is it because the image was
lazy loaded?
Or if it's text, am I blocking
the font until the web font
comes in?
So there are different issues
depending on which part of your
speed is broken.
All right. So now that you know
that generally, let's take a
look the a
A at some examples. This is
actually an example of a great
hook performance. There's a
fast time to first byte, first
contentful paint and largest
contentful paint.
This is crux data from the trio
tool.
And this second example, we can
see that this is somewhat
similar to the one I've shown
you is that time to first
byte is 1. 7 seconds, that's
pretty slow.
And so, it's actually impacting
the other two, even though
there's only a gap of what .
6 seconds to first contentful
paint ? And . 4 seconds to
largest contentful paint.
While all of these are yellow,
it's time to first byte that
has the bottleneck here. I'd
look at server issues.
In this next example, this is
an easier one because
the first two were actually
green, we know it's just the
largest contentful paint . I'd
look at that element to look at
what's going on.
This next one, you can see that
FCP or LCP is only . 3 seconds
after FCP. So FCP or first
contentful paint is the primary
bottleneck.
Finally, a lot of cases aren't
going to be so cut and dry. So
this one, time to first byte is
good, but FCP and LCP could be
worked on. All right. So those
are some examples.
Because this is probably the
stuff you've seen less of and
in the past, you maybe seen
more of like just the
lighthouse stuff.
So I use that information, and
then, finally bring up my lab
tool to dig in deeper.
So once I have those
directional clues, I will dig
in deeper. So for Shopify
sites, Shopify uses liquid, but
of course, there's a lot more.
We have a server side, it's not
static generated.
We do use liquid, and I've had
an article about how to
optimize Shopify sites.
A the lot of these issues are
going to be similar to the
general web if you're not using
a frontend framework.
Although, the issues for time
to first byte being slow on a
static
site might be more, for
example, around your provider.
So like, if you're using GitHub
pages, I don't think that's on
a CDN, but if you use Netlify
, there's a CDN for that and
also cloud front pages.
Depending on your service, that
could impact your time to first
byte.
But the FCP and LCP, especially
for eCommerce
sites might be common reasons
why a site might be slow
compared to the Shopify sites.
So, of course, this is a whole
other talk and we only have 22
minutes. I'm not going to go
into the different lab tools.
But what I'm trying to tell you
is, DOENTS start
don't start with just
Lighthouse or your lab tool,
you might go down
the rabbit hole with minimizing
your main thread work, which is
still important and a
valid issue, and especially
considering, because I think
this site has INP issues, as
well.
But instead, I want you to
start with the real user data.
Get your directional clues.
And then, dive deeper with lab,
only on the specific issues
, essentially, try to get your
heavy hitters first.
Don't worry what those
microoptimizations first.
And then, in the end,
hopefully, you'll have more
time to focus on that hobby
that you've been neglecting.
So thanks, again, you can find
out more about me on Sia. codes.
All right.
That's all I have, Mike. I have
no idea how we're doing on
time.
[ Laughter ]
≫ MIKE: We've got a few
minutes.
≫ SIA: All right. Go ahead.
≫ MIKE: That was great.
I think just that context on
like, I'm definitely guilty of
doing Lighthouse and then, I
love a good to do list. OK.
This is my work. I'm going to
--
≫ SIA: And it's not bad, it's
just like a computer looking
for common flags . But it can't
necessarily tell you, like, the
primary reason why your site
might be slow. So --
≫ MIKE: That's it.
So my question is you kind of
mentioned this in your talk
that it'll change per use case,
but what are the most -- where
do you typically see the most
problems? And what are -- is
there like a common thread
in those performance problems?
≫ SIA: Oh, well, yeah, I think
it really depends on what
you're looking at, so like I
said because I work
at Shopify and most of our
sites are on our Shopify
liquid, essentially, your
standard, standard system.
We also have Hydrogen, which is
a headless tool
. But there's common thread. We
actually used crux DATD data
with http archive. It might be
hard with your personal sites
to get in there.
But you can also use free tools
like the
web vitals NPM package to
collect your own information.
But what we saw using that
information was that on Shopify
sites, this is not like the
rest of the web. Like, 80%.
We hit a peak of 80% of Shopify
liquid sites were lazy loading
their contentful paint image .
The rest of the web was around
20%. We knew that was a
Shopify-specific systemic issue
and it was because in our
liquid API, we didn't have
the ability for the way
Shopify's rendered, we can have
sections repeat, so
essentially,
if you had a template in
11ty...
what do we call it?
A it's not template for the
whole page, but something
you're reusing, but you don't
know where it is.
So you know you don't want to
lazy load above the fold, but
you the do -- I'm probably
going way too in-depth here.
≫ MIKE: No.
≫ SIA: I added into the API the
ability to know where your
section on the page so you can
be smarter about how you load
that thing.
≫ MIKE: Interesting. That's so
cool.
Like that work is going to
influence millions of sites.
And really shift the
performance of the web because
of that.
That's -- such important and
powerful work.
≫ SIA: It's definitely exciting
when you can find something
like that and fix it and get
everyone back on track.
≫ MIKE: Very cool.
If anyone has anymore questions
or
wants to talk about what
performance for Sia, reach out
to her on Mastodon.
≫ SIA: Yeah, if you go to sia.
codes, I'm on Blue Sky, but
that's mostly for shit posts
like Henry was talking about.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, Sia.
≫ SIA: Thank you.