So this talk is titled don't
fear the cascade.
And I want to talk about not
the dish soap, I want to talk
about CSS, specifically , CSS.
The cascade is probably the
reason why CSS gets such a
bad on developers.
That's why I'm giving this
talk. The cascade doesn't have
to be this unknown, scary
thing.
If you haven't been keeping up,
CSS has legitimately become
awesome.
We have the half serial class
and
nesting built into CSS now and
scope styling, how awesome is
that?
And for the first time ever, we
have the tools to manage the
cascade in a way that feels
more hinged for lack of a
better word.
Yeah, this is a
topic with multiple layers of
rabbit holes. To keep things
digestible, I'll simplify my
explanations and provide
practical suggestions along the
way.
So to understand the cascade,
we're going to start with a
completely blank
slate with minimum amount of
HTML required to file a page or
create a page, rather, not even
style it.
And let's put a humble button
element in there. And
immediately, we can see that
this button element still has
default styling, even though
there's not CSS on the page.
Earlier Miriam explained this
in more detail.
But these styles come from the
user style sheet.
And yes, these default styles
do respect the light and dark
team . So my system, operating
system uses dark theme, this
button is styled in a dark
theme . I won't spoil the
surprise, because
I'm sure Sara's going to talk
about this later today.
But yeah, you can have dark
theme without writing CSS .
Yeah, the user style sheet is
literally CSS style but built
into the browser, this is where
the cascade starts.
On this slide, I have a screen
shot of style sheet.
I went to their source code and
found it there.
It's like hundred lines long.
Specifically, I'm showing a
small subsection
where this affects input, text
areas, and buttons . And this
rule sets up font property,
this
font property is probably the
reason why every CSS reset
that you see is something like
inherit, buttons
just so these elements will
match their
font size and font family of
their surroundings .
So, yeah, this is the first
step in the cascade.
And then, come author styles.
This is the more interesting
part. This is where the party
happens.
Before that, I want to talk
about shadow DOM really quick.
Shadow DOM allows you to attach
an internal
, and it can have hidden from
the main DOM.
And that unlocks cool things
like encapsulate styling.
Even if you don't like using
Shadow DOM directly, which is
totally
understandable, it's still good
to know because many built-in
elements use Shadow DO,
M underneath.
And I attached this blog post
if you want to learn more. I
explain how Shadow DOM works
here and this animation showing
how the light DOM and Shadow
DOM are interlinked together.
I explained, cool. I have a
screen shot of the detailed
element, which is
built into HTML itself, also
uses Shadow DOM.
Even if you don't use it
directly, you are using it
indirectly.
And yeah, the reason I bring
this up is Shadow DOM styles
cascade after the user spells,
if you have ha
my button component which is a
regular button and
style both from inside and
outside Shadow DOM, the outside
styles will win.
So the overall cascade order,
so far, goes something
like user agent styles, author
styles, Shadow DOM styles and
the rest of the page styles.
There's also the inline style
attribute which comes after
these. But that's not part of
cascade.
The browser doesn't need to
resolve the cascade in order to
get the style attribute.
It's literally attached to the
element itself.
But yeah, now that
we understand Shadow DOM, we
can talk about the rest of the
page. The most simple concept
is order of appearance.
So for example, you can style a
button using
an element selector and you can
make it pretty straight
forward. But what happens when
there's two of the rules?
The last one wins, this makes
sense. CSS written, top to
bottom and the last one
overrides anything before it.
But these element selectors
aren't super useful on their
own. What if you only want to
style this one particular
button?
This is where I would use a
class instead of an element
selector . But when we do this,
we find that
the order of appearance seems
to not matter anymore.
The class selector wins over
the element selector even if it
comes before.
So what's going on here?
And thens a to that is
specificity.
Hopefully, I said that right.
Specificity. I'm not going to
go into too much detail here
because it's a complex, but
pretty easily understood topic.
Just Specificity is a score
made of three parts.
Starting from the right side,
elements and pseudo element
selectors contribute to the
least significant part,
classes, and attribute
selectors and pseudo classes go
in the middle and IDs go in the
most significant part.
So the browser will take the
score and use it to determine
which selector wins.
Chrome dev tools even shows you
the specificity when you hover
selector.
If I go and inspect this,
and I hover over selector, you
can see it says, 201, that's
the specificity score.
Yeah, you don't have to
calculate it by hand,
essentially.
So in the previous example,
specificity of the button
selector, the button class was
0 10, but the specificity of
the element was 001, so it's
more specific, it's by order of
appearance.
As you can imagine, with really
large selectors, the
specificity would become a bit
cumbersome
to manage and that's why the
general advice given to us is
keep specificity low.
And this is good advice.
We should almost certainly
avoid ID selectors, for
example. And we can still use
them.
We can still use them instead
of #ID, we can use a natural
selector
. Or we can make a class
specifically for the thing
you're selecting.
So it's easy to understand the
problem with high specificity,
but keeping specificity low can
sometimes be challenging,
especially when you want to
share styles between different
elements
, so you might, like, you might
be tempted to make
a single class or every bend of
the button.
But each shares the base cloud
of the button and that gets
complicated.
Sometimes, we tend to go too
far with this advice . Where we
want to keep specificity, not
just low, but
totally flat, by only using
single class selectors.
This usually is done through a
convention or tooling like CSS
Modules.
And yeah, I've always just
found this kind
of advice restrictive. It feels
like using CSS without the
cascade.
So, yeah, for the rest of the
presentation, I want to show
you how much better things can
be with modern CSS .
The two topics that I would
broadly cover are
controlling specificity and
controlling the cascade itself.
Let's start with the easy one.
You might already know you can
increase the specificity of a
class selector by chaining it
to itself.
You can even use CSS nesting to
chain ampersands, this can
be pretty useful when you need
it, but only increases the
middle portion of the
specificity.
Now, this next part might kind
of blow your mind, but you can
use the is
pseudo class to make a huge
jump in specificity.
This is pseudo class, it's
interesting, lets you group
multiple selectors into a
select
single selector, but changes
the specificity of the whole
thing so only the strongest
selector in the group counts.
What this means is, you can
have a class selector act
like it has the specificity of
the ID selector.
And this ID selector doesn't
need to exist. It can just be
there hanging by itself.
You can do the same thing even
easier using the not pseudo
class. So this one requires you
to use
the impossible selector where
you can use
two IDs because, remember, an
element can only have one ID.
So this selector would never
match, and we're saying,
never not match this selector.
So this will match the thing
you chain it to. I love this
because you can chain it to
anything to scope it down, just
how much you want while
retaining the super high
specificity .
And if you chain it to the
universal selector, it'll match
everything by having the high
specificity that we want. You
shouldn't need this very often.
But it's so handy when you just
want to have certain styles,
have the highest priority.
So with that out of the way,
let's talk about decreasing
specificity.
We know how to increase it, how
do we decrease it? Because
that's kind of the goal, right?
We want to keep specificity
low, at least that's what
everybody tells us . So that's
where the rare pseudo class
comes in .
There is except it doesn't add
to the specificity.
We can put an ID selector in
there, and it'll have zero
specificity.
And just like is, you can chain
it to other selectors
. So you can have some parts
inside that don't count towards
the specificity, but the things
outside
do count.
There's one restriction
here you can't put a pseudo
element selector inside, but
that's just a thing that you'll
get used to. But yeah, in other
words, we now have a CSS
native way of writing any kind
of selector you want with just
the right amount of
specificity. That's awesome.
CSS is awesome.
The most obvious way to use
where is when you want to
create select this for CSS
preset. This kind of makes
sense.
You want the reset to have the
lowest cascade priority. You
put everything in where.
And I built my own reset that
uses this technique . And you
can find it on NPM under
the end cap name space.
With where, you can make zero
specificity, but many don't do
that.
I would actually suggest coming
up with a desire specificity
for all of your other styles.
So you might want your global
style to be no higher than
0,0,1. And you can still use
longer selectors there,
like restricting the
specificity . And yeah, you can
--
the point here is you can kind
of
just control the specificity
while not having restrictions
on how you're writing your CSS.
One thing I like to do is,
like, put everything that is
nested inside the main rule .
Put where so that the whole
block has a flat specificity,
and everything inside it has
zero specificity.
So you're like going top to
down, everything is like using
source order or order of
appearance and, like,
everything inside is flat.
So you have some specificity,
but just not too much
. So yeah, if you haven't use
d where, give it a shot, it'll
solve your headaches and it's
back all the way back to Safari
14 . Ask And that brings us to
my favorite topic, controlling
the cascade using layers.
If you have a CSS rule, you can
wrap it in a layer, an
anonymous layer, and you can
give it a name, and you can put
other styles in it, too.
So far, so good. But the
interesting part is when you
use multiple layer statements
and
put different -- or multiple
layer blocks and put different
styles in them.
So here, the second layer will
always be the first layer.
It's kind of like order of
appearance, but without
specificity part.
So here in the second layer,
we're using
where pseudo class, but the
first one still wins. Or
actually, I misspoke.
So in the second one, we're
using the
pseudo class with a lower
specificity but still wins
because it's in a layer that
comes later.
So the layer order is kind of
resolved in the way in the
order that is defined.
And then, there's on layer
styles which always have the
highest priority. It'll win
over all layer styles.
This might not feel intuitive,
but it kind of makes sense.
You'll get used to it.
The way I think about it, you
want to start with you lower
priority
layer so you can put your CSS
reset in a layer and leave
everything else unlayered.
This kind of allows you to
slowly add layers to your
codebase . Yeah, that's
kind of my introduction to
layer. I still have some time
so I'm going to dive a little
bit deeper. I mentioned layer
order.
It's the layers are prioritized
in the order that they first
appear . So if you have layer A
and layer B and
write layer A, again, the rules
inside the second appearance of
layer A will still lose to
layer B . The layer A was
already defined all the way up
there. To make this more
predictable, you can separate
layer statements from layer
blocks.
The layer statement will define
the order and the layer blocks
will contain the actual rules.
And you probably want to define
the layer order up front
because all of your other
styles or before all of your
other styles.
You can put the layer
statements in the
beginning of your first style
sheet, but what I like to do is
put it in style tag, and put
the style tag all the way up in
the head.
Because I don't trust
bundlers to put my first style
sheet in the correct place. So
I just like doing it myself
before any
other style sheets are linked.
So, yeah. Let's go even deeper.
So we can nest layers, this
functionality is built into
layers. So it's separate from
CSS nesting. You can nest
layers without using CSS
nesting.
And if you only want to
reference a nested
sublayer, you can use the dot
syntax.
But it gets even more
interesting when you do use CSS
nesting, because you can put a
layer block inside another
CSS rule, like a class
selector. You want to style
different parts of the same
component using different
layers.
I want to point out that this
is a CSS nesting is a
relatively new feature, so you
might want to use preprocessors
, SaaS to trans
get this part out for you. I
find this useful especially
when different part of the
components need to have
different priorities. For
example, I might have overrides
as a sublayer where I put
my scaler styles and print
styles.
These should always be all of
the other styles of the
component.
Moving on to layer strengths
and the idea of style sheets.
You can reference the same
layer name in multiple CSS
files and they'll work just
like you expect regardless of
how they're imported.
So you might have a giant
components layer that is
referenced in every single one
of your components and within
single file components,
in Vue or Astro, you can import
into a layer.
The external CSS pod doesn't
need to contain any layers. And
I want to give a shout out to
CSS
import here, it can transform
the import statements to
layer block statements and
inline all of the contents of
the style sheet and even works
for remote URLs.
This is great for performance,
mainly.
And I want to talk about SAUTSZ
SaaS real quick.
Layers were just like you
expect in SaaS, but when you
want to combine multiple SaaS
files into a single layer, you
need
to use metaupload CSS, you
can't use the use statement.
This was a recent update made
to SaaS to ensure that meta.
load CSS is a canonical way to
use layers in SaaS.
And finally, the most important
slide, you might have used
the important keyword to win
specificity battles in the
past. But we all know it's a
shameful hack and the general
advice is to
avoid important. And earlier, I
already showed various ways
to increase specificity. So if
you want to just win a
specificity battle, then
use one of those techniques
instead of important.
But the reason why important is
interesting here is emerges
kind of differently in layers.
The important keyword is more
important when used in lower
priority layers.
This feels strange, but I think
Miriam was explaining earlier
that
user agents and preferences
might declare some styles that
are legitimately important.
So even though all of the other
user styles are less important,
they want to say this
particular thing should be more
important . So works similarly
in layers.
So CSS reset, you might have a
rule that says,
may not be important if the
dialog is not open.
This helps ensure that
subsequent layers can't
accidentally override the
display when it's always meant
to be hidden
. I've done that accidentally
so many times where I set a
display grid
on the dialog and it shows when
it's not supposed to be
showing. So now I handle that
in my reset.
If you take everything we've
seen about layers so far, our
cascade
overlooks something like the
user styles and the page styles
and the Shadow DOM styles ask
and and unlayered styles and
the important styles come after
all of that.
And since I'm running out of
time, I won't go into too much
detail here, but important
style also have their own
quirks. In that, the user agent
important
styles are more important than
inline style attributes, for
example.
But yeah, I'm going to talk
about browser support real
quick. Browser, I think, 2022,
February, is when all browsers
shipped cascade layers. It was
a coordinated rollout and very
impressive to watch.
But if that still makes you
uneasy, there's post cascade
layers, which polyfills
everything
we've talked about so far.
And then, there's revert layer,
I haven't talked about it so
far because it's such
a broad topic. You might not
want to use it yet.
I have a blog post on this
topic.
And the only part I want to
mention just right now is that
if you're trying to use revert,
consider
revert layer instead. It works
even when you don't use cascade
layers.
Then, there's some best
practices. I think I'll skip
that.
Slides are stuck.
Oh, no, OK, sure.
There was an iframe here where
I was going to show that layers
and scope are different.
This is a CSS tricks article
written by Miriam Suzanne.
And yeah, I really want to
emphasize this point is that
layers and scopes are different
things.
You don't want to create a
layer for every single
component. They can overlap so
you can have layers within the
same
component or don't use it scope
your CSS.
And I think we can wrap it up
here since I ran out of time.
I just want to mention one last
thing, that I think Peter
Griffin would really enjoy
using cascade layers.
Yeah, that's all, if you want
to learn more, subscribe to my
RSS feed, and that's all for
me.
≫ MIKE: I just learned so much
there.
It's like a pain I didn't know
I had where I feel like in a
lot of situations I add a
lot of specificity to kind of
wrangle the browser to do what
I want
when, actually, what I want is
layers, which
not aware of at all.
Yeah. It's going to take me a
while to get my head around
that.
≫ MAYANK: Yeah.
≫ MIKE: It's a completely
different paradigm.
≫ MAYANK: The thing I tell
people is, start with just the
reset . Put that in your, in a
layer, and if you have some
third party styles, put
that in a layer, you don't have
to migrate your whole codebase
to layers right away.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
And so the advantage of doing
that is -- let's take a
really basic reset of, I'm
setting the margin of HTML
element to zero.
So that's in my reset in a lay
er.
But now, I decide I actually
want some padding on my HTML
, so then, I can have HTML and
what's a nonlayer called?
Called the root?
Or?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah. HTML and root
are going to be the same thing
to each other.
≫ MIKE: Yeah, now I can set my
padding on the HTML and
it'll just work without any
more specificity?
≫ MAYANK: Yeah, and if you wrap
it in rare to make the zero
specificity, it'll still work.
Because unlayer styles over
layer styles.
≫ MIKE: That's awesome. Very
cool.
Mayank, thanks for sharing that
today, I learned a lot. I'm
glad you're here.
≫ MAYANK: Thanks for having me.
≫ MIKE: All right.