Hey, my name's Henry,
the font's name is
Manuka, I'm a creative
technologist.
I also spent time in New York
City, based in Denver. Super
into hand crafted web code,
poetic
computation, CSS, and most
importantly for today, also,
shit posting. So thanks for
coming to the talk.
Digital frontiers,
Indie web cowboys, owning your
post with posse.
I'm super excited to get
started with this one.
We were given this vast realm
of self-discovery , philosophy
and joy and community. But most
of us spend most of our time in
the bad lands of brain rot and
attention farming and
doom scrolling and general bad
vibes.
We break our backs, the foundry
of algorithmic content as
endeavoring of our
sharing our interests corrupted
into the hollow twin of content
creation, to trap attention
spans, list
the thread emoji digital dams
to harvest scroll inertia.
However, it's not all bad.
There's plenty of folks who
oppose this mundane and
uninspirational for profit
corporate web, folks who
instead believe in the strange
and surprising web, hand built,
cell phone web.
The battle for the soul of the
net is fought upon three
particular
stages, well, OK, it's many
stages, but I'd love to focus
on three of them in particular.
Holy smokes, I'm killing it.
One, do you own your content?
If the companies that own the
platform
disappeared tomorrow or
devoured by the board
millionaire, would your content
have somewhere to live or also
vanish ? Two, can your content
go anywhere it wants?
If I want to find your posts,
do I need to go to a specific
platform? Or can I find and
reply to and share and
be delayed by those posts or
that content wherever
it prefers to dwell, wherever I
prefer to dwell, rather ?
Three, are you in control?
Can you post anything you want
or does someone decide, for
instance, that you have a
limited number of characters or
you can only post images as a
certain resolution
? What good is a banger shit
post, Mr. Anderson if you can't
pair it with a gif?
Those are familiar with what
the heck I'm talking about will
recognize these as some of the
core tenets of the IND
Indie web movement.
You own your demand and can
verify and identify yourself
across the web, owning your
content, and the specific
subject of today's talk,
publishing on your own site
first.
So POSSE, or publish on your
own site syndicate elsewhere,
is the idea that for example,
if I've got a banger
shit post and I often do, I can
create that post on my website,
write some software to reformat
and propagate it to other
common places of conversation,
such as
Mastodon or Blue Sky, no other
places.
And use additional tools and
standards to make the post and
the inevitable content
surrounding it because I said
it was a banger, serialized and
read by anyone in any arena,
always
linking back to the home URL
post, which by the way, will
never change .
I'll get a little more in-depth
on this, but right off the rip,
this solves everything.
I own it, syndicating to RSS
and social media that make my
posts are good or worthwhile,
which is everyone, engage with
them in the preferred format
and back feeding
the conversation that's
happening in all of those
places to my website collects
all of the great conversation
and engagement in one place.
And there's more wins to be
had.
Storing bangers canonically
allows you to be a better
steward of the web because you
can prevent link rot, thanks,
Twitter, and then, search
engines will learn to prefer
your site and search results if
they continue following links
back to your site .
So, I can see by your
individual faces, which
I can see that everyone's on
board with the strategy for
posting online.
In the rest of this talk, I'll
briefly cover a light technical
implementation of POSSE.
If you're feeling stoked on a
content syndication strategy
but not ready to take the leap,
you do have options.
Such as COPE. So briefly some
alternative strategies are
COPE, create once, publish
everywhere. It's the default
strategy.
The problem with posting the
same content everywhere, at
best, you're growing X number
of audiences on disparate
folks' sites, fractured digital
identity, there's
pesos, publish elsewhere and
syndicate on your own site.
There's actually room for PESOS
as an are archival sense.
Publishers, the Tweetback
project allows you to collect
historical posts from the
fractured identities and give
them a nice forever home
somewhere with a nice lawn,
careful,
he's a rescue. Also publish
elsewhere syndicate everything
to a silo.
Not because it's a good
strategy but because the
Indie web folks love a fuckin
algorithm, and you've got to
love them for it. I'm going to
sprint through building an
application that creates and
reads content.
P
We're going to make an app that
syndicates, capturing
engagement on
sites and rendering the
conversation back on our site .
Before I get into this, many
extremely bright people have
gone here before, many of them
aren't speaking today.
I admire all of these people
massively. This would not be
possible without their talks
and blog posts and their work.
There's a bibliography for this
talk, it's coming, I'll make it
available after I shut the hell
up.
Oh, yeah, and the other thing,
I meant to use this talk as an
excuse to rework the publishing
strategy on my actual personal
site, but as
I'm sure many of you can relate
to, I'm still redesigning it.
That's showbiz, baby, instead ,
we're going to create a
distinct and memorable
domain and that's showbiz,
baby,
or showbiz. baby. Don't worry
about the specific code. It's
an 11-minute talk.
I'm going to make everything
available after I get off
stage.
We'll start by creating an 11ty
project with two templates. One
that lists all of the bangers
and one that
creates individual permalinks
for the bangers. You might be
able to see in the market, if
you can see that, that I'm
using a format called Hcard as
part of microformats 2, which
is
a system of classes that we add
to the HTML to make our
information structured and
easily parsed by like crawlers
that come to look.
This is useful because we can
indicate who wrote the bangers
and what the useful parts of
each banger are.
Yeah, microformats  2, I got
off sync with the tabs.
All of this stuff is like super
well documented online.
It's a little bit wild west.
On the topic of
aweuthentication. We use the
domain as identity and use it
to
verify other instances of our
identity. Since my website and
GitHub account are both me, I
can verify those two identities
by linking to my GitHub account
from my
site and linking back to my
site from my GitHub account
useing realm A links .
This is the basis for Indie web
authentication
. Since I'm the only person
that can edit my website and
GitHub account, it's reasonable
to assume that both of those
sources are me.
Once we've verified and back
linked ourselves different
places online, we
can use a service called
Indie auth that can handle
authentication and web mentions
and add a few lines of code to
the head of our
site to tell the services that
they can go to Indie auth to
verify us.
Also, oh, there's like -- this
is off script.
There are some serious power
houses of the Indieweb in the
chat right now.
If I'm getting anything wrong,
feel free to rip me apart.
I specifically used GitHub in
the realm example because they
have a sign-in example that
Indie will coopt so you can
sign in securely as GitHub and
verify that I am my GitHub
account and by extension, also
my website.
But great, so now we've got a
website that verifies our
identity using
Indieauth and capable of
telling other services how to
authenticationuthenticate us.
Through publishing, it's 11ty,
we could create markdown files
by hand, but it's still really
nice, turns out, to go to a
website and click post. There's
nothing that clears the ass
of sending the Tweet. In this
case, I'm using Erin
Pereki's micropublish er
er Quill. This will feel like
magic the first time you do it.
We're going to grab a token and
proceed with our micropub end
point that Quill will speak to.
So I'm basically, we need to
accept publish requests from
Quill and convert them into
files that 11ty can build. I'm
going to create, I'm using
Netlify functions for this
because it's what I know .
Create a file function/micropub
and add the
corresponding endpoint to the
head on our in dex.
HTML, go to this end point to
make publish requests.
Also, I'll be using GitHub's
octokit tool to converting into
flat files in the GitHub repo.
We can grab a quick token from
there, as well. And we can
throw all of the tokens into a
.
end file and make them
available, but not public in
your environment. And then, we
can use them in the micropub
function.
Here's the function.
This borrows heavily from
Robert's tutorial publishing VI
writer. Here's the general
vibe. One, listen for post
requests and check their
veritoken matches the one from
Quill,
publish the content and
template them in a way that
11ty can work with. I made
markdown files with a timestamp
in the front matter.
And then, commit both the newly
created file to
GitHub and then, also, like a
-- some way to let -- like
basically a JSON file that
contains the most recently
posted post. I'll use it later.
But once that function's
deployed, we can sign into
Quill with our website, feels
amazing, make a post, and then,
watch
it magically appear on our site
pending a build set. Publishing
sorted.
Next, we've got to talk about
web mentions. This is the
conversation aspects.
From the Indieweb Wiki, it's a
super powerful protocol.
It lets us like, you know,
lightweight way and
standardized way tell our
friends and colleagues that
we're referencing their blogs,
et cetera, and lets us know
when folks are referencing or
talking about our work.
There's another service called
Webmention.
io, lets us read web mentions
from all over the web . We'll
sign up using the same
Indieauth steps as Quill, add
the mention endpoint to the
head. If it's feeling
repetitive, we're establishing
patterns, baby, and throw the
API key on our . end for later.
We can get web mentions from
other blogs, et cetera, just
like right off the rip.
But because this talk is
particularly concerned with
posting bangers, we need to
work out some way to collect
and share conversations, likes
B,
and replies, et cetera, from
social media . A free service
that does exactly that.
Con VRTs engagement into web
mentions.
Collecting engagement on the
other sites, et cetera, and
then, also to indicate and
create posts we can track
web mentions on that was the
like publish on our own site,
bridgy does that.
So, OK, once a post is created
and published on our own site,
we need to do the syndicate
elsewhere part.
I'm going to use another
Netlify function, it's what I
know. If you're an API genius
and want to do this a different
way, you can . The world is
your oyster.
Here's the function.
Again, TLDR, 11-minute talk, by
the way. We're going to grab
the last published note.
I stored it in the JSON file
like I said.
Ping Bridgy with a request to
publish to Mastodon and this
most recent post .
And that's literally it.
It'll just like Bridgy will
automatically post our posts ,
I've got -- somebody should've
proofread
this script, bro, holy smokes,
to Mastodon and
it's like four lines of code
like blue sky, other
syndication targets, whatever
you want.
So our flow is now completely
automated from I thought of a
genius post and I posted it via
Quill to having it published
on our personal site and copy
out to Mastodon, to whatever,
with a link back to our
original site.
So, on to the final step here.
Oh, crap, I've gone a little
bit over. I'm sorry.
Really cool now, the
conversations from all of these
different sources are collected
as web mentions.
So we can show all of those
conversations from the
bluebird, the butterfly, the
elephant, in one place.
So folks don't have to miss out
on a reply because
they prefer Blue Sky, they can
click back and read everything .
It's pretty easy to use 11ty
data files, run me the check,
Zach, to collect
web mentions as JSON from the
web mention API that I
mentioned earlier . And then
render them into templates,
Maxbook has a fantastic
tutorial on this . This borrows
from that heavily, obviously.
And I've included
implementation of that in the
GitHub repo, again, available
after the talk.
But that's it. Like, after
maybe two hours of work, you're
owning all of your content,
you're divested from the whims
of social media silos and sicko
owners and made the web more
kind.
There's a million enhancements
that can be made to this. You
can follow Cy Sia
's amazing guide, you could add
media endpoint in case you want
to post gifs, use microformats
to let folks find
a post from your site back on
to the silo, if you want.
All the code for today will be
examinable, like, under the
microscope, whatever, online,
on my personal website, Henry.
codes in the next couple of
days. Oh, I didn't mean to
leave that in there.
Oh, yeah, no, sorry, first big
talk, bear with me. And then,
yeah, thanks for listening
today. Thank you for 11ty for
having me and all of these
other amazing speakers.
I'm literally so honored to be
sharing the estage to these
people.
I've been looking up to y'all
since I was a wee child.
Last minute plug, if you 11ty
sickos love personal websites,
visit us at
personalsite. es and share
yours.
You can filter by RSS feed, you
can do whatever you want . Find
me somewhere JAUP line, Free
Palestine, thanks so much.
≫ MIKE: Thank you so much. That
was amazing.
Those principles of the
Indieweb are so important
as we've seen in the past
decade play out.
We really are the ones that
need to push these ideas and
, as you showed, like 11ty's a
great tool to kind
of be at the core of that
publishing platform.
≫ HENRY: Yeah, and it's a
stronger and stronger strategy.
≫ MIKE: We're going to move on
to our next speaker, thanks,
again, Henry.
≫ HENRY: Thank you so much.