The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, is
located in the Southeast corner
of the state 12 miles north of
the Ohio River, nestled
to woods, next to a
breathtaking waterfall, a
monument of battalion of
British soldiers and the
remains of a French settlement
that disappeared a hundred
years before that.
The quaint downtown of question
mark features a beautiful town
hall
rebuilt three times after fires
destroyed the previous two, a
magnificent library, and a
clock tower that stopped
working in the 1960s .
These were all built from the
fortunes of the Wylie Family,
town founders and creators of
the Wiley Safety
Envelope now in the cemetery at
the northwest corner of town
. The drive-in theater, bowling
alley, convenience store, two
cults, four murders, and seven
mysterious voids that sit at
the spiralling center of a
series of mysteries that have
beset the town over the last
year.
The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, doesn't exist.
It's a creation of myself and
the novelist Joe Meno, launched
in April of last year and
has unfolded on a near daily
basis in the year since.
It wraps, actually, in the next
couple of weeks . The story of
Question Mark has been told
across the internet.
On Instagram, Twitter threads,
The town of Question Mark,
Ohio, doesn't exist. It's a
creation of myself and the
novelist Joe Meno, launched in
April of last year and has
unfolded on a near daily basis
in the year since.
It wraps, actually, in the next
couple of weeks. The story of
Question Mark has been told
across the internet. On
Instagram, Twitter threads,
over email, on the phone, and
most immersively, on the web,
where it's unfolded across a
sprawling collection of
websites, over 40 in all , that
have played out like chapters
in a novel, advancing the main
story while also telling their
own at the same time.
There's no template for what
we're doing. I mean that in
terms of the fact that nobody
has told the story like this
for this long in realtime
across so many different
spaces. But I also mean it
literally.
Each site is built from
scratch.
There's no cookie cutter
approach to any of it because
each site is unique, each plays
a singular role in the story
and each site also has to stand
alone as something real and
believable.
Something that's marked with
the
age and ewe till I
utility of a work a day
website. John colton who wrote
a song for the story said we
were
building things as much
artifact as they were art.
That's exactly right.
Everything we made in Question
Mark needed to feel lived in
and real.
In that way, each site is a
puzzle, a puzzle for the
audience to solve, but also, a
puzzle for Joe and I as the
creators. How to make it work,
how to tell the right story,
how to make
it happen across multiple
screen sizes, and how to do it
in a turnaround time measured
in days or sometimes even
hours.
The key was to keep things
simple.
Each site was static, either
straight HTML, manually
deployed on Netlify, or when a
site required a
more complicated structure like
the newspaper with over 150
stories that span 90 years of
the town's history, that's
where 11ty came in.
Beyond that, all of our styles,
we're using tail
wind CSS, most interactions
were built with Alpine jsx, I
needed everything in a single
index
file because keeping track of
anything else was near
impossible.
While keeping it simple was
crucial to the endeavor, the
reality is a lot of what we did
with Question Mark, we couldn't
have pulled off a year ago.
We ended up leaning on
generative AI tools for imagery
more than we thought. And some
of the writing and coding.
In pushing them to see what was
possible with the tools
, I actually learned pretty
clearly they're just like any
other. And skilled hands, you
can do pretty incredible
things.
Of course, they are not perfect
in many, many ways, but for two
people with no budget to
imagine a world in near
realtime, it was liberating.
We used all of this, old
school, HTML, new school large
language models in service of
story.
The story of Violet
Bookman, a 17-year-old trying
to find her neighbor's cat Mr.
Business.
As readers, that's where we
meet her and we follow her
adventures through town. We
help her to solve mysteries and
find allies, even as the story
grows bigger and darker than a
missing cat.
But the real story of Question
Mark is one of grief, of
wishing you could return to a
past that felt better, felt
more whole, but realize
ing that to grieve is really to
move forward in spite of
everything.
That pattern, this is what the
story's about, and this is what
it's really about
. How we approached every site
that we built.
There was the garbage dump, one
of the more complicated and
janky builds that let readers
dig through hundreds of items
of trash to uncover a long
buried container of
toxic sludge. But really, the
dump was the story the town's
long time
mayor finally coming to terms
with the scale of her dead
husband's corruption.
There was the experimental crop
stations
online course catalog, where
you could actually take an
entire course on experimental
biology if you wanted to, but
the real goal was to take and
fail the employee security exam
in order to free
the sentient bean made of light
known as queuey.
There was the Question Mark
motel, which isn't coming up in
my slides. There it is.
The Question Mark Motel, which
actually advanced four
different stories on a single
page. Giving readers back story
on a number of different
characters simply by clicking
on the room. But really, it was
the story of one room.
Room O, and the cult that had
taken up residence there. And
their plan to commit a murder
on the eclipse. And then, there
was Bookman's music.
The music store run by Violet
Bookman's father . We knew we
wanted to bring readers into
the store
the same way we brought readers
into the ice cream shop, the
chicken joint and the pet shop
and many other locations in
town.
We also wanted to reveal a fun
detail about
Todd Bookman, he was in a one
hit wonder band
called Matrix who charted with
their song called ticking away.
Jonathan Colton wrote and
recorded that song for us.
What was the site really about?
It was about a way to explore
the distance between
Violet and her father that
emerged in the shadow
of the death of her mother four
years ago.
We hid that story throughout
the site and encouraged people
to interact and explore. Fill
out the form for music lessons,
and you
get an entry from Violet's
journals. Start inquiring about
instruments, and you'd get
another
entry delivered line by line.
You learn how distant she and
her dad have become.
She writes, maybe I'm just
afraid to have a relationship
with him because that would
mean admitting my mom isn't
ever coming back. On the about
page, we
reversed that point of view and
hear from Violet's father.
Click on the images of his late
wife and Violet as a child, and
you learn how he's been dealing
with the death.
I know I've been distant, he
writes, but I know both of
us needed to find answers in
our own way. I know I've been
afraid to talk about the pain
both of us are dealing with and
I know in just a few months,
she's going to be leaving for
college.
The Bookmans' music site came
together in two days. We
started with the story and all
grew from there.
It launched and we were already
on to the next chapter.
There are dozens of examples
like this. Because nothing in
Question Mark is what it
appears.
Almost everything has a deeper
connection to the story or to
the characters or to the theme
of loss and grief.
I have made a lot of websites
in the last year, and I will be
honest with you, I code with a
cat caught in a paper
bag. I am not here to tell you
about web standards or creating
elegant, efficient code, lift
the hood on any of these sites
that I've made, and they are a
horror show, but that is OK.
Because every site worked for
what it needed to be. A small
part in a larger whole.
Sure, they were janky as hell,
but they were sites that
thousands of people wanted to
go to and engage
in. They definitely did not a
adhere to best
practices, but instead, they
offered a doorway into a world
that people wanted to live
inside.
I love this post from one of
the folks on
the Discord server dead dicated
to unraveling the mysteries.
I struggle to make my brain
understand that I can't get on
a plane, go over there and sort
it all out myself, it's so real
to me.
This should be the aim of
anything that you build .
Create something that feels so
real
that someone has to struggle to
remember that it isn't.
That is making a website or 40
of them real good.
It doesn't matter if you've got
the latest skills or if you
know the cutting edge approach
to building or the right
framework or whatever. I had
none hof that when I started,
and I still do not a year
later.
Instead, have something to say.
Figure out the best possible
way to say it. The rest will
follow.
Every day Joe and I got to sit
down and ask ourselves
what's the story we want to
tell? And how can we build
something amazing to tell it?
And then we'd ask, what's the
real story we're telling? And
how does this artifact we've
created service that?
There's that pattern, again,
right? What's the story? What's
the real story?
And that's true with this talk,
too
. Because, yes, this talk is
about the work and love and
care that went into building
ing Question Mark for the last
year. But what it's really
about is this.
The web is still magical.
It's still a place where you
can build everything you want,
even a whole town.
There's no permission to get,
no hoops to jump through, no
risk of a platform shutting you
down, you don't
need fancy tools or a big team,
you just need your imagination,
a text file, a doc type HTML
tag and the whole world is
there for you to make.
It doesn't matter if it's
imperfect,
doesn't matter if the edges are
rough. Rough edges are just our
humanity showing through.
When people wax nostalgic for
the web, for the hamster dance
or MySpace profiles, what
they're nostalgic for is the
web
before it got all sanded down.
They're nostalgic for a web
that could give you splinters,
for a web with rough edges. For
a web that was more human.
But the story of Question Mark,
the real story is that you
can't move backwards .
That the past is the past, and
attempting to return to it
never works. And that's OK.
Because we don't have to.
The tools to make a web that's
more human,
more magical, more amazing are
not the tools of the past but
the tools of right now.
There's never been a better
time to make something,
anything, on the web.
You can build a world, tell a
story, make things happen big
and small, the web is still
vital, it's still exciting, and
the rules are there for the
breaking.
Thank you so much.
≫ MIKE: So cool.
I've never seen anything like
that. That was incredible.
≫ DAN: Neither have I, and I
made it.
≫ MIKE: Yeah.
So -- how did this start? Why
did you decide this platform
?
≫ DAN: So, I have worked with
Joe
for many years on and off. He
worked with me on the magazine
Punk Planet, I put out a couple
of books of his. But we have
not collaborated in probably 15
years.
And we went on a walk on a warm
November, and he was like,
I have this idea for a novel,
but I don't want to make it as
a book.
Kind of want it to exist on the
internet. And I was like, just
stop, let's do it.
And then, we figured it out
from there. You know.
We did not know what we were
getting into when we got into
it . But it's been a ride.
≫ MIKE: Is it a sequential
story? How do I navigate
between the parts of the story?
≫ DAN: So there are sort of
three main channels that the
story's told in.
One is Violet Bookman's
Instagram
account @violet bookman, I
don't remember it right now.
And then, there's the town
website, which is questionmark.
town, and the town
announcements that are
published from there, there
have been about 170, 180 town
announcements at this point.
Those are almost always the way
you branch into different
websites.
There's also the kind of sad
dad cop in town Ron
Deblosky who you can follow on
threads now, he was on Twitter,
but why would he still be
there?
And then, there's a mailing
list you can subscribe to, but
the
best way to get into it,
actually, is questionmark Ohio.
com, where we are breaking it
down week by week as
episodes, there are 42 episodes
you can read summaries for with
all of the links there.
≫ MIKE: Very cool. Thanks for
joining, Dan, it's a
fascinating project .
≫ DAN: Thanks for having me.
See you on the web.