≫ DAVID: Fantastic, thank you
Liam and I both work at CloudCannon
CloudCannon is a visual CMS for
11ty and for other SSGs,
and broadly speaking
we focus on two
things, we want to make it
easier
for everyone to manage the
content, and the visual
interface, and on creating and
supporting open source
SSG, agnostic tooling
. It's important for us that
there's absolutely no vendor
locking in CloudCannon, we
think your site, your source,
and your content should be
yours and stored in your Git
repo. You can take it when you
want to, it's fully portable.
Today, we're joining forces to
talk about how CloudCannon
has a feature called site
mounting that can combine with
a new open source tool that
creates a static API.
And that's aimed at allowing
large organizations to receive
the same benefits of static
sites and CMS as smaller single
site orgs.
So site mounting. Site mounting
allows multiple sites to sync
to one build image
on CloudCannon. You might have
seen this in action on 11ty
already
. Zach made a video about it
when the feature first launched
last year.
But today, in addition to
shearing components and layup
files on sites, we're going to
demonstrate a data link and
group of connected sites 11ty
sites , enabling content
syndication and
aggregation, new tool
flatlink.
≫ LIAM: Flatlake is tool we're
developing similar to the way
the static site generator spits
out static HTML files that can
be used as a website, Flat
lake spits out JSON files that
can be query . We'll show how
to aggregate and share content
between stand alone 11ty sites.
≫ DAVID: Let's imagine we're
tasked with building several
real good websites for quite a
large organization.
We're going to demo four
smaller sites connected to one
larger parent site, but there's
no technical limit. We'll call
out the larger site real big
company. You can check it out
if you like Real Big.
company, look at the GitHub,
it's all connected.
We love static sites, we love
flat files, we love 11ty.
And our smaller sites static
laboratories, 11ty
incorporated, and
liminal interfaces. It's very
unbrand.
You can imagine a large
corporation or university,
perhaps, needing a setup like
this.
They may or may not be
technical, they'll be managing
several hundred sites. So, I
can jump into this right now,
I'm editing on CloudCannon,
this is an 11ty
site I'm editing, I'm marking
down live in the visual.
It's great, right?
Really good for a single site.
I can edit everything quickly.
I can add page components that
our developer has built. But
what about a smaller site?
Had What about our smaller
sites?
If we want to jump to what the
big corporation needs, what if
they want to spin up a new
site?
They have quite a large wish
list here. How do they get
exactly the same page building
components in each site ?
What about brand recognition
for the real big corporate
family. And perhaps, more
importantly, if we update a
layout or a component, how can
it be reflected on all of our
sites?
That's a pretty decent sized
wish list. And of course, we
want this on 11ty for all of
the performance benefits of a
static site and on CloudCannon
for the benefits of visual edit
or without content stored in
Git. We can do all of this.
We can see this in action here,
this is Xity, a subsidiary of
real big company. You can see
here, our
site is retrieving the source
files from the component
library, that's the shear ed
common re
shared common repo and from the
common repo into the sites
includes layouts.
This is pretty straightforward
setup. Just an option within
CloudCannon to set up.
Here's a simplified version
where our site folder and our
conflict
tent files are sourced from the
content repo and layouts
sourced from the central repo.
And the important aspect is
that from here the 11ty
build proceeds as if all files
were arranged in one folder
originally and thus built as
one unified stacked site.
And once any files in the
common repo are changed, layout
is tweaked, perhaps, or a new
page building component is
added, any downstream link
sites have immediate access to
the new components and any
layout changes will
automatically rebuild every
affected site.
≫ LIAM: Where are we?
Now that we can share codes
between the sites in our
company, it'll be great if we
could share content, too.
So, bringing up their next wish
list, we have the content
wishlist.
So, on the main corporate
website, we want to rehost some
of the
featured news articles from
each division, plus for every
division's website, we want to
list the news articles
from every other division.
With this level of
interconnection between sites,
a typical approach would force
us to move the source of truth
for our content
out of our sites and into some
central data link.
But we don't want our team to
have to edit a data lake
directly, we want them to edit
their site in context.
To achieve that, we're going to
show how Flatlake and
site mounting work together to
create a static Git base data
lake, without change in
workflow for
the company. You can picture
building this with something
like site mounting on its own.
The burden of understanding all
of the source files means this
approach doesn't scale beyond a
few sites.
We're going to use Flatlake
to aggregate into a static API
and give every website access
to the data at build time.
We're going to keep the content
experience grounded in their
website, not in some giant
database.
Flatlake is driven by a single
configuration file and runs as
a stand alone command.
Our data lake repo
with just a Flatlake build
file. Looking down the file, we
see the extent of Flatlake
setup.
We define a news collection,
give it a set of inputs, one
for each division's news
folder.
We merge in some data to each
input to filter by division.
And I accidentally clicked on
the wrong thing .
[ Laughter ]
Here we are.
And -- there we go.
And -- we tell Flatlake we want
the
front data and the frontend
content to be part of the same
API . You'll notice this repo
doesn't contain the content
it's referencing. How you
achieve that depends on the
environment.
Locally, tends to use symbolic
links or Git submodules can be
good.
But for this talk, we're going
back to our good friend site
mounting. In CloudCannon, we
mount from each of the division
sites into the data lake and
hit build.
Behind the scenes, Flatlake
pulls the
markdown content files and
metadata and builds them up
into what I've been calling a
static API
. If we look at Flatlake's
output
directory, we can see a bunch
of folders containing JSON
files, files that list every
item in a given collection or
globally.
And there are files that
aggregate content on certain
data.
For example, highlighted as a
file that lists every news post
that was written by David.
Within it, we see the JSON
RENGS representation of the
content that Flatlake ingested.
The content allows you to host
them as a live API
with pagenation. And since this
is a flat folder full
of files, we can load it as
data, which we'll do for our
real big company.
So far, we've been site
mounting source files from one
site to another, which anyone
can do on CloudCannon.
To use our content as site
data, we want to output the
files . We can mount the data
files that generated into all
of
Real Big's 11ty sites. And it's
a feature of our higher tier
plans and unlocks
options for larger teams.
With the static JSON files on
disc, it's trivial to pull and
use this data.
On the main website, we're
pulling Flatlake's files adds
computer data ready to be used.
Since this glues together with
siting, you don't need to
trigger any builds.
One one of our we write a new
article,
it triggers Flatlake and
triggers every site that
consumes it to build with the
aggregated
content automatically. And a
great feature of the
syndication is it works
seamlessly
with the Git workflows. Content
only syndicates when
it lands on a main branch, and
each site can have as many
environments as they need
without leaking content.
No need to fork one giant data
lake or maintain version
content within it.
With all O that in place, plus
more liquid content
behind the scenes, we have
content syndicated and shown
across of Real Big's web
properties.
On the main corporate website,
you can list and read all
featured news articles from the
divisions.
And we made the related
articles section of each
division's website list the
latest news from all of
divisions, as well.
≫ DAVID: All of this dev work
only happens once behind the
scenes . For a team of editors,
website users and perhaps, the
nontechnical content folk, all
they need to do is
never get to the site they're
working on, choose the content
type that they're creating or
editing, and just get to work.
They have the layout and the
components already. And once
published, the content will be
syndicated to the parent site
as well as to any other sites
that mount the data lake.
It's also important to remember
that editors don't
need to wade through just to
get the content, they get it in
situ in the environment just
for them.
And that kind of sums up how a
real big company can build
real good static websites with
a great tool like 11ty. Can
share layouts across any number
of sites,
aggregate, syndicate the
content, and can keep
everything portable
with Git-based CMS, and that
means as I've said before, no
vendor locking, you always
control your
content as we think you should.
If you'd like to try any of
this out for yourself, please
have a look at CloudCannon.
com, and Zach and Mike
mentioned earlier, we have
a draw for a free migration to
CloudCannon and a bunch of
discounted plans over at
CloudCannon.
com/11tyConf. This is only open
during the conference. So you
have a couple of hours to
enter, still.
If you do miss out on those,
you can
still try out with a free trial
in one of the included
starters.
We have a new team plan we've
added for universities and
colleges who, I think, are
quite likely to find site
mounting and Flatlake a really
handy solution to manage that
standard several hundred sites.
You can also check out Flatlake
at flatlake.
app. And finally, do feel free
to take a look at Real
Big. company.
Read the content that was so
much fun to write . And check
out the files for Real
Big company if you'd like to
dig through the source there.
We're happy to answer questions
in chat after the talk or on
Mastodon, if you prefer. Thanks
very much.
≫ MIKE: Thanks, team. What a
duo.
≫ DAVID: That's great.
We're going to move on quickly,
but I want to quickly ask, what
kind of use cases do
you -- you mentioned,
universities with a lot of
different websites.
What other use cases do you
think this would be valuable
for?
≫ DAVID: I think anyone who
wants to share content to be
able to syndicate
content between sites, anyone
who wants sites to be
consistent.
It's for the users, people who
see the website, you could do
either approach
. You could have very different
websites with exactly the same
components.
I don't think there's a limit
to where this could go, really.
≫ MIKE: Very cool. Again, just
like pagefind, it's
dispelling the myth of the
limitations of static.
Now, you can have a full API of
your content to access it.
≫ DAVID: That's right, I used
to work for a university, we
had 300 sites and it was a pain
to do the content and
everything had to be manually
synced and kept perfect
separately, and
a tool like this would've saved
-- would've changed my life .